<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book SYSTEM "\\FSDEANTA\TechRelease\Accounts\Common\DeantaComposer\Publish\extra\DTD\Docbook\dtd\docbook.dtd">
<book><chapter><label>Chapter 1:</label><title>Symbolism, Myth, and the Move to Second Naïveté</title><para><emphasis role="italic">The Symbolism of Evil</emphasis> constitutes one of Ricœur’s earliest and most sustained attempts to articulate a hermeneutics that can grapple with religious texts and insights, while remaining committed to rigorous philosophical thinking.<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="1" xml:id="d1e12"><para>David Pellauer argues that this book “may conveniently be taken as a starting point for any analysis of Ricoeur’s hermeneutics.” David Pellauer, “The Significance of the Text in Paul Ricoeur’s Hermeneutic Theory,” in Reagan, <emphasis role="italic">Studies in the Philosophy of Paul Ricoeur</emphasis>, 99. Jérôme Porée also thinks of it “as the best possible entryway into the philosophy of Paul Ricoeur” and as a preview of his critical hermeneutics. Jérôme Porée, “The Question of Evil,” in <emphasis role="italic">A Companion to Ricoeur’s </emphasis>The Symbolism of Evil, ed. Scott Davidson (Lanham, MD: Lexington, 2020), 3, 4.</para></footnote> It is also famous for several notions that have become inextricably linked with Ricœur’s work, such as the proposal of the wager, the move from first to second naïveté, and his insistence on the “fullness of language” that requires an engagement with symbol, myth, and metaphor and in this way can give “rise to thought.”<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="2" xml:id="d1e14"><para>For an early discussion of Ricœur on religious symbols, see Beatriz Melano Couch, “Religious Symbols and Philosophical Reflection,” in Reagan, <emphasis role="italic">Studies in the Philosophy of Paul Ricoeur</emphasis>, 115-31. For a whole collection of essays on <emphasis role="italic">The Symbolism of Evil</emphasis>, see the just mentioned companion to the text edited by Scott Davidson. [An earlier and shorter version of the present chapter is included in that companion.] For a theological appropriation or “retrieval” of Ricœur’s symbolism of evil, see Peter B. Ely, “Revisiting Paul Ricoeur on the Symbolism of Evil: A Theological Retrieval,” <emphasis role="italic">Ultimate Reality and Meaning: Interdisciplinary Studies in the Philosophy of Understanding</emphasis> 24.1 (2001): 40-64. Ely provides a detailed summary of Ricœur’s interpretation of the Adamic myth in particular (the theological “retrieval” is confined to the last couple of pages). See also Jean Greisch, <emphasis role="italic">L’Herméneutique comme sagesse de l’incertitude</emphasis> (La Plaine Saint-Denis: Le Cercle Herméneutique Éditeur, 2015), 97-116 and idem, <emphasis role="italic">Paul Ricœur: L’itinérance du sens</emphasis> (Grenoble: Jérôme Millon, 2001), 89-141.</para></footnote> The tension between religious and philosophical language and their respective truths, which pervades Ricœur’s work (and which chapters 2 and 4 will consider more fully), is already evident in this early text. Ricœur clearly does not want to abandon central theological, biblical, or religious insights and yet is fully in agreement with scholars like Rudolf Bultmann that critical thought and commitments to truth, honesty, and academic rigor require untangling the conflation of history and myth. This chapter will highlight some of the problematic tensions in Ricœur’s account of the symbolism of evil and question whether the move to a second naïveté can really proceed as smoothly and easily as he implies in this work and whether this wager of meaning can “save” the religious truth in the way he proposes. It will suggest that mythic symbolism functions in much more complex ways than Ricœur contends and that his account would profit from an engagement with liturgical texts.</para><section role="H1"><title>Symbol, Myth, and the Fullness of Language</title><para>Ricœur proposes the exploration into the symbolism of evil with the explicit claim that symbolic and metaphorical language can offer something that propositional or philosophical language does not. Already in <emphasis role="italic">Freedom and Nature</emphasis> he had suggested that the relation between freedom and bondage might require more than a purely philosophical analysis, that it might have to have recourse to the empirical or the poetic (FN, 24). In that context, he outlines three steps for a philosophy of the will that proceeds from a strictly phenomenological (“eidetic” and “abstract”) analysis of the voluntary and the involuntary, via a more empirical account of the will and fallibility (in <emphasis role="italic">Fallible Man</emphasis>), to a poetics of the symbolism of evil. An “eidetics of the will” remains incomplete, if it is not supplemented by a “faithful description of incarnate freedom,” such as only a “poetics” can provide through an exegesis of myths and symbols (FN, 32). He argues that such symbolism and “concrete mythics” has to be explored within its “own universe of discourse” (FM, xlii), a claim he makes about religious language also in other contexts (e.g., FS, 35-47). Such figurative language is always already hermeneutic; consequently this primary symbolism can serve as “an initial step toward bringing myths nearer to philosophic discourse”; that is to say, the philosophical concept of fallibility can approach the “enigma” of the more “indirect or cyphered” religious discourse (FM, xliii). Fallibility refers to the “disproportionality” of our fragility: “Disproportion, intermediateness, fragility, fallibility, constitute a meaningful sequence” (PA, 2).<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="3" xml:id="d1e26"><para>For an analysis of Ricœur’s thought of the “fault” from <emphasis role="italic">Symbolism of Evil</emphasis> to <emphasis role="italic">Oneself as Another</emphasis>, see Guilhem Causse, “La ‘faille’ chez Paul Ricœur. De l’identité symbolique et narrative, à l’identité gestuelle et langagière,” <emphasis role="italic">Études Ricœuriennes/Ricœur Studies</emphasis> 9.2 (2018): 74-89. He argues for continuity between the two texts and interprets the fissure, gap or fault line of “faille” in terms of corporeal expression and gesture, arguing that “this fissure, this fault line, passes through the very heart of the human, but not as between two substances, but between two types of belonging, each lived as a whole, yet neither excluding the other” (75).</para></footnote></para><para>He reiterates such claims in <emphasis role="italic">The Symbolism of Evil</emphasis>. Serious thinking about the reality of evil is not reducible to purely rational statements, but requires a fuller and richer language, namely the language of symbol or myth (see also CI, 287-334). When it comes to the question of evil, rationality can be deceptive and must therefore listen “to the least elaborate, the most inarticulate confessions of evil” (SE, 4).<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="4" xml:id="d1e32"><para>In his book on Freud, Ricœur argues that “the great symbols concerning the nature and origin of evil are not simply one set of symbols out of many, but are privileged symbols.” <emphasis role="italic">Freud and Philosophy: An Essay on Interpretation</emphasis>, trans. Denis Savage (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1970), 527.</para></footnote> Myths bring us closest to “living experience” (SE, 5). This is especially true of narrations of origins, which serve to establish “all the forms of action and thought by which man understands himself in the world” (SE, 5). The function of myths is, first, to “embrace mankind as a whole in one ideal history” (SE, 162), second, to show the movement of narration as “essential history of the perdition and the salvation of man”; third, “to get at the enigma of human existence” “by means of a narration.” In this respect, the myth has “an ontological bearing” inasmuch as it connects what the human is with how humans exist historically (SE, 163). The myth, Ricœur suggests, has a heuristic and explanatory function via the symbol inasmuch as it evokes further thought and cannot be translated into purely literal language: “By its triple function of concrete universality, temporal orientation, and finally ontological exploration, the myth has a way of <emphasis role="italic">revealing</emphasis> things that is not reducible to any translation from a language in cipher to a clear language” (SE, 163; emphasis his; see also PA, 107-23, 149-75). Thus, the clarity of philosophical thinking can prove reductive and must be enlivened by the richness of symbolic and mythic language.<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="5" xml:id="d1e37"><para>Marc-Antoine Vallée says that “the phenomenological hermeneutics elaborated in <emphasis role="italic">The Symbolism of Evil</emphasis> can help us understand philosophically something meaningful about sin as a human experience of evil expressed in a biblical and theological language.” Marc-Antoine Vallée, “A Phenomenological Hermeneutics of Sin,” in Davidson, <emphasis role="italic">Companion to Symbolism of Evil</emphasis>, 38. Daniel Frey contends that Ricœur grapples with the issue of how one should “interpret symbolic-mythical discourse <emphasis role="italic">philosophically</emphasis> when one is fully aware—as too few philosophers have been!—of their specifically <emphasis role="italic">religious</emphasis> nature.” Daniel Frey, “On the Servile Will,” in Davidson, <emphasis role="italic">Companion to Symbolism of Evil</emphasis>, 59; emphases his.</para></footnote></para><para>Ricœur often stresses the proximity of such poetic language to lived existence. Symbolic language is directly linked to life, both because it is always already inscribed in speech and because it enacts language in existential living: “Symbols are already in the element of speech. ... they rescue feeling and even fear from silence and confusion; they provide a language for avowal, for confession; in virtue of them, man remains language through and through” (SE, 350). In other contexts, too, he distances himself from purely structural analyses that miss the richness and complexity of narrative and life (e.g., IT, 2-8, 80-86). This is why we must “start again from the fullness of language”; the meanings of myths and narratives are full and “pregnant” in expressing the ties between the human and the sacred (SE, 349). This may even lead us to the “hope for a re-creation of language” that would go beyond the movement of critique to a new kind of thinking (SE, 349). Thus symbolic language can “revivify” philosophy “through contact with the fundamental symbols of consciousness” (SE, 351). Symbolic thought and mythic narratives present an existential lived experience that expresses truth in fuller and more immediate language than philosophical abstraction would be able to do. It is closer to life and expresses it more authentically and with more emotional valence.</para><para>Much of the book develops these insights via a close analysis first of symbols of evil, such as defilement, sin, and guilt, and then of four myths of the origin of evil (ritual, tragic, eschatological, and gnostic), which are interpreted as giving insight about the human condition and the lived experience of evil. Ricœur is not only engaged in a general philosophical analysis of symbolism, but—in light of his earlier project on “fallible man” (in the French original printed together with <emphasis role="italic">Symbolism of Evil</emphasis> as Part I)—particularly concerned to deal with fragility, fallibility, finitude, fault, and guilt. He presents the symbol of guilt and the Adamic myth as the respective heights of the compared symbols and myths, as they gather together insights from earlier stages and express them in more sophisticated fashion. For example, while “the symbolism of sin breaks with that of defilement,” inasmuch as it is “an experience of a power that lays hold of man,” it also “rediscovers the major intention of the symbolism of defilement” (SE, 70). Similarly, the “feeling of guilt points to a more fundamental experience, the experience of ‘sin,’ which includes <emphasis role="italic">all</emphasis> men and indicates the <emphasis role="italic">real</emphasis> situation of man before God, whether man knows it or not” (SE, 7). The story of the fall and, later, the dogma of original sin both try to make sense of this primordial experience of sin. Guilt is the most fundamental experience of evil and best expressed by the myth of the fall. Thus, “the ‘Adamic’ myth is the anthropological myth <emphasis role="italic">par excellence</emphasis>; Adam means Man” (SE, 232). This narrative best encapsulates our experience of the human condition. Therefore, “we should not say, ‘The story of the ‘fall’ is <emphasis role="italic">only</emphasis> a myth’—that is to say, something less than history—but, ‘The story of the fall has the greatness of myth’—that is to say, has more meaning than a true history” (SE, 236). Ricœur tries to restore a philosophical significance to myth as a prefiguring of basic insights about the human condition, expressed in narrative and poetic form that conveys meaning in non-literal and non-historical fashion.</para><para>Throughout, he seeks to connect philosophical reflection on finitude with the experienced reality of sin and evil. Both sides have something to add to the discussion: “The hiatus between pure <emphasis role="italic">reflection</emphasis> on ‘fallibility’ and the <emphasis role="italic">confession</emphasis> of ‘sins’ is patent” (SE, 347). On the one side, philosophy proper, as committed to rationality, does not appeal to myth or symbolism, and thus cannot come to an adequate appreciation of evil in its everyday, existential reality and lived experience of being subject to passion. From the other side, religion, which is conscious of the enigma of the servile will, does not require the same methodological commitment to rational reflection. Thus, although philosophical thought is more rational, this also prevents it from a direct access to experience and a full comprehension of it, for which more mythic language is essential.</para><para>At the same time, Ricœur’s own project intends to transcend the symbolic and mythic language in favor of philosophical insight: “The failure of our undertaking challenges us to pose the more radical problem of the method of a philosophy which would learn from the symbols and yet be fully rational” (SE, 346). He is quite clear that his commitment is to philosophical thinking and that such philosophical speculation is far superior to the superstition of myth, which can no longer serve as “explanation” of reality today (SE, 5). Or, as he says in a different context: “Myth narrates, wisdom argues” (FS, 252). While the mythic narrative provides us with accounts of lived experience, here it does not itself convey truth. Rather, the kernel of truth, the logos, must be carved out of or “exorcised” from the myth (SE, 352). In fact, “the question of truth is unceasingly eluded” in the symbol (SE, 353). Symbols just point to further symbols; while they can “give rise to thought,” the thought or reflection itself is a separate endeavor.</para><para>Truth for Ricœur, at least in this context, thus lies with the historical and philosophical, not the symbolic or mythical. While they can instruct us about primordial human experience, they are ultimately no longer meaningful or truthful today. Although myths may give us access to a living experience of defilement, sin, and guilt, the myths themselves are no longer convincing to us (SE, 161). We must investigate the fullness of language in the myth in order to be able to “think” the symbols, but then demythologize, i.e. strip the concepts of their mythic trapping and re-enact the experience in “sympathetic imagination,”<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="6" xml:id="d1e69"><para>The expression “sympathetic imagination” exists only in the English translation; the original French literally says “in sympathy and imagination,” a phrase Ricœur used extensively throughout his work. See the chapter on the imagination below.</para></footnote> not to get back to the myth, but to recapture the more primordial truth conveyed through the symbols. The embrace of symbol and myth, then, is only temporary and has to be superseded by philosophical analysis. It provides the rich data, which philosophy can then mine, but is itself without truth and ultimately no longer believable, but something to be discarded once its kernel of meaning has been extracted. Although Ricœur judges the “detour” through symbolic and mythical language useful and enriching, maybe even necessary, he ultimately rejects such “primitive” language in favor of more strictly philosophical thought.</para><para>Here Ricœur seems to compromise his own earlier insights. Why should we listen to the “fullness of language” if in the end it turns out to be superstitious and no longer believable today? What has the myth added to our philosophical analysis if it is ultimately superseded and even replaced by it? Can a philosophical truth be carved out from the complexity of the myth, the symbolism cleansed of its superstitious trappings, and the kernels recovered in a second naïveté? Does that not close down or at least compromise the fullness of language of the myth? What has the detour taught us if it must finally be abandoned? Can the meanings of symbols be recovered today if they are no longer permitted to take on mythic or narrative garb?</para><para>Part of the problem is that there is a slippage in Ricœur’s account between the “primordial” and the “primitive.” While the primordial is taken to be instructive and worth exploring, the primitive is dismissed as simplistic and superseded or even invalidated by critical thought. On the one hand, Ricœur often insists that a return to the primordial is profitable and that we should not rush too quickly to complicated philosophical or theological speculation. Both in the <emphasis role="italic">Symbolism of Evil</emphasis> and in other articles he refuses to engage the Augustinian doctrine of original sin in favor of more primordial symbols of evil (e.g. SE, 4; FS, 249-61<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="7" xml:id="d1e78"><para>A slightly longer version of this piece was also published in English separately as <emphasis role="italic">Evil: A Challenge to Philosophy and Theology</emphasis>, trans. John Bowden (London: Continuum, 2007). In this piece Ricœur first discusses the relation between suffering, pain, and evil (an even much more obvious connection in French, which employs the same word <emphasis role="italic">le mal</emphasis> for both pain and evil), then considers various historical answers—beginning with myth and ending with theodicy—and concludes with a reflection on acting and feeling that acknowledges that the problem does not simply consist in thinking.</para></footnote>; for one exception see CI, 269-86). He consistently takes the biblical texts as the most primordial expressions of Christian (and occasionally Jewish) faith (FS, 35-47) and expends much energy interpreting them—far more than theological doctrines or speculative ideas. Going back to such primordial symbols allows the philosopher to “elaborate existential concepts” (SE, 356). The symbolic and mythical language has access to originary experience in a way speculative thought does not. Ricœur also often refers to goodness as more “primordial” than evil in a way that clearly implies it to be superior to, better than, and ultimately more powerful than evil (SE, 156; FS, 203-16; RB, 27-40).<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="8" xml:id="d1e80"><para>Indeed, Olivier Mongin considers this the central unifying theme in Ricœur’s work: <emphasis role="italic">Paul Ricœur</emphasis> (Paris: Éditions du Seuil, 1998), 248-49.</para></footnote></para><para>At the same time he argues that this primordial symbolic language is a first and immediate stage that can later give rise to more “abstract” language or speculation, in a way that suggests a linear progression of increasing sophistication: “There is something quite astonishing in this: the consciousness of self seems to constitute itself at its lowest level by means of symbolism and to work out an abstract language only subsequently, by means of a spontaneous hermeneutics of its primary symbols” (SE, 9). He outlines three separate stages, where myth and philosophy both go beyond but draw inspiration from the primary symbols. The primary symbols come first, followed by myth as a second level, and resulting in gnosis or reflection on the third level. The interpretation of the second and third levels relies on the first, especially in regard to confessing fault and fallibility (SE, 9). Indeed, Ricœur often distinguishes these three levels in mythical and symbolic language about fallenness—“first that of the primordial symbols of sin, then that of the Adamic myth, and finally the speculative cipher of original sin”—referring to “the second as first-degree hermeneutics, the third as second-degree hermeneutics” (SE, 237). He thus posits a fairly linear move from inchoate symbol to narrative myth to explicit articulation of doctrine.</para><para>Ricœur acknowledges that interpretation is always already at work at all of these levels, with the possible exception of the primordial symbol itself, which he tends to interpret as immediate. But there is interpretation already at the level of the myth: “The myth anticipates speculation only because it is already an interpretation, a hermeneutics of the primordial symbols in which the prior consciousness of sin gave itself form. That it gives rise, in its turn, to thought is a consequence of the fact that it itself interprets other symbols” (SE, 237). A hermeneutic process enables us to “re-enact” the myth in “sympathetic imagination” and thus to recognize the movement from primary symbols to secondary mythic language and the tertiary doctrines that might be built upon the symbolic core at work in them. Here the primary or primordial stage of symbolism and the later stages of narrative and philosophical speculation seem to exist in dynamic tension where each provides something to the other.</para><para>Yet, in other parts of the account the language of the primordial is employed in more ambivalent or even negative fashion. The symbol of defilement is seen as the most primordial but also as the most simplistic and most problematic of the three symbols of evil he discusses. It is linked to the “primitive” or “elementary” language of ritual (SE, 9), which is dismissed as “magic” and seen to be governed by fear (SE, 47). Indeed, Ricœur often labels ritual language itself as “primordial” in ways that actually seem to imply “primitive” with all the derogatory connotations that term carries (e.g., CI, 447). Although ritual confession brings to light various insights about the experience of evil—such as “blindness, equivocalness, scandalousness” (SE, 7)—it remains hampered by the ways in which the defilement seems to come from without. It does not involve self-reflection or any clear recognition of fault. For Ricœur ritual is almost exclusively identified with defilement and does not seem linked to sin or guilt in the same way: “It is the rite that exhibits the symbolism of defilement; and just as the rite suppresses symbolically, defilement infects symbolically” (SE, 35). Once there is a conception of a personal God rather than a more anonymous cosmic order, we move from defilement to sin (SE, 48).</para><para>Ricœur explores these latter “higher” stages or more sophisticated levels of the recognition of evil in much more detail. He thinks of this progression and advancement as a fairly linear movement, one that moves away from cosmic dimensions to more personal ones that become increasingly psychologically sophisticated. The move to the individual is especially significant for him: “this individualization of guilt breaks with the ‘we’ of the confession of sins” (SE, 105). Only if sin is an individual experience can redemption become a similarly individual and personal experience (SE, 105). This makes possible something like the “scrupulous conscience” with all its attendant effects (SE, 138). He is particularly interested in the psychological dimensions of the Adamic myth and its impact on the consciousness of the self or what it reveals about this consciousness. The value of the Adamic myth is precisely its universalization of the recognition of sin and guilt: “It was because the confession of sins involved this virtual universalization that the Adamic myth was possible: the myth, in naming Adam, man, makes explicit the concrete universality of human evil; the spirit of repentance gives to itself, in the Adamic myth, the symbol of that universality” (SE, 241). This myth enables philosophical speculation via the rupture it introduces between the ontological and the historical dimensions (SE, 242). It is not clear, however, why a heavy emphasis on the individual is necessarily an improvement over more communal ways of grappling with fault and guilt—or why this alone can be universalized to define all humankind. This is simply assumed.</para><para>Ricœur consistently considers the cosmic dimension as more primitive, while the ontological symbolism is more sophisticated and more philosophical, a higher and more advanced stage of thinking. He speaks of it as a progressive movement that moves from defilement to sin and then to guilt, away from the cosmically ritualized to the ontologically experienced (SE, 11). This identification of ritual and the cosmic is evident also in some of his later texts and almost always presupposed in any comments he makes about ritual or liturgy (e.g., FS, 48-67). Ricœur considers these “earlier” stages of religion “primitive” (especially the “cosmic” nature religions Eliade explores) and is certain that under no conditions can the philosopher or scholar return to them.<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="9" xml:id="d1e92"><para>For a more sympathetic reading, see Brian Gregor’s account of the relationship between Ricœur and Eliade: Brian Gregor, “Between Barth and Eliade: Ricoeur’s Mediation of the Word and the Sacred,” in Davidson, <emphasis role="italic">Companion to the Symbolism of Evil</emphasis>, 103-22.</para></footnote> Primitive religion features elaborate nature symbolism that engages in an unsophisticated “logic of correspondence” or equivalence (FS, 53-55, 279-83), which is often understood literally in ways that are utterly unconvincing to the contemporary person. Such literalism and primitive belief must be rejected by anyone who thinks. Critical thought is essential and ostensibly incompatible with ritual and its cosmic symbolism. We can thus never return to the primitive stage; ritual no longer holds lived meaning for us. In this regard Ricœur follows the Bultmannian and Durkheimian assumptions that the primary discourse is less sophisticated and riddled with superstitions, and therefore its demythologization is absolutely essential: “demythologization is the irreversible gain of truthfulness, intellectual honesty, objectivity” (SE, 350, repeated almost verbatim on 352). Again he associates truth here not with the “fullness of language,” as evident in symbol and myth, but with the rigorous academic and scholarly search for historical objectivity.</para><para>This is particularly evident in his analysis of the Adamic myth, which he considers the highest and most comprehensive narrative account of evil (SE, 306-46). It holds together the notions of “the chaos <emphasis role="italic">in</emphasis> me, <emphasis role="italic">among</emphasis> us, and <emphasis role="italic">outside</emphasis>” (SE, 258; emphasis his). Yet, at the same time, he is quite clear that even this myth is no longer believable and that it cannot be read as either history or explanation: “What does it mean to ‘understand’ the Adamic myth? In the first place, it means accepting the fact that it is a myth.” Thus, the question about when and where Adam ate the fruit is meaningless today; the story cannot possibly be understood literally, as he assumes the original hearers did. What today’s educated hearers know of human evolution “leaves no place for such a primordial event” (SE, 235). It is fairly evident throughout that Ricœur dismisses what he sees as the traditional assumptions about the figure of Adam and that he thinks it was previously taken in a literal, historical sense.</para><para>He is quite adamant that a historical or literal interpretation of this myth is not only false but actively harmful: “Hence, it is false that the ‘Adamic’ myth is the keystone of the Judeo-Christian edifice; it is only a flying buttress, articulated upon the ogival crossing of the Jewish penitential spirit” (SE, 239). The doctrine of original sin comes in for even harsher condemnation: “The harm that has been done to souls, during the centuries of Christianity, first by the literal interpretation of the story of Adam, and then by the confusion of this myth, treated as history, with later speculations, principally Augustinian, about original sin, will never be adequately told.” He calls it a “mythico-speculative mass” that should never have been posited as an explanation. By doing so, “the theologians have unduly required a <emphasis role="italic">sacrificium intellectus</emphasis> where what was needed was to awaken believers to a symbolic superintelligence of their actual condition” (SE, 239). Thus, apparently both myth and doctrine are to be rejected, even if the symbol itself gives rise to further reflection.</para><para>Ricœur consistently thinks of “primitive” religion as problematically entangling history and myth. To have separated them constitutes progress. We must engage the myth in a much more sophisticated manner that dismisses its (false) historical dimensions and “conquers” the myth via critical demythologization: “But another possibility offers itself to us: precisely because we are living and thinking after the separation of myth and history, the demythization of our history can become the other side of an understanding of myth as myth, and the conquest, for the first time in the history of culture, of the mythical dimension” (SE, 162). Ultimately, myths in general, but especially those with more cosmic and communal dimensions, must be left behind in our more enlightened and critical age.</para></section><section role="H1"><title>From First to Second Naïveté</title><para>The contemporary educated person thus cannot return to a simple belief in myths. Mythical language no longer has meaning for us. Ricœur thinks that we cannot possibly go back to a primitive naïveté, because such immediacy of belief has been “irremediably lost”; we cannot return to it (SE, 351). It can only be retrieved in a radically different fashion after moving through the stage of enlightened critique. Ricœur presents this move from first naïveté—through doubt, demythologization, and critique—to second naïveté in a fairly linear fashion. It is a process of growth or maturation from a childlike or “primitive” faith to an intellectual engagement with insights of science and rationality, which might lead us to doubt or even reject the more primitive faith, ultimately resulting in a mature faith that does not deny the intellectual insights yet goes beyond them to further and fuller thought. In a later interview he reiterates this: “We can no longer approach myth <emphasis role="italic">at the level of naïveté</emphasis>. We must rather always view it from a critical perspective. It is only by means of a selective reappropriation that we can become aware of myth. We are no longer primitive beings, living at the immediate level of myth” (PR, 120; emphasis in the original). Later, such immediacy will be problematic also because it is not open to interpretation in the same way as texts are. The “distance” or mediation of interpretation destroys the immediacy of belief.</para><para>Accordingly, he contends that one can arrive at a second naïveté via a thorough engagement with the symbolism employed in myths and a sophisticated recovery of the meaning in the original experiences they represent. What is required, in Kearney’s words, “is a hermeneutic dialectic between the claims of <emphasis role="italic">logos</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">mythos</emphasis>” (PR, 70). This is only possible through the “wager” of belief that enters deeply, albeit provisionally, into the symbolic and mythical accounts. The philosopher must adopt “belief” in “sympathetic imagination” in order to understand and analyze how it functions: “The philosopher adopts provisionally the motivations and intentions of the believing soul. He does not ‘feel’ them in their first naïveté; he ‘re-feels’ them in a neutralized mode, in the mode of ‘as if.’ It is in this sense that phenomenology is re-enactment in sympathetic imagination” (SE, 19). Thus, the philosopher maintains a sophisticated “neutral” distance from the original experience; he or she can analyze it and even enter into it to some extent via empathy albeit not real participation, but does so in an educated fashion that does not succumb to the more primitive dimensions of the myth. In a different context he affirms: “To separate kerygma from myth is the positive function of demythologization” (CI, 390). Thus, belief or doctrine is treated as separable from their ritualized instantiation.</para><para>Ricœur insists upon the important role of hermeneutics in recovering this naïveté: on the one hand, “there exists nowhere a symbolic language without hermeneutics” (SE, 350); on the other hand, “it is by <emphasis role="italic">interpreting</emphasis> that we can <emphasis role="italic">hear</emphasis> again” (SE, 351). The attempt to “re-feel” in sympathetic imagination is an interpretive process that reveals the meaning hidden in the symbol or myth. Therefore, “it is in hermeneutics that the symbol’s gift of meaning and the endeavor to understand by deciphering are knotted together” (SE, 351). Hermeneutics moves through the moment of belief, and via the process of interpretation it is able to isolate its truth and recover it for today: “For the second immediacy that we seek and the second naïveté that we await are no longer accessible to us anywhere else than in a hermeneutics; we can believe only by interpreting. It is the ‘modern’ mode of belief in symbols, an expression of the distress of modernity and a remedy for that distress” (SE, 352). Thus hermeneutics is able to bring together the meaning of now-defunct symbols and our modern, more critical and thus more honest, condition. We cannot, however, ever return to the more immediate situation of belief.</para><para>Thanks to the hermeneutic circle, “I can still today communicate with the sacred by making explicit the prior understanding that gives life to the interpretation” (SE, 352). While the ancients lived within a sacred universe of immediate relation with the gods, today we have hermeneutic sophistication, but thus give up the ability to live within the sacred dimension. Hermeneutics is consistently associated with the movement to critique: “Thus hermeneutics, an acquisition of ‘modernity,’ is one of the modes by which that ‘modernity’ transcends itself, insofar as it is forgetfulness of the sacred.” Being or transcendence no longer speak to us “under the precritical form of immediate belief, but as the second immediacy aimed at by hermeneutics.” This becomes “the postcritical equivalent of the precritical hierophany” (SE, 352). Thus, the wager of empathetic belief pays off in a “modern” and critical appropriation of “being” without its superstitious entanglements with the sacred.</para><para>Yet, what exactly does it mean to have such an “equivalent” of the primitive or precritical? How can such sympathetic imagination still be possible, if the immediacy of belief and ritual life is really so utterly foreign to us? What would it mean to come to an “equivalent” insight that preserves the “truth” of what we have now discovered to be irredeemably false? We have left the enchanted world irretrievably behind us and have progressed to a stage of modern enlightenment that despite his sensitivity to the importance of symbolic language Ricœur clearly sees as superior: the criticism of demythologization is an advance that is more truthful, more intellectually honest, and more objective (SE, 352). If truth and honesty are so firmly associated with scientific objectivity can the primitive symbol or myth really teach us anything?</para><para>The various tensions uncovered here consequently point to troubling dichotomies in Ricœur’s early work. He elevates the primordial but rejects the primitive. He seeks the fullness of language but ultimately equates it with superstition. He wants to move to a second naïveté while rejecting the first as false and dishonest. He tries to remove the kernel of truth from a symbol that no longer functions with a commitment to objectivity as “real” truth. He acknowledges that purely philosophical language is insufficient and requires recourse to the fullness of symbol and mythical language, yet assumes that this language no longer functions, that it no longer compels us, and that it must be rejected as untrue. Ricœur’s analysis, then, depends on two related assumptions: first, that a core or nucleus of truth or meaning can be isolated in the primordial symbols or myths and that this core is transferable into the contemporary situation or can be recovered as a truth; second, that this proceeds via a linear, progressive movement where something of the primordial continues to be preserved across the stages of development and is in some form encapsulated in later insights. Yet, both of these are questionable assumptions.</para><para>First, can such a core of insight really be isolated, can it be protected and transferred without loss, and can it be recovered today?<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="10" xml:id="d1e144"><para>Richard Kearney raises this question as well in an interview: “But is it possible to extract the <emphasis role="italic">logos</emphasis> and yet leave the <emphasis role="italic">mythos</emphasis> intact?” (PR, 121). In his response Ricœur does not really address the question, but does distance himself more fully from Bultmann’s method of demythologization than he does in <emphasis role="italic">Symbolism of Evil</emphasis> (PR, 122). Kearney appropriates Ricœur’s notion of the wager, especially in regard to a move through a critical, quasi-atheist, position in order to return to faith, in much of his work. See his “Returning to God after God: Levinas, Derrida, Ricoeur,” <emphasis role="italic">Research in Phenomenology</emphasis> 39.2 (2009), especially 172-83, and Richard Kearney, <emphasis role="italic">Anatheism: Returning to God After God</emphasis> (New York: Columbia University Press, 2010).</para></footnote> Is it possible to gain such truth and retrieve kernels of symbol or myth, if they are, in fact, so patently false and so unbelievable to us today? Can the second naïveté really retrieve anything from the first if all narrative trappings have to be removed entirely? Is it possible to isolate the core of truth from the primordial symbol in a way that can transfer smoothly to the philosophical insight? Ricœur repeatedly refers to such a “nucleus” of meaning that must be isolated from the “magical” interpretation of primitive symbolism. This nucleus emerges fully only via the more sophisticated levels: “If one should ask, then, what the <emphasis role="italic">nucleus </emphasis>[<emphasis role="italic">le noyau</emphasis>] is that remains constant through all the symbolizations of defilement, we should have to answer that it is only in the progress of conscience [or consciousness<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="11" xml:id="d1e152"><para>Although Ricœur stresses the development of the “conscience” later in the book, here he seems to mean a growth in “consciousness” instead. (The words are the same in French and are obviously related in this context: a greater awareness or consciousness of sin or guilt may result in the development of the conscience.)</para></footnote>], as it advances beyond and at the same time retains the notion of defilement, that its meaning will be manifested” (SE, 45-46). Even the meaning of the earlier symbol ultimately only emerges as interpretation progresses to higher stages. The interpretive process of isolating the meaningful kernel is thus linked to his assumptions about the connected linearity in which higher stages sublate the insights of lower ones in a quasi-Hegelian progression, while also constituting significant advance beyond them.<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="12" xml:id="d1e154"><para>In a different context, Ricœur will later be slightly more hesitant about the idea that one could isolate a kernel of truth and carry it successfully across a process of demythologization to a new context (FS, 62).</para></footnote></para><para>For example, although he admits a “phenomenological continuity between defilement and sin,” Ricœur argues that the ontological dimension or reality of sin stands in contrast to the “‘subjectivity’ of the consciousness of guilt” (SE, 86, 82). He consistently thinks of guilt as superior: “What is essential in guilt is already contained in this consciousness of being ‘burdened,’ burdened by a ‘weight’” as internalized anticipated chastisement (SE, 101), but this superiority can take on some of the insights from the symbolism of defilement. This is a decisive moment for him, which constitutes an important advance: “The birth of a new ‘measure’ of fault is a decisive event in the history of the notion of fault; and this event represents a double advance, from which it is not possible to turn back” (SE, 104). We thus succeed in discerning the meaning of fault via the progression from defilement via sin to guilt, while also advancing or progressing in such a way that earlier stages are rendered primitive and inaccessible in comparison. Guilt means that we have internalized the sense of sin in the form of the conscience, the interior feeling of guilt that measures and evaluates itself (SE, 143). Ricœur consistently describes the internal and personal movement of guilt as superior to the external and communal elements of defilement or sin (e.g., CI, 430). Guilt is the higher stage that develops out of the lower stages and constitutes the kind of progress that cannot and should not be reversed. Yet, is the complete internalization of fault in the form of guilt really such a high achievement?</para><para>This linear progression from defilement over sin toward guilt can certainly be questioned. Returning to ritual more fully might have enabled Ricœur to complicate his account.<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="13" xml:id="d1e159"><para>In one of his early essays Ricœur proposes to undertake this, but does not really do so. He claims the philosophers ought to consult “penitential literature wherein the believing communities have expressed their avowal of evil” and look at “confession of sin,” but no such texts—much less practices—are actually discussed in his essay (CI, 425).</para></footnote> Part of the great insight but also the problem of his work here is that he tries to separate fault from finitude, while also holding these insights together. He wants to argue both that an individual consciousness of guilt (i.e. the development of a personal conscience and of individual notions of redemption) are an achievement and higher stage than the more communal and cosmic accounts of defilement, while simultaneously maintaining that the most sophisticated myth (i.e. the Judeo-Christian Adamic myth) combines all the insights of the earlier stages. Yet, this is not only contradictory; it also misrepresents the historical record. Many symbolic expressions of ritual, which Ricœur repeatedly associates with earlier, primitive stages, are highly sophisticated, non-literal enactments of the enmeshment of defilement, sin, and guilt. Indeed, ritual is not simply about cosmic defilement, but also about guilt and evoking contrition. Rites of confession acknowledge the person as sinner who must be forgiven (and redeemed), while also often employing language of illness and defilement that figure finitude more in terms of weakness or attack by evil forces. Although Ricœur conflates them, the latter two images are actually substantively different: the contrast or cure for defilement is purification, for illness it is healing.</para><para>Such language of sin in terms of illness and redemption as salve, geared at the health of soul and body, is pervasive in early patristic and medieval texts of all Christian traditions. Many religious rituals in various traditions, including Christian liturgy, speak of sin in terms of both illness and weakness, thus acknowledging that the line between finitude and fault, weakness and sin, fallibility and guilt are not always clearly drawn, but that all these aspects are entangled with each other in complicated ways. To provide just one example from the Orthodox lenten liturgy: “I am clad in a garment that is defiled and shamefully blood-stained by a life of passion and self-indulgence. I have stained the garment of my flesh, O Saviour, and defiled that which was made in Thine image and likeness. I have fallen beneath the painful burden of the passions and the corruption of material things; and I am hard pressed by the enemy.”<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="14" xml:id="d1e163"><para>From Ode 2 of the Great Canon of St. Andrew of Crete, prayed on the first four weekday evenings of the first week of Great Lent and in its entirety again on the Thursday of the fifth week of Great Lent. Translation taken from <emphasis role="italic">The Lenten Triodion</emphasis>, trans. Mother Mary and Archimandrite Kallistos Ware (South Canaan, PA: St. Tikhon’s Seminary Press, 2002), 382. Being a victim of evil as well as a perpetrator of it are often mentioned within a few lines (or minutes) of each other. For example, the first ode includes the verse, “I am the man who fell among thieves... they have covered all my body with wounds, and I lie beaten and bruised,” and prays for Christ’s healing (ibid., 379). A few lines further it is affirmed that “from my youth, O Saviour, I have rejected Thy commandments. Ruled by the passions, I have passed my whole life in heedlessness and sloth” (ibid., 380). This sort of smooth back and forth between speaking of evil as an illness to which one succumbs versus a fault one commits or a condition in which one finds oneself is extremely common in the liturgical texts, especially in the Great Canon. The text was originally composed in the late 7th or early 8th century and has been used liturgically since at least the 10th century. For a detailed discussion—that actually shares Ricœur’s interest in the consciousness of sin—see the fifth chapter of Derek Krueger, <emphasis role="italic">Liturgical Subjects: Christian Ritual, Biblical Narrative, and the Formation of the Self in Byzantium</emphasis> (Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 2014), 130-63. See also Doru Costache, “Andrew of Crete’s Great Canon, Byzantine Hermeneutics, and Genesis 1-3,” in Sarah Gador-Whyte and Andrew Mellas, eds., <emphasis role="italic">Hymns, Homilies and Hermeneutics in Byzantium</emphasis> (Leiden: Brill, 2021), 67-85.</para></footnote> Here stain and defilement are interpreted as conditions for which one is culpable, while at the same time the situation is interpreted as one of temptation and attack by the enemy. Ritual practices can express this kind of enmeshment of fragility, fallibility, fault, and guilt, which can register existentially as imprisonment or illness, while not absolving the penitent of culpability or excluding feelings of guilt. The distinctions between defilement, sin, and guilt are far from clear in liturgical language, and this itself conveys an important existential truth: feelings and even actions can be experienced both as overpowering us or imprisoning us and as something in which we are deliberately involved and for which we are culpable. We can cause harm to others unintentionally and feel guilty for it, even when we were practically unable to act otherwise. Ricœur acknowledges the ways in which these experiences can be enmeshed in a different context where he points to the “strange experience of passivity at the very heart” of evil in that “human beings feel themselves victims while at the same time being guilty.”<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="15" xml:id="d1e165"><para>Ricoeur, <emphasis role="italic">Evil</emphasis>, 38.</para></footnote> Symbol, myth, and especially ritual can give voice to this experience.</para><para>It is also not true that symbolic or mythic language was originally taken literally in the sort of simplistic fashion Ricœur often implies, at least not when speaking of Christian liturgy.<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="16" xml:id="d1e169"><para>I strongly suspect that this is also not the case for most other forms of symbolic ritual or religious myth. In fairness, Ricœur does seem to recognize this once for Christian liturgy. In his interview at Taizé he says: “On the level of representation liturgy accomplishes something of that post-critical naïveté that I have sometimes called a second naïveté... although it is certainly true that only predication has meaning, liturgy already lives it in its figures.” “Postface,” 250-51. He does not develop this further in the brief interview and does not return to this tentative suggestion elsewhere, as far as I am able to ascertain.</para></footnote><superscript> </superscript>Liturgical texts often deliberately confuse persons and time periods; they do not treat them in any straight-forward historical, literal, or chronological fashion. This is particularly evident in the way in which biblical or historical characters (including Christ and the “saints”) are remembered or referenced within liturgy. It rarely occurs in the manner in which we usually speak of historical events; rather, they are often treated as present in some form or even evoked in a future mode through petition for assistance. (Later chapters will grapple with this much more fully.) The liturgical texts in these traditions handle the figure of Adam in particular in far more complex ways than Ricœur acknowledges for ritual practices.</para><para>There is no sense in which the myth of Adam is used in a purely historical fashion within Christian liturgy, at least as regards the patristic tradition. Rather, it is a richly mimetic employment that often deliberately upsets historical chronology. A particularly fascinating example of this is found in the liturgical poems of Romanos the Melodist (6th c.), one of the most famous liturgical author in the Eastern Christian tradition.<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="17" xml:id="d1e175"><para>For English translations of the liturgical poetry of Romanos, see Romanos the Melodist, <emphasis role="italic">On the Life of Christ: Kontakia</emphasis>, trans. Ephrem Lash (San Francisco: HarperCollins, 1995) and <emphasis role="italic">Sacred Song from the Byzantine Pulpit: Romanos the Melodist</emphasis>, trans. R. J. Schork (Gainesville, FL: University of Florida Press, 1997). For secondary discussions, see the second chapter of Krueger, <emphasis role="italic">Liturgical Subjects</emphasis>, 29-66; Grosdidier de Matons, <emphasis role="italic">Romanos le Mélode et les origines de la poésie religieuse à Byzance</emphasis> (Paris: Beauchesne, 1977); Joost van Rossum, “Romanos le Mélode et le «kontakion»,” in <emphasis role="italic">L’Hymnographie. Conférences Saint-Serge XLVIe Semaine d’Études Liturgiques 1999</emphasis>, eds. A. M. Triacca and A. Pistoia (Roma: Edizoni Liturgiche, 2000), 93-104; Sarah Gador-Whyte, <emphasis role="italic">Theology and Poetry in Early Byzantium: The Kontakia of Romanos the Melodist</emphasis> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2017) and the two chapters on Romanos in Gador-White, <emphasis role="italic">Hymns, Homilies, and Hermeneutics in Byzantium</emphasis>, 89-123.</para></footnote> In one of his kontakia (liturgical verse poem) for nativity, he describes Adam and Eve coming to Bethlehem after Christ is born in order to ask how much longer it will take for them to be finally redeemed. Eve and Mary become involved a long discussion in which Mary—after consulting with her son—tells them that they must wait a little longer.<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="18" xml:id="d1e177"><para>It is fascinating that women function very prominently in many of these kontakia, including those of Ephrem the Syrian, which are even considerably earlier. Eve does all the talking; Adam does not really get a word in edgewise.</para></footnote> Romanos also composed a liturgical hymn specifically about Adam and Eve, which was sung during the second week of Lent and portrays the biblical story in dramatic fashion. But Adam shows up all over the place: on Theophany, where Adam’s eyes are opened as Christ is baptized, on Palm Sunday, multiple times during Holy Week—both in Hades and on earth—and of course after the Resurrection.<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="19" xml:id="d1e179"><para>Adam is also mentioned in several other hymns, such as that for Palm Sunday and for “The Triumph of the Cross” during Holy Week, as well as the one for Holy Friday, where Adam is portrayed as being in error not really as particularly sinful, and those for the Resurrection (of which there are several). An examination of the role of Adam in Romanos’ liturgical poetry alone would make for a fascinating and instructive study.</para></footnote> Indeed, several popular hymns for Holy Week imagine debates between hell, the devil, and death, in which Adam is the spoil they discuss and do not want to let go. Some of the journeys to Paradise, imagined to be taken by Mary after the Dormition (her “falling asleep”) or by the dead thief who was crucified with Christ in accounts of Holy Week, also comment on Adam’s presence or absence in Paradise.<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="20" xml:id="d1e181"><para>See Steven J. Shoemaker’s <emphasis role="italic">Ancient Traditions of the Virgin Mary’s Dormition and Assumption</emphasis> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2002), which includes translations of several of these late antique sources.</para></footnote></para><para>Clearly, these are highly imaginative performances that have a variety of pedagogical and theological purposes, but they do not pretend to make any literal historical claims. Instead, they are profoundly poetic. Both the patristic examples and contemporary liturgical texts take great liberties with the biblical personages and even the scriptural texts on which they are based. No straight-forward historical claim is being made when Adam and Eve visit the nativity crib or show up at the foot of the cross. Although most of the ancient and medieval audiences engaged in these prayers presumably assumed that some particular Adam and Eve had actually been around at some point as first-created people, this assumption is quite irrelevant to the creative mimetic way in which the figures are employed throughout. Contemporary Orthodox liturgy, which often draws on these patristic texts in some form, still handles the figures and biblical texts with similar ambivalence that does not come down to taking them literally or treating them as straightforward historical accounts.<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="21" xml:id="d1e184"><para>This is probably true for the use of biblical texts in worship more broadly, even in Christian confessions that otherwise tend to greater literalism.</para></footnote></para><para>In these contemporary texts,<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="22" xml:id="d1e188"><para>“Contemporary” is obviously a relative term here, given that most Orthodox liturgical texts reached their final form in the 13th and 14th centuries. Although the music developed further and changes in performance also occurred, the texts themselves have not really been altered since then and many rely on much earlier sources. But Romanos’ kontakia, for example, are no longer employed in their original form, although some remnants remain in later liturgical texts.</para></footnote> particularly during penitential seasons such as Great Lent, Adam is referred to in the first person (singular and plural), the second person, and the third person, thus moving ambivalently from a symbol for all of humankind and its shared condition, or a figure encapsulating our own personal transgressions, to an identifiable person having committed a particular sin, to a model held up as warning against imitation, to serving as harbinger of Christ, to someone one can address for help in one’s own struggles. Adam is all of these at the same time. The liturgical figure of Adam speaks both of our transgressions and of a broader implication in evil structures, on the one hand of our personal evil acts for which we are responsible and must repent, and on the other hand of our enmeshment in a whole history of evil, which both precedes and follows us and of which we are a part not by our own choosing. Adam designates our need for repentance as well as our need for healing.</para><para>Adam thus functions liturgically on multiple levels: as a person who speaks for us and on our behalf and hence might give us insight into our own condition, as someone with whom we identify, and as a symbol that contrasts first and second Adam and hence sees him in relation with Christ. The distinction between historical or symbolic would make very little sense here; it is a distinction completely foreign to this narrative world or liturgical context. The composers of these texts clearly did not think of these distinctions as a hindrance or of these different liturgical “persona” as incompatible. This is by no means a literal or “naïve” reading. Indeed, most liturgical texts are not at all interested in providing a history of origins. Sin and evil are realities with which we must cope and the liturgical texts and practices help us do so. They speak from <emphasis role="italic">within</emphasis> a condition of fallenness and weakness, a condition that knows itself both personally responsible and overpowered by larger forces that it often finds itself helpless to combat. And these forces operate both externally and internally. All these realities are expressed and addressed within the liturgical texts while not attempting to solve the whence and where of sin and evil.</para><para>In either case, the “primitive” use of symbolic figures and mythical accounts, at least within liturgical texts, is far more complex than Ricœur assumes. They already operate at multiple levels and are far from being understood only or even primarily in a strictly historical sense. This might suggest that the early uses of these myths were neither “naïve” nor “primitive”—and possibly that our firm distinctions between literal, historical, psychological, and ontological levels do not constitute great progress. The liturgical texts are already complex readings of primordial human experience in a theologically sophisticated manner. The figure of Adam functions within the liturgical texts in much the rich and complicated way Ricœur wants to reserve only for the philosophical and hermeneutic analysis. One might suggest that to arrive at the primary modes of religious faith, one must look not only at biblical texts, but also at the actions and practices in which religious believers engage. Liturgical texts and performances may well constitute just as originary and authentically an expression of religious faith as the biblical narratives. Analyzing them hermeneutically may uncover important dimensions of the meaning of faith and religious expression to the philosopher.</para></section><section role="H1"><title>Wagering on the Servile Will</title><para>The culminating point of the move from defilement via sin toward guilt for Ricœur is the notion of the “servile will,”<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="23" xml:id="d1e201"><para>It is translated as “slave will” in some of the translations of his work (and as “bound will” in PA). In an interview with Yvanka Raynova it is even rendered as “bad will” (AGT, 671). All these translations refer to what is usually in English called “the bondage of the will” in its Augustinian sense. For a fuller treatment, see Frey, “On the Servile Will,” in Davidson, <emphasis role="italic">Companion to Symbolism of Evil</emphasis>, 51-66 and Greisch, <emphasis role="italic">L’Herméneutique</emphasis>, 73-78.</para></footnote> which he consistently interprets as a great achievement. It is not simply a concept of fallibility, but is found at the level of more sophisticated speculation (SE, 151). The contradiction implied in a will that is both bound and free is “insupportable for thought,” but at the same time constitutes “the central theme of ‘salvation’” (SE, 152). The notion of the servile will combines aspects of all three symbols of evil and thus serves as “the symbol of a sinful being who is at the same time <emphasis role="italic">act</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">state</emphasis>” (SE, 154; emphases his). He outlines a triple schematism of the servile will, in which defilement must become a “positive” guilt (“positiveness”); evil is experienced as external and always already there, taking us captive (via “seduction”); and the yielding of the self to slavery (via “infection”) “points toward the relation of radical evil to the very being of man” (SE, 156). Thus, despite his reluctance to engage in theological speculation, the idea of the “servile will” constitutes the apex of his analysis, the core insight that can be isolated via the progression through the symbols, the culminating point of the development of evil, as extracted from the poetic and narrative developments.</para><para>Ricœur elaborates on this in other contexts. He considers the servile will the religious equivalent of the “wounded cogito” that the “masters of suspicion,” Marx, Nietzsche, and Freud, reveal to us in their attack on the illusion of self-consciousness (CI, 148, 322). This wounded cogito “posits but does not possess itself”; it “understands its originary truth only in and by the confession of the inadequation, the illusion, and the lie of existing consciousness” (CI, 173). By uncovering this condition, psychoanalysis in particular proposes a sort of rival hermeneutics of symbols.<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="24" xml:id="d1e211"><para>This is obviously worked out in far more detail in his book on Freud, which is also the first book to posit itself explicitly as an exercise in hermeneutics. The French title is <emphasis role="italic">De l’interprétation. Essai sur Freud </emphasis>(title and subtitle were reversed and slightly amended in the English translation to <emphasis role="italic">Freud and Philosophy: An Essay on Interpretation</emphasis>). See also some of the essays included in <emphasis role="italic">Conflict of Interpretations</emphasis> and in the first volume of essays and lectures, entitled (in English) <emphasis role="italic">On Psychoanalysis: Writings and Lectures, Volume 1</emphasis>, trans. David Pellauer (Cambridge, UK: Polity: 2012).</para></footnote> Although Ricœur rejects the “dogma” of original sin as original, inherited guilt, he consistently affirms the theological insight that evil precedes us, that our fundamental condition is sinful, and that we are held captive by it (CI, 282-83).<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="25" xml:id="d1e213"><para>He also refuses the idea that only the theologian would have the right to reflect on these questions. Indeed, he says quite forcefully: “I, for one, do not divide philosophy and theology in this way. As <emphasis role="italic">revealing</emphasis>—and not as revealed—the Adam symbol belongs to a philosophical anthropology just as much as all the other symbols.” He continues: “For my part, I hold that no symbol qua opening and uncovering a truth of man is foreign to philosophical reflection. Hence I do not take the concept of original sin to be a theme extraneous to philosophy but, on the contrary, to be a theme subject to an intentional analysis, to a hermeneutics of rational symbols whose task is to reconstruct the layers of meaning which have become sedimented in the concept” (CI, 305; emphasis his).</para></footnote> The Adamic myth reveals the mystery that “each of us also discovers evil, finds it already there, in himself, outside himself, and before himself: such that I do not begin evil; I continue it” (CI, 284). After reviewing the controversy between Augustine and Pelagius, he affirms that “it is Augustine who remains right, through and in spite of this Adamic mythology” (CI, 281). Evil, then, “is a kind of involuntariness at the very heart of the voluntary, no longer facing the voluntary but within the voluntary, and it is this which is the servile will” (CI, 286). That Augustine might be profoundly mistaken, not just about hereditary evil, but also about the bondage of the will, does not seem to be entertained as a possibility.<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="26" xml:id="d1e215"><para>In the interview with Raynova, he admits that “all that I had said on bad will was bound to a very specific tradition of our culture, the tradition of Saint Paul, Saint Augustine, Luther, Karl Barth, etc., and transposed into philosophic terms” (AGT, 671).</para></footnote></para><para>The Adamic myth, then, shows us “the ‘tragic’ aspect of evil” and gives us “the symbol of ‘captivity,’ of slavery” that shows evil both proceeding from freedom and limiting it, both “act <emphasis role="italic">and</emphasis> habit” (CI, 306, 308; emphasis his). The myth is “irreducible to the ethical,” even shows a “humiliated ethical” (CI, 309). At the same time, the tragic vision of evil points to the “category of hope,” an insight he will also reiterate in many other contexts (e.g., CI, 314, 436-39; FS, 203-16; FS, 299). Indeed, one might say that this tension between fragility and hope permeates Ricœur’s thought from beginning to end. The notion of original sin takes “up one fundamental aspect of the experience of evil, namely, the both individual and communal sense of human impotence in the face of the demonic power of evil already there, long before any bad initiative may be assigned to some deliberate intention” (FS, 254). Even in one of his final lectures on religion, he still considers the notion of the bondage of the will central: “That which is called bad will, captive free will, servant-will is about an easily identifiable experience: it is felt as an intimate binding of oneself by oneself” (RB, 28). Therefore, “the religious has as its function the deliverance of the core of goodness from the bonds that hold it captive” (RB, 30). Even in the fragments left after his death and published posthumously as <emphasis role="italic">Living Up to Death</emphasis>, he reiterates this conviction to some extent (LD, 23-29).</para><para>The notions of fragility and fallibility are also at the very origin of Ricœur’s work. Already <emphasis role="italic">Freedom and Nature</emphasis> raised the question of the fault and of fallibility in regard to the will, which <emphasis role="italic">Fallible Man</emphasis> then goes on to explore more fully in phenomenological and existential terms.<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="27" xml:id="d1e232"><para>For fuller discussions of these texts, see the two collections edited by Scott Davidson, <emphasis role="italic">A Companion to Ricoeur’s</emphasis> Freedom and Nature (Lanham, MD: Lexington Books, 2018) and <emphasis role="italic">A Companion to Ricoeur’s</emphasis> Fallible Man (Lanham, MD: Lexington Books, 2019), as well as the discussions in Greisch’s <emphasis role="italic">L’Herméneutique</emphasis>, 59-95 and his <emphasis role="italic">Paul Ricœur</emphasis>, 29-87.</para></footnote> He suggests that “the idea that man is by nature fragile and liable to err” is “an idea wholly accessible to pure reflection” (FM, 1). Fallibility, fault, fragility, and finitude are all closely connected for Ricœur, although he does distinguish his project frequently from a Heideggerian or Sartrean notion of finitude (e.g. FM, 3, 25, 39, 43, 134). Fallibility concerns the gap between our desires and our capacities, the disproportion between what we are and what we wish to achieve, between the misery of the human condition—including the puzzle whether this is a “primal wound” in our condition or “our fault” (FM, 13)—and its striving for transcendence. The human is restless; we are divided against ourselves, in conflict with ourselves (FM, 92, 106, 125, 132). Indeed, “the restless heart” is “the fragile moment par excellence” (FM, 82). Again, the Augustinian tenor of this is unmistakable.</para><para>Fragility in these early texts encapsulates a sense of limitation, disproportion, the “fault” line or mediation between reality and possibility (FM, 140). Fragility is about human weakness, but read in terms of the “capacity to fail” (FM, 141). He rarely considers dimensions of weakness or frailty that are not already on the way toward fault. While fallibility is not itself evil, it provides the occasion for it: “Fallibility is the condition of evil, although evil is the revealer of fallibility” (FM, 144). Fragility connotes this gap between fallibility and fault, between possibility and reality (FM, 142); it is “fallibility without fault” or before fault (FM, 144). Even here Ricœur insists that the primordial “shines through” the fallen, that “however primordial badness may be, goodness is yet more primordial” (FM, 144, 145), although the contrast remains one between good and evil. This is a fundamental conviction that Ricœur will never abandon (he reiterates it almost literally in MHF, 491; RB, 29; and other contexts). He concludes his treatment: “Fragility is not merely the ‘locus,’ the point of insertion of evil, nor even the ‘origin’ starting from which man falls; it is the ‘capacity’ for evil” (FM, 146). In another context he stresses that fragility is “clearly prior to the fall” (PA, 4). Fragility remains linked to fallibility or fault in these early texts. Phenomenology can access and depict the notion of fallibility, but a recourse to symbol or myth is required for a fuller account of evil and fallenness (FM, xliv). Although Ricœur insists repeatedly in this text that he is undertaking a purely philosophical reflection, it is fairly clear that it is profoundly informed by Augustinian notions of the restless heart and the bondage of the will.</para><para>Yet, is this servile will really such an unmitigated achievement? It is a thoroughly Augustinian notion, appropriated by several Protestant traditions, that does not represent the entire Christian tradition, much less the experience of evil in other religious or secular contexts. The Eastern Christian tradition—Syriac, Coptic, Byzantine, Slavonic, and others—does not feature such a notion of the bondage of the will and instead brings ideas of defilement, illness, sin, and guilt together in ways that do not suggest a development of one as superior to others, but instead always assumes intricate and intimate connections between them. As already mentioned, it is also an eminently liturgical tradition in which ritual continues to convey primary theological meaning rather than being superseded or replaced by theological speculation. The “servile will,” one might thus suggest, is not the highest Christian achievement, the “final word,” so to say, on evil, the deepest insight into the human condition, as Ricœur maintains repeatedly, despite all his reluctance to speak of original sin. Rather, it is an Augustinian aberration that contradicts the Christian message. The infamous passage in Romans 7:14-20 about Paul’s supposedly tortured conscience (“the introspective conscience of the West,” in Krister Stendahl’s famous phrase) was not read in such Augustinian (or Lutheran) fashion anywhere in the Christian East and the high view of human potential to repent and do the good continues unabated in much of that tradition. That may cause its own set of problems, but at the very least it suggests that an account of evil that holds together dimensions of defilement, sin, and guilt is indeed possible, while also remaining deeply liturgical. In this respect, it may provide a salutary alternative to the tortured conscience of the West—and a liturgical means for grappling with its consequences.</para><para>Maybe most problematic is Ricœur’s strong emphasis on individual consciousness of guilt (i.e. the development of a conscience) and the high value he places on individual notions of redemption.<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="28" xml:id="d1e240"><para>See also the crucial essays on guilt and punishment in CI, 354-77, 425-39.</para></footnote> Yet what makes religion so powerful and compelling—and this can obviously have both positive and negative implications—is its communal nature, its ability to bind people together (<emphasis role="italic">religare</emphasis> actually means to “tie” or “connect”) and to allow them to participate in something higher, larger, and more meaningful than themselves, more than an individual can generate on his or her own. Existentially, weakness, fault, and even guilt are at least as much communal or relational phenomena as they are purely personal ones, although fault and guilt can obviously separate us from others and be experienced in immensely isolating ways. Yet, it is precisely the harm to or even breakdown of relationships that turns sin or fault into debilitating experiences, causes feelings of guilt, and shows the need for the restoration of relationships. And sin can clearly also be a communal phenomenon, as is true for structural or systemic injustices—such as racism, genocide, or environmental devastation—that transcend the fault of any one individual and may well require communal repentance and certainly redress on scales much larger than individual ones. Even redemption makes very little sense as a purely individual notion, even if it can obviously be an intimately personal experience.<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="29" xml:id="d1e245"><para>In this respect, it is telling that in a different context Ricœur associates (communal) religion with the naïve stage that has been superseded by the attacks of the atheist “masters of suspicion”—Nietzsche, Marx, and Freud—and to which we can now no longer return and instead retrieves an (individual) form of belief that remains viable after the move through atheism (CI, 440-67).</para></footnote></para><para>Besides challenging Ricœur’s somewhat too simplistic linear configuration and suggesting that liturgical experience moves much more fluidly back and forth between “first” and “second” naïveté (or at least that the first is not as “naïve” as he suggests), one might thus also contend that the liturgical use of Adam could still prove helpful for addressing issues of systemic and corporate evil that go beyond individual responsibility. How do we best acknowledge our culpability for environmental problems, for example, when the problem far transcends our individual “will” or personal trespass?<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="30" xml:id="d1e249"><para><superscript></superscript>I work this out more fully in my contribution “Our Responsibility for Universal Evil: Rethinking Fallenness in Ecological Terms,” <emphasis role="italic">I more than Others</emphasis>, ed. Eric Severson (Newcastle upon Tyne: Cambridge Scholars Publishing, 2010), 60-74.</para></footnote> Ricœur may well be right that symbols can help us deal with a reality here that is not simply rationally resolvable and that it opens a space for confession that cannot be expressed in simply rational (or Enlightenment) parameters. The complex liturgical identification with Adam, replete with superlatives and emotive content (with “limit-expressions,” to use Ricœur’s later language), might open a path toward confessing and confronting deep complicity in realities of evil that go far beyond what we can “fix” individually and yet require confession and repentance maybe more insistently than much smaller personal trespasses. Instead of trying to move to a naïveté that rejects the mythic dimension in favor of a re-appropriation of the symbolic meaning, we might be better advised to operate at multiple levels simultaneously. In many ways the modern scientific version of things constitutes impoverishment and simplification, not enrichment or progress. Maybe what we need is not a recovery of “naïveté,” but an appreciation and re-appropriation of the narrative richness and poetic depth of religious myth as it is expressed in the fullness of liturgical language without abandoning scientific insights or seeing them as intrinsically opposed to each other, operating with conflicting accounts of truth.<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="31" xml:id="d1e251"><para>This might also help us grapple with the great discomfort Ricœur expressed at the end of his life about traditional Western theories of atonement, especially in his <emphasis role="italic">Living Up to Death</emphasis>, fruitfully connecting one of his earliest texts with his final posthumous work and confronting the challenge it might pose for the theologian drawing productively on Ricœur’s work.</para></footnote></para><para>Such engagement with liturgical practices might also shift the emphasis from an exclusive focus on belief to one more aware of the ways in which religion is expressed in practices. The symbolism of ritual is not primarily about belief; it is the <emphasis role="italic">enactment</emphasis> within ritual that matters existentially. Therefore there are no kernels of belief or knowledge to be carved out and transported to a new reality. Ricœur consistently insists on the importance of belief, including his famous formulation of the wager: “Such is the wager. Only he can object to this mode of thought who thinks that philosophy, to begin from itself, must be a philosophy without presuppositions. A philosophy that starts from the fullness of language is a philosophy with presuppositions. To be honest, it must make its presuppositions explicit, state them as beliefs, wager on the beliefs, and try to make the wager pay off in understanding” (SE, 357). In a different context he even says: “I understand religion as a primitive structure of life which must always be overcome by faith” (CI, 441). Yet, maybe starting from the fullness of religious language and tradition would lead one not first of all to <emphasis role="italic">beliefs</emphasis> but to practices and actions. That is to say, we would start not only from the fullness of language but the fullness of practices and ways of living. One must participate actively in a ritual for it to function; it is not primarily, or at least not exclusively, a matter of belief or faith. One comes into ritual not really in order to affirm something that might be true or false, but in order to experience something, to live within it, to participate in it. Its truth is an existentially lived reality. The wager in that case is not only a wager of belief that must be filled with understanding. Rather, the ritual “wager” is a wager of participation that becomes filled with meaning. That does not exclude belief, language, or understanding, but they are not the primary or sole stakes.</para><para>Although Ricœur for the most part moved beyond these early explorations of myths and engaged religious topics subsequently via a more single-minded hermeneutics of biblical texts, he remains focused on the issue of “belief” (rather than examining practices) to the very end of his career (cf. RB). Although much of his other hermeneutic work explores connections between texts and actions, narrative and life, when it comes to faith or religion, especially in its Christian iteration, Ricœur remains firmly focused on the biblical texts. This is what will be examined more closely in the next chapter, which deals with what might be considered the “middle” period of Ricœur’s religious hermeneutics.<footnote role="end-bk-note" label="32" xml:id="d1e262"><para>For an early self-interpretation of this shift in his thought, see Paul Ricœur, “From Existentialism to the Philosophy of Language,” printed as appendix to <emphasis role="italic">Rule of Metaphor</emphasis> (RM, 372-81, especially 379). Peter Kenny has delineated three stages in Ricœur’s career in which he drew the boundary between the two discourses or disciplines differently. He suggests that in Ricœur’s very early work the boundary was still very fluid until Ricœur realized that such fluidity was not acceptable in the academy. The “middle” stage is marked by a stricter division between the two as Ricœur became established as a major thinker with strong philosophical pedigree. After his retirement, when he no longer needed to prove himself, Ricœur again felt freer to engage the two discourses with each other. Although this assessment is helpful on some level, it explains Ricœur’s drawing of distinctions and relationships primarily in terms of Ricœur’s personal psychology and need for academic recognition. Peter Kenny, “Conviction, Critique, and Christian Theology,” <emphasis role="italic">Memory, Narrativity, Self and the Challenge to Think God: The Reception within Theology of the Recent Work of Paul Ricœur</emphasis>, ed. Maureen Junker-Kenny and Peter Kenny (Münster: LIT Verlag, 2004), 92-102. See also Patrick L. Bourgeois, “From Hermeneutics of Symbols to the Interpretation of Texts,” in Reagan, <emphasis role="italic">Studies in the Philosophy of Paul Ricoeur</emphasis>, 83-95. For an excellent review of the relationship between philosophical and theological hermeneutics in Ricœur’s thought, see Francesca Brezzi, “Paul Ricoeur: Interrogare e interpretare la fede,” <emphasis role="italic">Aquinas: Rivista Internazionale di Filosofia</emphasis> 57.1 (2014): 159-75. She thinks that the two function in complementary fashion in his work, in the form of “hermeneutic circularity or <emphasis role="italic">reciprocal donation</emphasis>” (173; emphasis hers). Aside from those by Mongin and Grondin already mentioned, see also two other recent helpful introductions to Ricœur’s overall thought: Greisch’s <emphasis role="italic">Paul Ricœur: L’itinérance du sens</emphasis> and Johann Michel’s <emphasis role="italic">Paul Ricœur: Une philosophie de l’agir humain</emphasis> (Paris: Cerf, 2006).</para></footnote></para></section><section role="H1"><title>Notes</title></section></chapter></book>
