<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE book SYSTEM "docbook.dtd"><book><chapter><label ele-id="5DDE0C5">13</label><title ele-id="E44AB3F">The Word of God in the Liturgy<footnote label="1" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-0BCEF06"><para>I first sketched out this theme in my contribution to the Sixth Theological Conference under the Meissen Agreement between the Church of England and the Evangelischen Kirche in Deutschland (EKD), held at Düsseldorf in 2008 and published in English and German in Christopher Hill, Matthias Kaiser, Leslie Nathaniel and Christoph Schwöbel (eds), <emphasis role="italic">Bereits erreichte Geneinschaft und weitere Schritte: 20 Jahre nach der Meissener Erklärung/ Communion Already Shared and Further Steps: 20 Years after the Meissen Declaration</emphasis> (Frankfurt am Main: Verlag Otto Lembeck, 2010), pp. 197–224.</para></footnote></title><para ele-id="DD64D03">The church treasures, interprets and transmits the truths of revelation, while confessing its complete dependence on the Word of God. It serves revelation as a sort of conduit or channel for it, mediating, communicating and perpetuating it in the world and in history through its typical practices. The church holds the Word in its hands and passes it on in its narrative of salvation history (of which it is itself a part), in its doctrine and catechesis, in the humble work of theology, and above all in its celebration the liturgy and performance of the sacraments, replete as they are with revelatory symbols and narrative structure. This chapter is devoted to exploring this aspect of divine revelation, as the Word of God, in its proper home within the church.</para><section role="H1"><title ele-id="9498A2B"><emphasis role="bold">Liturgy the primary locus of revelation</emphasis></title><para ele-id="FFCD743">Matthew Levering affirms: ‘The liturgy is the primary place in which the Church participates in and interprets the revelation of God.’<footnote label="2" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-0ACDA87"><para>Matthew Levering, <emphasis role="italic">Engaging the Doctrine of Revelation: The Mediation of the Gospel through Church and Scripture</emphasis> (Grand Rapids, MI: Baker Academic, 2014), p. 59. See also Philip Caldwell, <emphasis role="italic">Liturgy as Revelation: Re-Sourcing a Theme in Twentieth-Century Catholic Theology</emphasis> (Minneapolis, MN: Fortress Press, 2014).</para></footnote> The church’s celebration of the liturgy presupposes the reality of divine revelation and would be meaningless without it. The liturgy brings revelation to realisation in our midst in Word and sacrament, both of these means of grace serving as effective, communicative symbols of revelation. There is an intimately symbiotic relationship between liturgy and revelation. Like certain twin stars in a galaxy, they revolve around each other. Latourelle states: ‘What is announced by revelation is accomplished by sacrament.’<footnote label="3" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-C666791"><para>René Latourelle, SJ, <emphasis role="italic">Theology of Revelation</emphasis> (New York: Alba House, 1966), p. 386.</para></footnote> Revelation is kept alive in the church through prayer and praise, through preaching and teaching, that is through the ministry of the Word in its several forms, and in the celebration of the Eucharist with baptism and the other sacraments. The church continually meditates on revelation in prayer, worship and study, thus assimilating it into her collective consciousness.<footnote label="4" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-FF30592"><para>Ibid., p. 306.</para></footnote> The church also witnesses to the fact of revelation and to its central content in the Christ-event, well beyond the boundaries of the church building in its compassionate ministry to the poor, the downtrodden and the victims of injustice and oppression, lifting up a prophetic voice on their behalf in the midst of society and in the name of Christ – and this is also a ministry of the Word.</para></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="9D8F6A5"><emphasis role="bold">Scripture within the liturgy</emphasis></title><para ele-id="C1B4256">Anthony Thiselton, the pioneer and advocate in Anglophone theology of biblical hermeneutics, soundly insisted that 'How we read, understand, interpret, and use biblical texts relates to the very identity of Christian faith and stands at the heart of Christian theology<emphasis role="italic">.’</emphasis><footnote label="5" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-F864E59"><para>A. C. Thiselton, <emphasis role="italic">New Horizons in Hermeneutics</emphasis> (London: Marshall Pickering, 1992), p. 2. In our exploration of the Word of God in relation to divine revelation, and particularly of the second form of the Word, Holy Scripture, we are not able to enter into a discussion of the hermeneutical aspects of the reception of the Word, though these are obviously crucial. A starting point that resonates with the present approach is Gerhard Ebeling, <emphasis role="italic">Word and Faith</emphasis>, trans. James W. Leitch (London: SCM Press, 1963 [1960]), ch. XI, ‘Word of God and Hermeneutics’.</para></footnote><superscript> Alongside Thiselton’s affirmation we may place Stanley Hauerwas’ definition of the church as ‘the community that hears and responds to the Word of God’.</superscript><footnote label="6" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-CB153FD"><para>Stanley Hauerwas, <emphasis role="italic">A Community of Character: Toward a Constructive Christian Social Ethic</emphasis> (Notre Dame, IN: University of Notre Dame Press, 1991).</para></footnote><superscript> But we hardly need these two familiar voices to drive home the truth that the centrality of Scripture, understood as the second form of the Word of God, following Barth’s scheme, is crucial to the nature and purpose of the church. It is axiomatic that, f</superscript>or the integrity of the Christian church, its faithfulness to its calling, few things are more important than the right use of the Bible. By the ‘right use’, I mean using the Scriptures in the manner for which they were intended – that is intended by the authors and editors of the biblical material (who were not always ‘singing from the same hymn-sheet’). But above all, the ‘right use’ is the use that respects what the Scriptures are intended for by the Holy Spirit who, in a mysterious sense, not accessible to empirical investigation, inspired (and inspires) the Scriptures. The mysterious mechanics of the inspiration of Scripture is not on our agenda here, but we may note in passing that (as previously discussed) it is an instance of necessarily inscrutable divine action which involves a double causality, divine and human, and where the causal joint is not discernible. The right use of the Bible respects its nature and purpose: the genres of the literature, the context in which it emerged, the intentions of the authors and the semantics of the text. More than anything, the right use of the Bible honours its role in the salvific purposes of God and for that purpose it is ‘sufficient’ to set us on the road to salvation and to bring us safely to our destination, as I believe all major Christian traditions affirm.<footnote label="7" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-4149068"><para>Timothy Ward, <emphasis role="italic">Word and Supplement: Speech Acts, Biblical Texts, and the Sufficiency of Scripture</emphasis> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2002), is barking up the wrong tree to the extent that he feels the need to defend the sufficiency of Scripture for salvation. Surprisingly, he does not engage with <emphasis role="italic">Dei Verbum</emphasis> of Vatican II.</para></footnote></para><para ele-id="94F3257">However, where there is a ‘right’ use, there is also a ‘wrong’ use. It is obvious to anyone with a sense of history that the ways in which the Bible has been used in the church (both by the institution and by individual Christians) have often left a great deal to be desired and have frequently been highly perverse, even downright iniquitous. The situation seems little better today.<footnote label="8" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-B3855F1"><para>Dennis Nineham,<emphasis role="italic"> The Use and Abuse of the Bible</emphasis> (London: SPCK, 1978 [1976]);<emphasis role="italic"> </emphasis>Adrian Thatcher, <emphasis role="italic">The Savage Text: The Use and Abuse of the Bible</emphasis> (Hoboken, NJ:<emphasis role="bold"> </emphasis>Wiley Blackwell, 2008).</para></footnote> Research undertaken by the University of Cardiff, Wales, UK, and the Bible Society in 2002-3, into the use of the Bible in the United Kingdom, threw up a disturbing picture. It showed that the Bible was generally used by Christian ministers in preaching and teaching in an arbitrary, unfocused and undisciplined way – often merely to reinforce existing practices and prejudices. It showed that many clergy and other ministers, mostly working under pressure, tended to abandon whatever training they may have received in modern biblical scholarship and the hermeneutical arts at their training institution and to revert to a merely devotional, rhetorical and superficial use of Scripture, with little regard for the context, genre, translation and interpretation of biblical texts and passages.<footnote label="9" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-4AF8B26"><para>‘The Use of the Bible in Pastoral Practice’: www.cardiff.ac.uk.</para></footnote></para></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="F379BFB"><emphasis role="bold"><superscript>Responding to biblical naivety</superscript></emphasis></title><para ele-id="18CE571">So the use of the Bible with scholarly integrity, at least as far as one recent survey goes, is rare. I could not advocate the imperative of preaching with scholarly integrity if I did not take it to heart myself. My own practice in preaching undoubtedly falls short of full consistency and lacks some specialist scholarly expertise. But I do at least normally include, at an appropriate point in the sermon, some brief comments about the historical-critical background to the passage(s) that form the lections for that particular Sunday of the Christian Year (and I normally relate my sermon to the readings and to the Sunday, which not every preacher does). So I might touch lightly on such matters as authorship, context and genre, before attempting some necessarily brief exposition and application of the text (with some practical illustrations). In this way, I ‘turn the corner of the page' for those who want to go further in their understanding of the Scriptures and the Christian faith. I have never known any one to be offended by an honest, scholarly, handling of the text in the pulpit, moderated to the level of the congregation of course; quite the reverse. My sense, based on more than half a century of preaching, is that adult congregations resent being patronised and infantilised by being talked to at Sunday-School level – which means in practice being kept completely in the dark about the findings of modern biblical scholarship and interpretation. In my experience most churchgoers do not have a clue about even such basics as ‘the Synoptic problem’ and the priority of Mark or the authorship of John’s Gospel and the Epistles of Peter and Jude (for example) and remain rather embarrassed or nonplussed about patently mythical elements of the Old Testament, such as the two creation accounts of Genesis 1–3. Embarrassed not because they are still struggling to take them literally, but because they are ashamed that many clergy seem unable to speak openly about the mythical genre and function of such narratives in Genesis, let alone the Gospels. My pastoral experience over many years suggests that not a few churchgoers are not even aware that the Old Testament was written in Hebrew and the New Testament in Greek. Their tacit assumption is that divine revelation was given in English!</para><para ele-id="9E57491">However, I find that congregations respond with fascination and with enthusiasm for the Bible when they are treated as intelligent adults and invited to ponder unfamiliar insights. Parish-based Bible-study groups, which are by definition self-selecting, provide an opportunity to go into more depth. There is a shameful lack of honesty and theological integrity about the way that the Bible is used in church. Often it is as though the biblical scholarship of the past two centuries had never happened. Some lay people are hungry to understand the Bible better and so to gain a stronger grasp of the faith. They are not always well served. For example, as far back as 1936, in her autobiographical, stream-of-consciousness work <emphasis role="italic">Novel on Yellow Paper</emphasis>, the poet-turned-novelist Stevie Smith castigated the Church of England for infantilising its congregations by talking down to them and reinforcing their ignorance, thus deservedly (she judged) stupifying itself even more in the process. The church should, Stevie Smith insisted, stretch its people by employing ‘high’ notions that people would struggle to grasp and in that struggle they might apprehend the essential mystery of Christianity.<footnote label="10" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-2CA4110"><para>Stevie Smith, <emphasis role="italic">Novel on Yellow Paper</emphasis> (London: Virago, 1980 [1936]), pp. 173–9.</para></footnote></para></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="F226A1F"><emphasis role="bold">The Bible and the Word of God</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36B80E1">It is incontestable that the Bible is fundamental to Christian existence in every way. We do not need to be Fundamentalists or bibliolaters to affirm that. The Bible inspires and informs the content of our prayers and hymns. It provides the very substance and texture of preaching and teaching – or should do so. It guides and shapes the pastoral care that is offered. The sacraments of the gospel have their mandate in Scripture and the liturgy is a tissue of biblical expressions and allusions. The Bible is also constitutive of the work of Christian theology, for much of the substance of theology consists of biblical exegesis – though obviously biblical study is not the only form of theology. Biblical exegesis has been a key task of the church from the beginning. It received fresh impetus from the Renaissance and the Reformation through the recovery of ancient texts in their original languages – the power of the word – and is now central to most major historical traditions. There is a continuum of scholarly biblical study running from the early sixteenth century, through the Enlightenment and nineteenth- and twentieth-century scholarship, to the present. The sixteenth-century Renaissance scholars, Erasmus, Luther and Calvin, are still cited by modern commentators: they were critical scholars according to their lights at the time (though obviously lacking many key skills according to ours). The Protestant Reformers carried forward their cause very largely by detailed work on the biblical text, polemical and tendentious though their writings often were. We might think particularly of Luther's, Bucer's and Calvin's biblical lectures and commentaries, especially Luther's pivotal<emphasis role="italic"> Lectures on Romans</emphasis> of 1515 and the<emphasis role="italic"> </emphasis>multi-volume commentary on Genesis of his last years, and Calvin's commentaries on every book of the Bible except Revelation.<footnote label="11" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-7F95CF9"><para>For the Reformers on Scripture see Paul Avis, <emphasis role="italic">In Search of Authority: Anglican Theological Method from the Reformation to the Enlightenment</emphasis> (London and New York: T&#x0026;T Clark, 2014), chs 1 and 2.</para></footnote> We might also consider how that trajectory continues in Dietrich Bonhoeffer's turn to the Scriptures, particularly in <emphasis role="italic">The Cost of Discipleship</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">Life Together</emphasis> and Karl Barth's extraordinary commentary (one that is not a commentary by any normal reckoning) on Romans, more conventionally on John 1–8, and the sustained, detailed biblical exegesis that runs through his multi-volume <emphasis role="italic">Church Dogmatics</emphasis> and its predecessors in Barth’s theological career.</para><para ele-id="689C6E4">From the Anglican stable, I would include, from the same period as Bonhoeffer and Barth (the first half of the twentieth century): Lionel Thornton, CR, on biblical typology and the theology of revelation; Edwyn Hoskyns on the Fourth Gospel and the theology of the New Testament; and the early work of Michael Ramsey, eventually Archbishop of Canterbury, especially his <emphasis role="italic">The Gospel and the Catholic Church</emphasis> (1936). Hoskyns, who translated the second edition of Barth's commentary on <emphasis role="italic">Romans</emphasis> into English, echoes Barth's famous saying about the thrill and challenge of discovering ‘the new world within the Bible’. Hoskyns asked: 'Can we rescue a word and discover a universe? Can we study a language and awake to the Truth? Can we bury ourselves in a lexicon and arise in the presence of God?'<footnote label="12" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-39F4091"><para>Karl Barth, <emphasis role="italic">The Word of God and the Word of Man</emphasis>, trans. D. Horton (London: Hodder and Stoughton, n.d.), ch. 2: ‘The Strange New World within the Bible’ [lecture given 1916]. ‘Strange’ was added in the English translation. E. C. Hoskyns, <emphasis role="italic">Cambridge Sermons</emphasis> (London: SPCK, 1970), p. 70.</para></footnote> Hoskyns and Ramsey (together perhaps with John Robinson and Alan Richardson) represented the best of the Biblical Theology movement in its impact on the Church of England and we are still rewarded when we turn to them. In all these biblical expositors, from the Reformers to recent times, we see a passion for the Word of God in Scripture at work for the redemption of the world. I trust that the present work reflects some of the theological passion for the Word of God.</para><para ele-id="13C4756">The Bible has a foundational and irreplaceable role in every aspect of Christianity, not simply because because of its function as an authoritative text for an institution, but because through that text God's Word, Jesus Christ, shines out. In the gospel the essentially hidden God shines forth: 'the light of the gospel of the glory of Christ who is the image of God' (2 Cor. 4.4). It is the nature of the hidden God to reveal Godself without dispelling the mystery. 'God is light and in him is no darkness at all' (1 Jn 1.5). Luther spoke of<emphasis role="italic"> deus loquens</emphasis> and Barth affirms that 'The true and living God is eloquent and radiant.'<footnote label="13" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-77788C8"><para>Barth, <emphasis role="italic">CD</emphasis>, IV/3, p. 79, cited J. Webster, <emphasis role="italic">Confessing God</emphasis> (London and New York: T&#x0026;T Clark, 2005), p. 40.</para></footnote> Through the Word, God is continually communicating and revealing Godself to us for our eternal good and beatitude. But the Bible and the Word of God are not exactly synonymous. The Scriptures are the privileged vehicle and medium of God's self-communication to humankind. It is primarily in and through the Scriptures that we hear and receive the Word of God, Jesus Christ. It is in and through the Scriptures that God's Word reaches out to us, speaks to us, indwells and transforms us – and this is true of private Bible reading and private theological study and also applies to the liturgical proclamation of the Scriptures which is our main topic here.</para><para ele-id="83B6CB3">When we speak of the Bible as 'the Word of God', we do so properly and justifiably – but by analogy or in a figure. If the primary Word (<emphasis role="italic">Logos</emphasis>) of God incarnate is Jesus Christ, then the canonical texts that speak of him, testify to him and proclaim him, cannot be identified absolutely with him. There is closeness, but also distance; sameness, but also difference; unity, but also distinction. Certainly the Hebrew Bible speaks of the Torah and of the prophetic oracles as God's word or 'the word of YHWH’ (in most English-language Bibles translated as ‘the LORD'). In the New Testament, especially in Paul, the Word of God is often identified with the proclamation of the gospel (<emphasis role="italic">kerygma</emphasis>) and becomes a synonym for it, 'gospel' and 'word' being juxtaposed in grammatical apposition (I Thess. 2.9, 13; 1 Cor. 1.17-18; 2 Cor. 4.2-3). However, when our studies immerse us in the cultural, social and other historically contingent aspects of the Bible, it becomes more difficult in practice to equate the biblical text with the Word of God, one-to-one. Such studies bring home to us the fact that the anthropology, psychology, gender-identity, cosmology, historiography and eschatology of the Bible, to name just a few of the more striking aspects, are not ones that we can meaningfully share. Like Barth, I want to do full justice to the human, historical aspects of the biblical text, while still affirming that Scripture is rightly called the Word of God, though not the Word of God exclusively or exhaustively. In Barth, as we have previously noted, the Bible is one of the three forms taken by the Word, the first, definitive and determinative form being Jesus Christ, to whom the Scriptures (the second form) bear witness; the church's proclamation being the third form which must be faithful to Scripture and therefore to Christ.<footnote label="14" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-EAA95B9"><para>K. Barth, <emphasis role="italic">CD</emphasis>, I/1, 4, pp. 88ff.</para></footnote> As Barth sees it, the Bible becomes the Word of God through God's sovereign action, because 'in this event the human prophetic and apostolic word is a representative of God's Word'.<footnote label="15" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-FAB2982"><para>Ibid., p. 109.</para></footnote> The Bible is the Word of God, according to Barth, 'to the extent that God causes it to be his Word, to the extent that he speaks through it'.<footnote label="16" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-4272074"><para>Ibid.</para></footnote><superscript> Barth’s stance here seems to play up the latency or potentiality of the Bible as the Word of God to an exaggerated extent and to play down, to an unnecessary degree, the fact that the Holy Spirit consistently, in many diverse circumstances, in all cultures and languages, does own the Scriptures and does speak to human hearts and minds through them. Webster, for all that he owes to Barth, avoids the latter’s occasionalism and the precarious contingency of holding that Scripture becomes from time to time the Word of God, when he writes: ‘Extending himself into the structures and practices of human communication in the sending of the Holy Spirit, the divine Word commissions and sanctifies these texts to become fitting vehicles of his self-proclamation. He draws their acts into his own act of self-utterance, so that they become the words of the Word, human words uttered as a repetition of the divine Word, existing in the sphere of the divine Word’s authority, effectiveness and promise.’</superscript><footnote label="17" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-06DA41B"><para>John Webster, <emphasis role="italic">The Domain of the Word: Scripture and Theological Reason </emphasis>(London and New York: T&#x0026;T Clark, 2012), p. 8.</para></footnote></para></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="FF4F5D7"><emphasis role="bold"><superscript>Words and the Word</superscript></emphasis></title><para ele-id="23CFACC"><superscript>How can we affirm that the Scriptures contain, mediate and convey the Word of God, Jesus Christ, that they are conduits of revelation, sacramental of the Word? How can such everyday, common-or-garden things as the words that we form in our minds and utter all day long be sacramental of divinely-revealed truth? What enables human words to mediate divine revelation is the fact that words are created signs and bear the potentiality imparted to them by their Creator. As created realities, words have the capacity to participate in the reality which they signify, just as the bread and wine of Holy Communion participate in the Body and Blood of Christ, making them present to faith in the celebration of the Eucharist. Let us not fall into the pitiful mistake of supposing that because words are everyday human matters they cannot mediate divine truths.</superscript><footnote label="18" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-1227BEB"><para>Cf. the comments on Ibid., p. 59.</para></footnote><superscript> What could be more ordinary and down to earth than bread (for those in our unequal world who are fortunate to have enough of it)? Yet Christ chose it to signify our participation in (the sacrifice of) himself. ‘Blessed are you, Lord God of all creation: through your goodness we have this bread to set before you, which earth has given and human hands have made. It will become for us the bread of life.’ And let us not think that, because the divinely created gift of words is often abused, words do not participate, through their created, God-given nature, in the realities that they signify. What could be more abused than alcohol, when it leads to a consuming addiction eventuating in drunken rages, and loss of self-control in word and deed, eventuating in harm to persons and things and bringing in the end sickness and death? Yet Christ chose wine to signify the shedding of his blood in atoning sacrifice. So it is with words, with the gift of speech. ‘With [the tongue] we bless the Lord and Father, and with it we curse those who are made in the likeness of God. From the same mouth come blessing and cursing’ (Jas. 3.1–12, at 9–10a).</superscript></para><para ele-id="DF69472"><superscript>At this point we are seeking to retrieve a semiotic tradition that runs from Augustine through Aquinas to Coleridge and to modern sacramental theology and affirms the revelatory potentiality of words as signs. The poet and artist David Jones put it memorably when he averred that, in the Incarnation, the Logos ‘entered the realm of signs’.</superscript><footnote label="19" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-FCFFAAA"><para>David Jones, ‘Art and Sacrament’, in id., <emphasis role="italic">Epoch and Artist</emphasis> (London: Faber and Faber, 1959 [1955]).</para></footnote><superscript>But the realm of signs is also and as such the realm of the interpretation of signs, of hermeneutics. As Webster puts it, ‘The Word elects to enter the realm of signs, and thereby the realm of their interpretation.’</superscript><footnote label="20" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-64A6B6C"><para>Webster, <emphasis role="italic">The Domain of the Word</emphasis>, p. 24. See also on this broad theme: Stephen Prickett, <emphasis role="italic">Words and the Word: Language, Poetics and Biblical Interpretation</emphasis> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1986).</para></footnote><superscript> All signs are by nature over-determined – the freight that they carry is a surplus, an excess, of possible meanings – and their interpretation is therefore inevitably contested. But for the church, which hears the Word of God, and for the work of biblical exegesis within the sphere of ecclesial faith, the hard work of the interpretation of Scripture is an act of discipleship and obedience, an expression of communion with Christ, and an episode in the continuing history of God’s reconciliation of the world. We are drawn further into the revealing-reconciling economy of grace in the act and process of discerning and interpreting and pondering the substantive content of Scripture.</superscript><footnote label="21" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-48DFC58"><para>Cf. Webster, <emphasis role="italic">The Domain of the Word</emphasis>, p. 48.</para></footnote></para></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="D658626"><emphasis role="bold"><superscript>The Primacy of the Word Incarnate</superscript></emphasis></title><para ele-id="2021AE5">The three forms of the Word of God are not on the same level. There is a hierarchy of forms of the Word. Divine revelation in the Word that is Jesus Christ is not derived from any other or any prior source, except within the being, nature and purposes of God. The original and originating revelation in Jesus Christ is self-standing, autonomous. There is an infinite qualitative distinction (to use the language of Kierkegaard and the early Barth) between the Word that is Jesus Christ and the second and third forms of the Word. Scripture, in its character as witness to and mediator of the Word that is Jesus Christ, is derived from that revelation and depends on that primary act of God's self-communication. So although the Bible has often been treated by Christians in a frankly idolatrous way, as though it were the first and last word of divine revelation, Scripture is not self-standing and is not autonomous; it is derivative of the work of the incarnate Logos. Furthermore, the church's proclamation, the third form of the Word, is doubly derivative and dependent, in that it takes its substance and content from Scripture which itself is wholly dependent on the primary Word of God that is Jesus Christ.<footnote label="22" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-2FF0878"><para>Barth, <emphasis role="italic">CD</emphasis>, I/1, p. 117: ‘revelation is originally and directly what the Bible and church proclamation are derivatively and indirectly, i.e. God's Word’; p. 102 stresses ‘the supremacy, the absolute constitutive significance’ of Scripture for the church's proclamation.</para></footnote><superscript> Nevertheless, our agenda now is to affirm the true Word-nature of the church’s proclamation in the modes of liturgy and pastoral care. S</superscript>o, in order to explicate the role of the Word in the third form, proclamation, we now return to the theme of the Threefold Word of God, but we do so from a different angle and perspective from that adopted earlier. In this chapter we are looking at the action of the Word in the celebration of the liturgy considered as a primary expression of the church’s proclamation. In all that follows, we aim to show the primacy of the Word that is Jesus Christ, the original and originating Word, but also the true Word-nature of the liturgy.</para><para ele-id="22E4DD7">In its transcendence and autonomy the original and originating revelation is the primary form of the Word (the Logos) of God, 'the Word itself', as Barth puts it.<footnote label="23" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-1AAC519"><para>Ibid., p. 118.</para></footnote> 'The Word of God is uncreated reality, identical with God.'<footnote label="24" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-7406B2C"><para>Ibid., p. 158.</para></footnote> The Scriptures then become the secondary, dependent, form of the Word of God, to be distinguished from the primary revelation which is Jesus Christ, though closely aligned with it.<footnote label="25" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-CD6903B"><para>Barth, <emphasis role="italic">CD</emphasis>, I/2, p. 463.</para></footnote> The actual biblical text is an empirical public fact, open to the whole world’s scrutiny, though many areas of uncertainty and instability surround it as a text, as a human artifact. Divine revelation as the action of the Logos in the world (Jn 1.1-5, 10), is, however, not an empirically identifiable entity; it is a transcendent reality that is postulated by faith on the basis of the scriptural witness and the church's proclamation. The Scriptures are the Word of God because they witness to, embody and mediate God's self-communication, which in itself always remains transcendent, surpassing human thought and speech. So the Word of God, as it impacts the world and human lives, is not without words, but it is much more than words. The Word is an active personal power that conveys God's presence and effects God's purpose (cf. Gen. 1; Isa. 55.10-11). God's <emphasis role="italic">creative</emphasis> Word brought the heavens and the earth into being; God's <emphasis role="italic">redeeming</emphasis> Word entered the world humanly and bodily in Jesus Christ; God's <emphasis role="italic">sanctifying</emphasis> Word is at work in the church through the action of the Holy Spirit.<footnote label="26" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-9936E7B"><para>Cf. André Birmelé, art. ‘Word of God’, in N. Lossky et al. (eds), <emphasis role="italic">Dictionary of the Ecumenical Movement</emphasis> (Geneva: World Council of Churches, 1991), pp. 1072–6.</para></footnote> Nevertheless, there is only one Word. As Barth so often insists, God's Word is God's work.<footnote label="27" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-3B01D49"><para>E.g. Barth, <emphasis role="italic">CD</emphasis>, I/1, pp. 143ff.</para></footnote> And Christian theology holds that the triune God’s work in the world (<emphasis role="italic">ad extra</emphasis>) is indivisible.</para><para ele-id="C234721">The Word of God is, then, primarily and definitively, the person of Jesus Christ, the now and forever incarnate Logos<emphasis role="italic"> (</emphasis>Jn 1.3); secondly it is the biblical writings which point to or speak of him; thirdly it takes the form of the proclamation (<emphasis role="italic">kerygma</emphasis>) of the church, grounded in the Scriptures and faithfully and consistently pointing to Jesus Christ. We hear that Word in and through the Scriptures, studied, read in church and preached. But we also find God's Word embodied in the sacraments, as visible words and effectual channels and vehicles of saving grace.<footnote label="28" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-4DB35BD"><para>Barth, ibid., p. 56. Barth also mentions liturgy in general, the sacraments and hymnody as forms of proclamation. Because a future volume in this personal series of Fundamental Theology is devoted to the sacraments (<emphasis role="italic">The Sacraments of the Gospel and the Sacramentality of the Church</emphasis>), I am holding back on sacramental theology here.</para></footnote> The Word is also ministered to us in pastoral care as another but connected vehicle of proclamation grounded in Scripture and conveying the grace of Christ the Word to those who receive it. So we can affirm that it is through the church's ministry of word, sacrament and pastoral care (‘the cure of souls’), taken together, that the triune God carries out the work of our salvation. Each of these ministries is constituted, given its mandate and rationale, by the Word of God, coming to us in and through the Bible as it has been handed down and at the same time interpreted and taught (‘traditioned’) in the church.<footnote label="29" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-78C9687"><para>The Meissen Common Statement affirms that the church is constituted and sustained by the Triune God through God’s saving action in word and sacrament and that ‘a ministry of pastoral <emphasis role="italic">oversight (episkope)</emphasis>, exercised in personal, collegial and communal ways, is necessary to witness to and safeguard the unity and apostolicity of the church’ (<emphasis role="italic">The Meissen Agreement</emphasis> (London: The Council for Christian Unity, 1992), p. 18; cf. pp. 15, vii, ix.</para></footnote></para><para ele-id="0ECF116">Thus the content of the Word of God for us is Jesus Christ as he is found in the Bible. It is by reference to him that we know that what we receive is God's Word. As the Barmen Declaration (1934) of the German Confessing Church unforgettably expressed it: 'Jesus Christ, as he is attested to us in Holy Scripture, is the one Word of God whom we have to hear, and whom we have to trust and obey in life and in death.'<footnote label="30" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-0DF5888"><para>Echoing Zwingli’s Berne Theses of 1528, Article 1: ‘The holy Christian church, whose sole Head is Christ, is born of the Word of God, is incorporated in the same, and hears not the voice of a stranger’ (cited Barth, <emphasis role="italic">CD</emphasis>, I/1, p. 151).</para></footnote> Jesus Christ cannot be found and known without the Bible, yet he infinitely transcends it as text, bursting through its limitations. Luther said that both the Old Testament and the New preach Christ. That is because they point, in their character as witness, to the Word of God who is none other than Jesus Christ. It does not mean that both Testaments point with equal clarity and explicitness to Christ, or that the content of either Testament is exhausted by that ultimate focus in Christ; they contain material which does not so point, at least not at all directly. Not only in its sublime passages, but with all of its human imperfection and with all of its – sometimes – earthy roughness and even blasphemous attribution of iniquitous and criminous commands to God – the Bible is (to quote Luther) the manger in which Christ lies and the Scriptures are the 'swaddling clothes' in which he is wrapped and partly obscured.<footnote label="31" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-4DBE39D"><para>Cited Barth, <emphasis role="italic">CD</emphasis>, I/1, p. 123, from Luther, <emphasis role="italic">Sermon on Luke 2</emphasis>,<emphasis role="italic"> WA</emphasis>, 12, p. 418, l. 24.</para></footnote> The Scriptures belong to the realm of creaturely reality and God's revelation always comes to us, as Barth insisted, clothed in the garments of creaturely reality.<footnote label="32" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-2DA37B8"><para>Emphasised by T. F. Torrance, <emphasis role="italic">Karl Barth: An Introduction to his Early Theology 1910</emphasis>–<emphasis role="italic">1931 </emphasis>(London: SCM Press, 1962). Discussion in P. Avis, <emphasis role="italic">The Methods of Modern Theology</emphasis> (Basingstoke: Marshall Pickering, 1986), ch. 3.</para></footnote> In striking contrast to Luther’s homely concreteness, John Webster calls the Scriptures 'the sanctified creaturely auxiliary of the communicative presence of God'.<footnote label="33" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-99C9599"><para>Webster, <emphasis role="italic">Confessing God</emphasis>, pp. 46f; see further id., <emphasis role="italic">The Domain of the Word</emphasis>.</para></footnote></para></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="128E189"><emphasis role="bold"><superscript>The temporal mission of the Word</superscript></emphasis></title><para ele-id="C5D5BCA">The past, present and future of created time are the sphere of action of the Word of God through the Holy Spirit. (a) <emphasis role="italic">Past </emphasis>The Word of God has been at work in the world since creation, ‘<emphasis role="italic">en arche</emphasis>; in the beginning’, a moment for which a date could never be given (Gen. 1.1; Jn 1.1). Since ‘the beginning’, God has not left Godself without witness at any time (Acts 14.27). In many and various ways, in times past, God spoke God’s Word to our fathers and mothers through the prophets (Heb. 1.1) because the prophets have been since the world began (Lk 1.70, KJB/AV, BCP), but now God’s Word has been given in a Son. (b<emphasis role="italic">) Present </emphasis>The Scriptures witness to this Word spoken in past times, but they witness not in an external and detached way, as though they were something separate from the Word, but because they themselves are the channel and medium of God's Word, so in a sense (which we have tried to elucidate) become and are God’s Word. The Scriptures mediate the Word as its vehicle or channel, though the Word cannot be trapped in the words on the page. The Word of God is active in the world today as a contemporary event, especially in the church’s exposition of the Scriptures, the proclamation of the gospel by every appropriate means, the celebration of the sacraments, and the church’s outreach to the needy and oppressed. The sovereign Word continues its work far and wide in the world and in human hearts and lives. (c<emphasis role="italic">) Future</emphasis> In the Word, as God's performative speech, lies the only future for the church and for the whole creation. It is through the Word, active in the world in the power of the Holy Spirit, that the eschatological fulfilment of God's purposes will come to pass. 'He upholds all things by his powerful word' (Heb. 1.3). As Barth says: 'The Word of God is the Word that God <emphasis role="italic">spoke, speaks,</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">will speak</emphasis> in the midst of all men [sic].'<footnote label="34" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-E294F74"><para>Karl Barth, <emphasis role="italic">Evangelical Theology: An Introduction</emphasis>, trans. Grover Foley (London: Collins/Fontana, 1965 [1963]), p. 22. I would not use the biblical language of God’s speech without noting the significance of its anthropomorphic character, which I have attempted briefly earlier in this study.</para></footnote></para></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="C0ADABD"><emphasis role="bold">The external Word and the internal Word</emphasis></title><para ele-id="42C45ED">The distinction between the external Word and the internal Word is familiar and has its uses, but we should not hold the two apart or play off one against the other; both are needed and have their part to play in God’s address to the world. As well as the external, audible Word, drawn from the Scriptures and heard in preaching, sacraments and pastoral care, there is the internal, mystical, Word from God that only the Holy Spirit can speak to the human heart and which alone can quicken the human spirit into receptivity and faith – though the possibility remains that it can be denied and refused with calamitous consequences for one’s spiritual state and destiny. The theme of the internal, secret, vivifying and judging Word runs through the Bible, from Moses addressing Pharaoh, whose heart God had hardened, through the promise in Jeremiah of a heart of flesh, in place of a heart of stone, that would spontaneously keep God's commandments, to Jesus’ parable of the sower, where some seed did not penetrate the surface of the ground, to Paul's affirmation that God has shone in the hearts of believers. The internal and external word must be distinguished without being divided (to use a Coleridgean expression). The one is not given without the other. Paul makes the distinction which is also the connection when he says: 'We proclaim Jesus Christ as Lord ... For it is the God who said, “Let light shine out of darkness”, who has shone in our hearts to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jesus Christ' (2 Cor. 4.5-6). The external, audible word of proclamation has to be matched by the internal, secret illumination of the heart.</para><para ele-id="5D1E110">Augustine, following Paul, has an acute awareness of the way that God speaks through the words of human instruments and of the need for grace to enable the heart to respond. Through his saintly mother Monica, God was steadfastly admonishing him to reform his life, yet her words did not at the time penetrate his heart.<footnote label="35" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-3ECF546"><para>Augustine, <emphasis role="italic">Confessions</emphasis>, trans. R. S. Pine Coffin (Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1961), p. 46 (Book II, 3).</para></footnote><superscript> Thomas Aquinas states the distinction between the twofold speaking and hearing thus: ‘One is exterior, whereby God speaks to us through preachers, the other is interior whereby he speaks to us by inner inspiration.’ Aquinas further explains the interior Word: ‘This inner inspiration is termed speech by analogy ... God by interiorly inspiring us does not show his essence for us to see, but some signs of it, some spiritual likeness of his wisdom.’</superscript><footnote label="36" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-382EF2E"><para>Thomas Aquinas, <emphasis role="italic">De veritate</emphasis>, XVIII, 3, cited Aquinas, <emphasis role="italic">ST</emphasis>, vol. 1 (Ia. I, Appendix 7; p. 89).</para></footnote><superscript> Thus there is the outward sign that points to the truth that we need to hear; and there is the inward sign which has explosive, generative, power to transform both our thinking and our lives.</superscript></para><para ele-id="06CFA46">We see the distinction between the external and the internal Word operating existentially in the life and writings of Simone Weil. For her, none of the promises that Christ made to the institutional church could equal the force of the expression 'Your Father who sees in secret' (Mt. 6.4, 6). Brought up by completely non-Christian parents and without contact with the Christian faith, the young Simone Weil had felt the power of the secret, internal, Word. She wanted to live for Christ and frankly longed to die for him, but she remained unconvinced in conscience that she should obey the outward Word and be baptised and so join the (Roman Catholic) church. She protested that God was not calling her to that; the path of obedience did not lead to institutional affiliation and outward conformity. But we should heed what she affirms about the internal Word: '[T]he word of God is the secret word. He who has not heard this word, even if he adheres to all the dogmas taught by the church, has no contact with truth’.<footnote label="37" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-0CE79A3"><para>Simone Weil, <emphasis role="italic">Waiting on God</emphasis>, trans. Emma Crauford (London: Fontana, 1951), p. 46.</para></footnote><superscript> </superscript>Weil's testimony resonates with what the Fourth Gospel says about the mysterious work of the Spirit, moving and working invisibly like the wind, with only its effects being seen (John 3.8).</para><para ele-id="C23D778">Like St Paul, Martin Luther speaks of the Word shining into a person's heart.<footnote label="38" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-DC3A0BC"><para>Luther, <emphasis role="italic">WA</emphasis>, 32, 343; <emphasis role="italic">LW</emphasis>, vol.<emphasis role="italic"> </emphasis>21, p. 55, cited Paul Althaus, <emphasis role="italic">The Theology of Martin Luther</emphasis>, trans. from 2nd German edn by R. C. Shultz (Philadelphia: Fortress Press, 1966), p. 36, n. 6.</para></footnote><superscript> </superscript>In <emphasis role="italic">The Bondage of the Will</emphasis>, Luther distinguishes between the external and the internal clarity (<emphasis role="italic">claritas</emphasis>) or perspicuity of Scripture. External clarity refers to the public ministry of the Word: the biblical message of salvation is abundantly clear in the sense that we understand the meaning of the words, we know what the text means; it is not ‘double Dutch’. Internal clarity, on the other hand, concerns 'the knowledge of the heart' because the Holy Spirit is needed to give heartfelt understanding of Scripture.<footnote label="39" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-07E7818"><para>Martin Luther, <emphasis role="italic">The Bondage of the Will</emphasis>, trans. J. R. Packer and O. R. Johnston (London: James Clarke, 1957), pp. 71–2.</para></footnote> However, Luther's practical emphasis is definitely on the external Word. For Luther, the Holy Spirit works in and through the external Word and not apart from it. The preached Word goes before the secret operation of the Spirit. Provoked by the fanatics, whose cultivation of enhanced spiritual states and private revelations smacked of works-righteousness and seemed to confuse human and divine action, Luther says the opposite of what Simone Weil believes for herself when he insists: 'God will not come to you in your private room and speak to you. He has therefore arranged that the external word should be preached and go before – so that after a man has heard the word with his ears and grasped it with his heart, the Holy Spirit, the real teacher, comes and gives power to the word so that it takes hold.'<footnote label="40" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-D2DA194"><para>Luther, <emphasis role="italic">W</emphasis><emphasis role="italic">A</emphasis>, 17 II, 459f, cited Althaus, <emphasis role="italic">The Theology of Martin Luther</emphasis>, p. 37. See also the discussion in Barth, <emphasis role="italic">CD</emphasis>, I/1, p. 70, with citations from Luther.</para></footnote> In this way the external Word becomes the internal Word. For Luther, the connection between the external and the internal domains is vital in order for the mission of the Word to be accomplished, for 'if God remains silent, the final effect is as though nothing had been said’.<footnote label="41" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-FBC2272"><para>Luther, <emphasis role="italic">WA</emphasis>, 10 III, 260; <emphasis role="italic">WA,</emphasis> 17 II, 174, cited Althaus, <emphasis role="italic">The Theology of Martin Luther</emphasis>, p. 39.</para></footnote> But Luther recognises that the presence of the Word in the heart is self-authenticating; there is an internal testimony of the Holy Spirit. 'Everyone may be certain of the gospel when he has the testimony of the Holy Spirit in his own person that this is the gospel.'<footnote label="42" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-F16C1BC"><para>Luther, <emphasis role="italic">WA</emphasis>, 30 II, 687f and n. 13, cited Althaus, <emphasis role="italic">The Theology of Martin Luther</emphasis>, p. 38.</para></footnote></para><para ele-id="2BB4567">John Calvin echoes this idea (but in the context of the credibility of Scripture, rather than, as with Luther, the effectiveness of preaching) with his concept of the 'inward testimony of the Spirit' (<emphasis role="italic">testimonium</emphasis> <emphasis role="italic">spiritus sancti </emphasis><emphasis role="italic">internum)</emphasis> which alone can add the certainty of faith to the truth of the Scriptures. 'The same Spirit, therefore, who spoke by the mouth of the [biblical] prophets, must penetrate our hearts, in order to convince us that they faithfully delivered the message with which they were divinely entrusted.' When the Holy Spirit does testify to our spirits that Scripture is (as Calvin sees it) the Word of God, then we begin to 'feel a divine energy living and breathing in it – an energy by which we are drawn and animated to obey it, willingly indeed and knowingly, but more vividly and effectually than could be done by human will or knowledge’.<footnote label="43" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-17EAE15"><para>John Calvin, <emphasis role="italic">Institutes of the Christian Religion</emphasis>, trans. Henry Beveridge (London: James Clarke, 1962), vol. 1, pp. 72–3 [I, vii, 4–5].</para></footnote></para><para ele-id="36D9A11">Classical Anglican writers since the seventeenth century (e.g. Bishop Robert Sanderson, Bishop Joseph Butler, John Henry Newman) have stressed the role of the informed conscience as the place where (in our terms) the internal and external Word come together, where there is discernment and a call to obedience. Conscience is the voice of God, but it needs to be educated and trained and it is here that biblical teaching, ministered by the church, has a vital place. At the end of the day, conscience must always be followed. To go against one's conscience, even if it is misguided in certain respects, is to make moral and spiritual shipwreck.<footnote label="44" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-271DE18"><para>H. R. McAdoo, <emphasis role="italic">The Structure of Caroline Moral Theology</emphasis> (London: Longmans, Green &#x0026; Co., 1949); Peter H. Sedgwick, <emphasis role="italic">The Development of Anglican Moral Theology 1680–1950</emphasis> (Leiden: Brill, 2023).</para></footnote></para><para ele-id="A5F4B77"><superscript>The distinction between the external and the internal Word of God has something to say to all preachers. We should fulfil our calling by preaching the biblical message, opening up the scriptural Word in faithful, informed exposition; and we should trust the Holy Spirit, the original inspirer of that Word, to apply it to the hearts and minds of the hearers as the sovereign Spirit chooses. Preachers do not need to strive officiously to make the message ‘real’ or ‘relevant’. They do not need a repertoire of rhetorical tricks to dress it up. They should never work themselves into a fever or a frenzy. A sermon is not an exercise in anxiety and stress.</superscript><footnote label="45" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-56AE1F8"><para>Cf. the comments of Webster, <emphasis role="italic">The Domain of the Word</emphasis>, p. 26.</para></footnote><superscript> Let the Word, external and internal, do its work. A well-meaning preacher of my acquaintance often begins the sermon with not one but two humorous stories, no doubt downloaded from a website of religious jokes, though without any obvious connection with the biblical lections of the day or with the theme of the body of the sermon to follow – just to make the congregation smile and pay attention. It may have worked at first, but it soon wore thin; congregational disappointment and frustration supervened. Another dedicated priest, whose ministry I otherwise respect, habitually preaches without doing more than making a passing allusion to the readings or even the great theme of the day; his sermons are typically devoid of biblical exposition. When the external Word is absent, how can the internal Word do its work? ‘The hungry sheep look up, and are not fed.’</superscript><footnote label="46" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-98A51F0"><para>John Milton, ‘Lycidas’ (1638), in John Milton, <emphasis role="italic">The English Poems of John Milton</emphasis>, ed. H. C. Beeching (London: Oxford University Press, 1913), pp. 34–9, at p. 37 (l. 6).</para></footnote></para></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="2BD2BF6"><emphasis role="bold">The Word in the liturgy</emphasis><footnote label="47" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-7D7F804"><para>Among much that has been written on this topic, I am particularly indebted to the illuminating work of: Juliette J. Day, <emphasis role="italic">Reading the Liturgy: An Exploration of Texts in Christian Worship</emphasis> (London and New York: T&#x0026;T Clark, 2014); Cally Hammond, <emphasis role="italic">The Sound of the Liturgy: How Words Work in Worship</emphasis> (London: SPCK, 2015); David Jasper, <emphasis role="italic">The Language of Liturgy: A Ritual Poetics</emphasis> (London: SCM Press, 2018); Nicholas Wolterstorff,<emphasis role="italic"> Acting Liturgically: Philosophical Reflections on Religious Practice</emphasis> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2018); Victoria Raymer, <emphasis role="italic">The Bible in Worship: Proclamation, Encounter and Response</emphasis> (London: SCM Press, 2018); Gordon Jeanes and Bridget Nichols (eds), <emphasis role="italic">Lively Oracles of God: Perspectives on the Bible and Liturgy</emphasis> (Collegeville: MN, Liturgical Press, 2022).</para></footnote></title><para ele-id="C0F5042">How are the Word, the liturgy and pastoral care connected? In the practice of Christian life and ministry they are seamlessly related, bound together in a biblical-liturgical-pastoral nexus. Through this constellation of key means of grace God the Holy Trinity calls us, speaks to us a saving Word and carries forward the work of making us whole. The human imagination is the locus of this salvific event because we are addressed by God at the level of the imagination (though not only there), that is to say creatively and poetically, and our response is infused with imaginative, aesthetic elements (though the moral component is also crucial). Imagination – the totality of the person at its most profound and creative level – is the privileged site of divine-human encounter and engagement, though it goes without saying that the Holy Spirit remains free and sovereign to approach the human subject in any way that ‘seems good to the Holy Spirit’ (Acts 15.28).<footnote label="48" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-5D38B6D"><para>Paul Avis, <emphasis role="italic">God and the Creative Imagination: Metaphor, Symbol and Myth in Religion and Theology</emphasis> (London and New York: Routledge, 1999).</para></footnote></para><para ele-id="FC58976">In the church’s liturgy, just as in Scripture, there is a divine-human interface and rapport in the form of dialogue; the logic of the liturgy is one of mutual involvement and mutual self-giving, the self-giving of the loving, gracious God to God’s children and the self-giving of God’s children to God and to one another in communion. God addresses us through the ministry of the Word, read, preached, prayed, sung and sacramentally symbolised. We return our answer to God in the words of the same liturgy. The liturgy is also our human response to the Word and call of God. Yet we can only respond in the words that God has already given us, words based on Scripture. We are blessed when we answer the Word with the Word. So we are caught up into the eternal movement of the self-offering of the incarnate, risen and glorified Word to the Father in the Spirit. Through this dialogue, this verbal and ritual dance, we enter by grace ever more deeply into the Logos, the mind of God, being conformed over time to ‘the mind of Christ’ (1 Cor. 2.16).</para><para ele-id="32B6793">In all this work, we are interpreting Scripture simply by using it. The liturgical use of Scripture is one of the most significant acts of biblical interpretation that we know. A continuous creative process of reception and creative appropriation is going on. However, there is no need to be pedantic about this: the way that biblical texts or simple allusions function in liturgy is not the same as the way that they function in Scripture itself. In liturgy some poetic licence is appropriate; there is no need to be completely hamstrung by academic scruples. The liturgy is a performed text, an enacted text, a dramatic rendition. The words on the page are brought to life as they are incorporated into architecture (sacred space), music, vesture and dramatic action – and simultaneously reflected back to the participants through all these tangible media. In order to achieve this purpose, the liturgy has its own way of unifying the scriptural account of salvation history, corralling diversity into unity. Liturgy funnels down the Word of God in Scripture into a worshipful shape and means of grace, but without (we trust) detaching the biblical material from its native context and turning it into something other. Scripture retains its canonical integrity through its place and role in salvation history; it is surpassed and more deeply embedded because, in the liturgy, it is incorporated into its fulfilment and completion in the person and work of Christ to which it originally pointed. Vagaggini puts it thus: ‘The liturgy reads the Scriptures in the light of the supreme principle of the unity of the mystery of Christ, and therefore of the two testaments [sic] and of the whole of sacred history, an organic-progressive unity under the primacy of the New Testament over the Old, and of the eschatological realities over the reality of the present economy.’<footnote label="49" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-CB01165"><para>Cyprian Vagannini, <emphasis role="italic">Theological Dimensions of the Liturgy</emphasis>, trans. Leonard J. Doyle and W. A. Jurgens, from the 4th Italian edn (Collegeville, MN: Liturgical Press, 1976), p. 456.</para></footnote></para><para ele-id="ED7421A">Worshipping Christians are liturgical people, formed and shaped by the work (<emphasis role="italic">leiturgia</emphasis>) of the Christian people of God, living the liturgy in lives of thankful sacrificial service. We understand ourselves, our lives, in the light of the liturgy. The liturgy actualises salvation history in us through <emphasis role="italic">anamnesis</emphasis> and<emphasis role="italic"> epiclesis </emphasis>– making its meaning and power present in us (‘in me’) through the Holy Spirit. As the words and themes of scriptural salvation history are recalled from the past into the here and now as living realities (<emphasis role="italic">anamnesis</emphasis>), they are endued with divine <emphasis role="italic">afflatus</emphasis> (<emphasis role="italic">epiclesis</emphasis>). We re-live salvation history because it now takes place in us, as once elsewhere. Thus Paul tells the Corinthian Christians with unabashed concrete realism that through baptism: ‘You have died with Christ. You were buried with him. You have risen with him. Now walk in newness of life’ (cf. 1 Cor. 6.1–11).</para><para ele-id="AF11CA5">The striking fact about the liturgy is that it is filled with biblical quotations and allusions. For many, perhaps most, Christians – who are not daily Bible-readers – the liturgy is possibly the only place where they encounter Scripture – but encounter it they do, in spades. The Christian liturgy is permeated by the Bible, infused with it, laden with it. The Bible is present in the liturgy physically, audibly, semantically and symbolically.<footnote label="50" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-E44AB5F"><para>Cf. Bridget Nichols in Jeanes and Nichols (eds), <emphasis role="italic">Lively Oracles of God</emphasis>, p. 151; I have added ‘semantically’, that is in the meaning of the words.</para></footnote> Take the Bible out of the liturgy and what do you have left? The biblical quotations and paraphrases are structured by the various purposes and intentions of the liturgy: to excite worship, to give thanks, to teach the faith, to strengthen discipleship and to sanctify lives through the sacraments. It is not too much to say that the church’s liturgy is actually constituted – given its existence – by Scripture, that is to say by the Word of God, so that it becomes a mode of proclamation of the Word (the third form of the Word of God). Only those who know their Bible really well are fully aware of this. The liturgy and its accompanying hymnody are probably the paramount means of instilling the words, ideas and temper of the Scriptures into Christian minds and hearts. ‘The liturgical reading of the Bible is the biblical catechesis of the Church.’<footnote label="51" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-E4D1014"><para>Vagannini, <emphasis role="italic">Theological Dimensions of the Liturgy</emphasis>, p. 486.</para></footnote><superscript> </superscript>When Anglican divines (I use the term 'Anglican' for shorthand, though it is anachronistic before the late seventeenth century at least) felt the need to defend their liturgy against its Puritan critics, who believed that they themselves were more 'biblical' than the established forms of Anglicanism (most Puritans were within the Church of England until the 1630s), those divines (Richard Hooker notably) often pointed to the deep biblical sources of the liturgy. Towards the end of the seventeenth century Jeremy Taylor asserted: 'Very much of our liturgy is in the very words of Scripture. The Psalms and Lessons and all the Hymns [Canticles], save one, are nothing else but Scripture ... So that the matter of them is, out of question, holy and true.'<footnote label="52" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-E147561"><para>Jeremy Taylor, <emphasis role="italic">An Apology for Authorized and Set Forms of Liturgy</emphasis>, Preface, in P. E. More and F. L. Cross (eds), <emphasis role="italic">Anglicanism: The Thought and Practice of the Church of England illustrated from the Religious Literature of the Seventeenth Century</emphasis> (London: SPCK, 1935), p. 174. Taylor's book dates from 1646, but the Preface was added in 1673.</para></footnote> Preaching at some time between the two World Wars, Herbert Hensley Henson, Bishop of Durham, said: 'It is certain that a larger place is given to the reading of Scripture in the appointed services of the church of England than in those of any other church. Beyond other Christians we are accustomed to hear the Bible read in our parish churches.'<footnote label="53" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-5FE3C4D"><para>Herbert Hensley Henson, <emphasis role="italic">Theology and Life</emphasis> (London: Mowbray, n.d), p. 23. Henson made bolder and more questionable claims in the same paragraph: 'Of all the Reformed churches it is perhaps not excessive to say that the Church of England holds in respect of the Bible a kind of primacy. For not only have English scholars played a conspicuous part in Biblical science from the time of the Venerable Bede, but it is generally allowed that the greatest of all the vernacular versions of the Bible is that which we possess in the Authorized Version.' It <emphasis role="italic">was</emphasis> 'excessive' to say that!</para></footnote> Henson's exclusive claim strikes us today as inappropriate. Whatever may have been the case three-quarters of a century ago, the Revised Common Lectionary (RCL), has helped to unify the churches at a practical, liturgical level. However, with its snippets of text, its trunctated lections that come from nowhere and lead nowhere and its disregard for authorial context (e.g. its typical omission of the opening greetings in the Epistles), the RCL seems to have reduced the substantive biblical input of the worship of the churches that use it, including the Church of England.</para><para ele-id="3B0E7C4">The Church of England's contemporary liturgy<emphasis role="italic"> Common Worship</emphasis> presents as a tissue of biblical phrases and images, sometimes almost too richly, thickly and arbitrarily spread. The first version of one of the baptism services had to be withdrawn because it suffered from suffocating figurative overload – images jammed together without form or pattern. Some<emphasis role="italic"> Common Worship</emphasis> services are still afflicted by cartloads of the metaphorical <emphasis role="italic">non-sequitur</emphasis> and this feature is particularly jarring in the Collects. The problem may lend itself to David Jasper’s distinction between a salutary ‘ritual poetics’, which is performative and transformative and lends itself to the dramatic dimension of liturgy, and the false liturgical ideal of what he calls ‘literary poetics’, which are contrived and so may be superficially eloquent and evocative without performative effect. Jasper plausibly claims that the mid twentieth-century quest for liturgical language that is clear, simple, accessible and easy to understand has taken liturgical revision down the wrong road and has resulted in debased liturgical texts. The cause that Jasper promotes could hardly be more important because, as he insists, words are not merely springboards to a worship considered as something over and above the words themselves, but vehicles of its very substance.</para><para ele-id="93BEF8C">The language of liturgy, as address to God, <emphasis role="italic">necessarily</emphasis> and by its nature transcends our understanding and therefore cannot be confined within the limits of ‘ordinary’ speech. The metaphysical demands the metaphorical. You cannot simply walk in off the street, as an unchurched individual, and expect to slip comfortably into the celebration of the liturgy, though you could immediately be at home in a communicative sense if you walked for the first time into a worship event where you sang jejune choruses (‘worship songs’) and applauded pious testimonies, full of self-deception. Liturgical language is bound to seem odd and strange to our ears at first, but that belongs to its essence and is ineradicable. In worship we are in the realm of mystery because we are approaching God solely because God is already drawing near to us. Mystery both attracts and inspires with awe, as Rudolf Otto classically showed.<footnote label="54" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-D3D0E19"><para>Rudolf Otto, <emphasis role="italic">The Idea of the Holy</emphasis>, trans. John W. Harvey (Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1959).</para></footnote> We need to be inducted into liturgical language and learn how to respond to its resonances in a way that edifies. We need training in liturgical worship. The crass literal-mindedness, materiality and gossipy triviality of popular mass culture is a major obstacle. But liturgical language is inescapably metaphorical and symbolic and therefore allusive. It demands words and images that unite, liberate and open up new vistas of the imagination. Samuel Taylor Coleridge proclaimed that ‘words are not things’ but ‘living powers, by which the things of most importance to mankind are actuated, combined, and humanized’.<footnote label="55" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-46285E6"><para>Samuel Taylor Coleridge, <emphasis role="italic">Aids to Reflection</emphasis>, ed. John Beer, <emphasis role="italic">Collected Works of Samuel Taylor Coleridge</emphasis>, ed. Kathleen Coburn, vol. 9 (London: Routledge; Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1993), p. 10 (Preface; words in uppercase changed to lower case).</para></footnote> He held that words are not merely signs or symbols of reality, but are real entities. shape our view of God, ourselves and the world As we have already noted, the Hebrew<emphasis role="italic"> dābār </emphasis>means both ‘word’ and ‘thing’, suggesting a word that is at the same time an act, and an act that is simultaneously a communicated unit of meaning.<footnote label="56" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-6B0B0BA"><para>Martin Dudley, ‘<emphasis role="italic">Vox Clara</emphasis>: The Liturgical Voice in Advent and Christmas’, in Martin Dudley (ed.), <emphasis role="italic">Like a Two-Edged Sword: The Word of God in Liturgy and History; Essays in Honour of Canon Donald Gray</emphasis> (Norwich: Canterbury Press, 1995), p. 69.</para></footnote><emphasis role="italic"> </emphasis>The words of the liturgy cry out to be understood in that way: they have living power. The practice of liturgical poetics draws us into a tradition and a community where we may grow in understanding over time. Liturgical prayer is not an instant commodity. Liturgical language brings together past and present. It and only it can place us at the heart of the theological mystery of the church. It works in the realm of embodiment and not apart from the physical, material stuff of life, but therewith suffused with the glory of God.</para></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="934C018"><emphasis role="bold">Mystery and materiality in the liturgy</emphasis></title><para ele-id="124E722">For Hammond in<emphasis role="italic"> The Sound of the Liturgy</emphasis>, the whole liturgy is an eloquent visible <emphasis role="italic">sign</emphasis> to believers and unbelievers alike of Christian truth. The elements within it – not only words but also gestures, postures and three-dimensional symbols – are signs in themselves. Like Jasper, Hammond believes that liturgical scholars have not sufficiently considered how words work in worship. Her four deceptively simple topics – repetition, rhythm, punctuation and posture – the 'structural supports' of liturgy, help in 'sounding the depths of the liturgy'. I interject that the depths of the liturgy are not simply how words do their job, but how they serve the Word, which is Jesus Christ, the Scriptures and the church’s proclamation, albeit not without words. We cannot have any of those results without words, but we need to keep our gaze fixed, through them, as through a window, on the Word which is the source and goal of them all. Ministers of the Eucharist certainly need to understand the nature of the script in front of them. But a liturgy is not merely a script and a script is not a liturgy. Liturgy is <emphasis role="italic">enacted</emphasis>.<emphasis role="italic"> </emphasis>It consists of words (mainly scriptural) spoken collectively and dialogically, with the intention both of addressing God and of addressing each other in the presence of God and in the face of God (<emphasis role="italic">coram deo</emphasis>) – in other words, relationally, inter-personally and interactively in a delicate complexity of sacred movement (<emphasis role="italic">perichoresis</emphasis>). In liturgy we do all that with words and with the help of an array of other sacred signs (for words are also signs), together with a range of significant physical actions performed by priest and people. I suspect that liturgy is a unique genre, neither simply prose nor simply poetry, neither merely word nor merely action, nor solely drama nor solely performance, but some active, creative fusion of them all. How vital to the church’s mission it is, then, that the church should be equipped with priests and bishops, assisted by deacons and lay persons, who understand the liturgy and how it works in the service of the Word and are able to lead its celebration, with the congregation, in a manner that is dignified, uplifting and God-centred, neither incompetently bumbling, nor idiosyncratic and quirky, nor egotistical, nor therefore, in any of these ways, jarring on the worship-sensibility of the worshippers and dimming the glory of God in the liturgy.</para><para ele-id="B0059BD">Hammond reminds us that worship is an action of the whole person, physical as much as spiritual. Posture and physical effort are the basis of sound. The persistent Platonic and Cartesian mind-body dualism of the Western philosophical tradition has encouraged us to think that worship takes place in the head and therefore to privilege words over actions, taking liturgical statements to be primarily about conveying semantic, cognitive content or information. The legacy of Romanticism insists that authenticity lies in individual self-expression, in articulating our personal feelings. Turning worship into entertainment – much the current trend – cannot be done without putting the 'worship-leader' centre stage and making a celebrity out of a servant. Some churches (I have experienced and endured it!) even have a ‘warm-up’ act to build up the congregation’s expectations of the preacher’s performance and bring them to a pitch of receptivity, like a political rally. So while one part of Christ’s church is letting rip, waving arms in the air, and crying ‘Alleluia!’ and ‘Amen!’, in season and out of season, another part remains typically buttoned-up and Anglo-Saxon, too lukewarm to kneel, singing with lips barely parted and whispering the responses!</para><para ele-id="C3BC63B">Worship that is offered 'in spirit and in truth' (Jn 4. 23–4), that is worthy of God as far as human effort ever can be, demands the highest human skills that we can find. Worship needs premeditation, practice, choreography, rhythm, repetition and physical exertion. Hammond confronts head-on the pernicious assumption in our culture that what is 'performed' savours of insincerity and deceit, our nagging doubt as to whether repeating inherited words can have authenticity, and she assails the cult of false (because inevitably predictable) spontaneity. She wants to bring back <emphasis role="italic">mystique</emphasis>. What do we think makes 'a prayer well-prayed'? I would reply: the expressed devotion of the whole person, body, mind and spirit.</para><para ele-id="7A5231E">Our whole physical-spiritual constitution longs for God and responds to God. The Psalmist yearns for God from deep within; his very flesh is parched without God. ‘O God, thou art my God: early will I seek thee. My soul thirsteth for thee, my flesh also longeth after thee; in a barren and dry land where no water is’ (Ps 63.1–2, BCP). Longing, yearning, unrequited love, is a physical experience, felt extremely it can make us ill; but when it is satisfied it can make us radiant with happiness. Pope Benedict XVI in the Encyclical <emphasis role="italic">Spe Salvi</emphasis> (‘Saved by Hope’, 2007, 33§) wrote about the connection between desire and prayer, reminding us that St Augustine defined prayer as an exercise of desire. James Montgomery (1771–1854) finely expressed this in a hymn: 'Prayer is the soul's sincere desire,/ Uttered or unexpressed;/ The motion of a hidden fire/ That trembles in the breast.' And Christina Rossetti expressed it with awesome passion: ‘My faith burns low, my love burns low;/ Only my heart's desire cries out in me/ By the deep, thunder of its want and woe,/ Cries unto Thee.<footnote label="57" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-630AED1"><para>Christina Rossetti, ‘None other Lamb, none other Name’, in <emphasis role="italic">The Face of the Deep: A Devotional Commentary on the Apocalypse</emphasis> (London: SPCK, 1892).</para></footnote></para><para ele-id="2097E48">In liturgy the whole person is engaged, body, brain, voice and guts. There can be no anthropological dualism here, no Platonic etheriality. The physical dimension of liturgical worship is not an add-on or dispensable flourish but is worship itself. One cannot have the complete meaning-content of worship – a content that could be expressed in propositional form if desired – without the body. Just as our minds and spirits need to be trained and disciplined to participate meaningfully in worship, so do our bodies. Liturgy is a practice and and such a physical and social function, as well as a noetic one. As Sarah Coakley has insisted, ‘liturgy is ... <emphasis role="italic">not</emphasis> an affective <emphasis role="italic">complement</emphasis> to intellectual reflection, but rather the means of a full integration of all aspects of embodied selfhood into the life of Christ’. Coakley further writes: ‘bodily movement, sensual acuity, affective longing, and noetic or intellectual response, are intricately entwined and mutually implicated in what is occurring, and indeed are being trained over time to intensify their capacity for response to the risen Christ’.<footnote label="58" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-9C63557"><para>Sarah Coakley, ‘Beyond “Belief”: Liturgy and the Cognitive Apprehension of God’, in Tom Greggs, Rachel Muers and Simeon Zahl (eds), <emphasis role="italic">The Vocation of Theology Today: A Festschrift for David Ford</emphasis> (Eugene, OR: Wipf and Stock, 2013), ch. 10 (pp. 131–45), at pp. 143f.</para></footnote> In the liturgy we open up and surrender our whole selves – body, mind, spirit – to the presence and grace of God who meets us there in fellowship with others.<footnote label="59" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-5378CCE"><para>Mark Wynn, <emphasis role="italic">Emotional Experience and Religious Understanding: Integrating Perception, Conception and Feeling</emphasis> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2005), shows with reference to Schleiermacher and Newman, alonside more more thinkers, that affective experience, as e.g. in the devotion of worship, is ‘toned’ with value and information, so it has cognitive significance; thus body and mind are working together and never divorced.</para></footnote><superscript> The Word of God is addressed to the body also.</superscript></para><para ele-id="5CBB95C">In sacramental and other symbolic actions, including the use of freighted words, the meaning is encoded in the visible, audible sign. The signs participate in the reality to which they point and which they truly communicate. We reverence the cross and the crucifix <emphasis role="italic">as though</emphasis> it were the actual one on which Christ died. In the (Lutheran) Church of Sweden, communicants, having received the sacrament, step sideways to reverence the large cross that is held up for them. It is not theologically reductive (as I have heard claimed) when the liturgy says that the bread and wine of the Eucharist 'become to us' the body and blood of Christ, as though it were merely our faith that makes them so (which would be a stark version of the unacceptable doctrine of ‘receptionism’). The consecrated elements impact us and have an effect; they make a difference; there is a becoming taking place. A personal copy of the Bible, used constantly, becomes iconic of God's Word to us (never an idol, I trust), though it remains physically a book and so a human artifact, like any other. Hammond nicely describes making the sign of the cross over oneself (as though to say, 'I do this/take this only through the cross of Christ') and taking up the elements of bread and wine at the Offertory as 'the visible affiliative gesture'. But perhaps the most <emphasis role="italic">devoted</emphasis> sign in the liturgical repertoire: the threefold liturgical kiss: kissing the Holy <link er-cited="false" linkend="Tat" role="table">Table at</link> the start and end of the liturgy, kissing the Book of the Gospels when the reading is concluded, and kissing loved ones at the Peace. The chaste kiss expresses the union; it unites us both physically and spiritually to those potent entities (the priest also kisses the cross at the neck of the stole when vesting). This puts me in mind of Psalm 85.10: ‘Mercy and truth are met together: righteousness and peace have kissed each other’ (BCP). While transcendent realities cannot be<emphasis role="italic"> comprehended</emphasis>,<emphasis role="italic"> </emphasis>they can be <emphasis role="italic">apprehended</emphasis> when mediated through symbol and sacrament. These signs are fathomless, polyvalent, over-determined; we will mine their depths all our lives.</para><para ele-id="FD5B2CE">As a classicist and patristic scholar, Hammond is sympathetic to the value that the ancient world placed on the skills of rhetoric, namely how to secure an entrance into the minds of your listeners for the message that you want them to take on board. The antithesis of this ancient art is the familiar bluff, anti-intellectual style that strains to avoid any impression of artifice. Hammond stresses that sincerity and humility are not enough; worship demands our best skills. In practice not all worship ministers manage even to project the voice, a skill that is still needed even with amplification; but the ability to <emphasis role="italic">modulate</emphasis> sense and meaning, to achieve the right <emphasis role="italic">tone</emphasis>, in the service of the Word, is even more rare. Who has not squirmed in their pew when a lesson-reader has declaimed the text, dramatising it as though it were a play or film score, or has misconstrued it with hilarious results. I have heard in a rural context the parable of the vineyard so mangled that, 'This is the heir, let us kill him' (Mt. 22.38), became, 'This is the hare, let us kill it'; and 'whoremongers' (Rev. 21.8, KJB) turned into 'war mongers' (the same applies no doubt)? To minister the Word of God in liturgical worship is a high calling and demands our best skills and insights; we should never allowed the Word to be trashed.</para><para ele-id="217656A">Hammond's criticisms of aspects of the Church of England’s <emphasis role="italic">Common Worship</emphasis> are restrained, but strike home. The minimal use of rubrical directions for gesture and posture, compared with earlier official texts, downplays the physical dimension of worship. Minimizing repetition (this applies to modern Bible translations too; they are sometimes impatient of Hebrew parallelism) undermines the function of a text, considered as a 'speech-act', to ingrain and embed Christian truths in the lives of worshippers. The transmission of the faith from one generation to the next relies on memory and therefore needs repetition, which leads to imitation. Corporate acts, the unison of hearts and minds, require the predictability that repetition gives. It creates a secure space, an ambience of trust, in which we can let go of petty egotistical concerns and give ourselves to God. It helps us to see more clearly, to focus on the object of attention. 'Repetition is of the essence of Christian worship.'<footnote label="60" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-035E7F0"><para>Hammond, <emphasis role="italic">The Sound of the Liturgy</emphasis>, p. 85.</para></footnote> Although the language of <emphasis role="italic">Common Worship</emphasis> is sometimes richer and the imagery more imaginative than that of its modern predecessors, there is an occasional failure to respect rhythm and stress, both of which Hammond believes are arguably the most important factors in making liturgy memorable (e.g. 'who is alive and reigns', instead of 'who lives and reigns', is asymmetrical and jars).</para><para ele-id="0966D4F">In what circumstances is the Church, with all its failings, faults, sins and even crimes, most transparent to God and to the Word of God? When is it most revelatory of the gospel? In what mode or state of the church can people most clearly see Jesus Christ depicted? Is it not when the church reaches out to the poor, the sick, the outcast and the bereaved? But may it not be also when the liturgy, incorporating the sacraments, is competently and reverently celebrated so that Christ and the cross are lifted up? When words and sacramental signs serve the Word glory shines through and worship can become a window into God's saving work in Christ. As Hammond puts it, 'Prayer with the body becomes an act of public witness to the faith.'<footnote label="61" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-E80B493"><para>Ibid., p. 58.</para></footnote> We should not hold down the spirit (or rather Spirit) of worship, bottle it up, and button it up. It needs outward, visible and physical expression for the sake of the world. ‘Thus saith the Lord GOD, Behold I will lift up mine hand to the Gentiles, and set up my standard to the people: and [then] they shall bring their sons in their arms, and thy daughters shall be carried upon their shoulders’ (Isa. 49.22, KJB).</para></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="54AC956"><emphasis role="bold">Confronted by the Material Text</emphasis></title><para ele-id="BE4CAB4">A very basic aspect of the materiality of the liturgy is its text.<footnote label="62" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-0E47EA9"><para>Rowan Williams, <emphasis role="italic">The Edge of Words: God and the Habits of Language</emphasis>, Gifford Lectures (London and New York: Bloomsbury, 2014), ch. 4; David Grumett, <emphasis role="italic">Material Eucharist</emphasis> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2016).</para></footnote> Liturgy is by definition<emphasis role="italic"> scripted</emphasis>. That does not mean that there is no room for spontaneity, adaptation and silence; but there is always a script, a score, to be followed and that is a material entity, a human artifact. The text in front of us in church contains the essential elements of the rite, without which we would not have a liturgy. The text is an aspect of worship that we could not possibly do without, yet we take it for granted most of the time (unless we are liturgical scholars, perhaps). The text is, as Juliette Day puts it, 'the elephant in the church' (p. ix).<footnote label="63" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-DFE373C"><para>Page references to Day, <emphasis role="italic">Reading the Liturgy</emphasis> are embedded in my main text.</para></footnote> Day wants to force us to pay attention to the text, to hold it up for analysis, to <emphasis role="italic">see</emphasis> the text and to see it as a human artifact, the outcome of a process of production or creation. Many of us are fascinated by the question of the authorship of ancient liturgies (whether by Hippolytus or Thomas Cranmer, for example), but strangely, we seldom pause to ask how our modern liturgies came into being, what the process of creation was and whose voice and pen (or probably, laptop), within a committee or synod was dominant in the discussion and the drafting process and what difference that has made (p. 21). So let us now take seriously the materiality and facticity of the text.</para><para ele-id="15DDC3F">First we have to reckon with the stunning theological truth that in liturgy (just as in Scripture) the eternal and transcendent Word of God, in an act of infinite humility, takes the form of<emphasis role="italic"> text</emphasis>. The most damning thing that can be said about a bad sermon or bad theology is that, in them, the Word has become mere words (as the Orcadian poet Edwin Muir, contemplating the Calvinistic Kirk of Scotland, put it, ‘The Word made flesh is here made word again’).<footnote label="64" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-632D023"><para>Edwin Muir, <emphasis role="italic">‘</emphasis>The Incarnate One’, in <emphasis role="italic">Collected Poems</emphasis> (London: Faber and Faber, 1984), pp. 228–9.</para></footnote> Written words that are then spoken – texts, scripts – are the inescapable medium or vehicle of the Word of God in both the liturgy and the sermon within it. In the Incarnation, the eternal Word of God was united to human nature and took the form of a slave (Phil. 2.6–8). Correspondingly, in Scripture and the liturgy (which is substantially composed of scriptural material) the sovereign Word of God (<emphasis role="italic">Logos</emphasis>), in an act of supreme condescension, adopts the text, owns it, allies itself to it, submits to it and speaks through it. To serve the Word in this revelatory way the text must be translucent in the hands of the Holy Spirit, distinguished by <emphasis role="italic">claritas</emphasis>; it cannot be opaque as to its meaning and import. The Word must shine through it so that we can seek and find the Word (Jesus Christ) within the text or through the text. Our attention does not rest on the surface of the text, the grammar, the syntax, the choice of words (usually in translation), even the typeface. We simply see through it, though necessarily by means of it as an instrument or medium. Our ultimate focus is elsewhere, seeking the source of the light, travelling up the spiritual sunbeam. As we have previously noted, in William Blake’s characterisation of truth-yielding perception, we must learn to see not with, but through the eye’.<footnote label="65" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-6F58DD7"><para>William Blake, <emphasis role="italic">The Complete Poems</emphasis>, ed. Alicia Ostriker (Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1977), p. 860; ‘The Everlasting Gospel’, ll. 103–7; cf. id., p. 510. ‘The Marriage of Heaven and Hell’.</para></footnote> In Michael Polanyi's terms, we have a tacit or subliminal, not explicit and conscious, awareness of the meaning of a liturgical text. As an object of our attention it is merely subsidiary, serving a higher end. Although we employ various native aptitudes and learned skills in navigating the text, they are in order to our doing something else. Polanyi's example is riding a bicycle: we probably cannot explain how we manage to stay upright, but by long practice we know how to do it and can peddle away without thinking about it.<footnote label="66" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-250BAF5"><para>Michael Polanyi, <emphasis role="italic">Personal Knowledge</emphasis>, Gifford Lectures (London: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1958); id., <emphasis role="italic">The Tacit Dimension</emphasis> (London: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1967).</para></footnote> In worship our gaze is directed, not <emphasis role="italic">at</emphasis> but<emphasis role="italic"> through </emphasis>the words on the page, beyond, to God, the church and the self – above all to the Word. We may be enthralled by the best words in the best order, as in a satisfying liturgy; we may be intoxicated by the beauty and dignity of the text; but that is not what we are there in church for.</para><para ele-id="E51F239">A liturgical text generates high thoughts and strong feelings, eventuating in address to God or to fellow worshippers (including occasionally the minister/president). The human God-ward aspect of praise and adoration is our task (<emphasis role="italic">leiturgia</emphasis>) in worship because it is our responsibility, ‘our bounden duty and service’. But it is what God the Word (Jn 1.1–3) has to say to us, through Scripture readings, the homily and indeed through the liturgy as an entirety, that has priority and takes precedence theologically. If the Word did not first speak to our hearts, we would have no words to speak to God; we would be mute. In the empirical order of experience, liturgy appears to be, in the main, speech addressed to God. But, in the order of theological reflection, liturgy is essentially a response to prevenient grace, which furnishes us with a language that we can internalise and make fully our own in coming to God – with the major proviso that the embedded ideological assumptions of the rite are not such as to disturb our prayers and even alienate us from the text, as patriarchal, anthropocentric and sexist language does for many.</para><para ele-id="D5AE725">Thought, giving rise to speech, takes off from the text and is immediately on the wing. Speech transcends the text and leaves it well behind. Liturgy is not 'reading aloud to God' (p. xi), but a heart-felt cry to God for redemption. Speech is not the end product; it is only a vehicle. Within speech resides meaning and it is the meaning that matters; it is meaning that we intend in our speech. It is the meaning – the <emphasis role="italic">Logos</emphasis> becoming <emphasis role="italic">mythos</emphasis> (extended, articulated narrative) – that gives coherence, vitality and integrity to the act of worship. Not that the meaning is or ever can be monolithic; while the outward text, whether of Scripture or liturgy, is comparatively stable and fixed, the meaning that readers, whether they be worshippers or biblical scholars, find in it or draw from it is highly diverse. These multiple meanings show that the text or script of the liturgy is not set in stone, but is to some extent fluid, flexible, malleable and determined by factors external to the text, whether these are the subjective, psychological disposition of the interpreter or the social, cultural-linguistic and political context and environment in which the liturgy is being performed (probably both at once). A liturgical (or any other) text is not a laid-down deposit of meaning like a seam of coal, so that its meaning can be extracted from the mine. The text continually furnishes the raw material of spiritual perception; it perpetually generates meanings. What the liturgy means to worshippers reflects their intention in coming before God together in worship. Our meaning embodies intention: it is what we want – what we need – to say to God and to each other in the presence of God, 'our discourse of praise' (p. 15) and of penitence and intercession also. In all these ways, we indwell the Word of God as the Word gives itself to us in humility and love. ‘Love, the bird, is on the way’, sang Eleanor Farjeon in her Advent carol ‘People Look East’; but let us now say, ‘Love, the Word, is on the way.’</para><para ele-id="812A15B">But much greater than any individual, subjective, intention is the formal intention of the church as that has been formed over time. The default intention of the worshipper, whether they realise it or not, is to do what the church does; and by aligning themselves with the liturgy as part of a worshipping congregation, they tacitly do so intend. But without the text we would not have speech and without speech we would not have the meaning that conveys the all-important intention, the desires of our hearts, that are already known to God, as the Collect for Purity in the Book of Common Prayer reminds us.</para><para ele-id="A926F0D">Our turn to God and address to God is not made with the lips alone; it is also embodied in action and in gesture. Kneeling, standing, closing one's eyes, attending and listening in silence, putting the hands together, making the sign of the cross, raising one's arms, stretching out one's hands to receive – all these gestures are modes of wordless address to God. Architecture, vestments, candles, altar frontals, flowers, crosses and crucifixes, icons and other images and (perhaps above all) music are visual signs that are, so to speak, ancillary or auxiliary to the text, supporting it while being supported by it. These visual and verbal signs are eloquent in themselves, but become doubly powerful when the text serves as a commentary on them. We probably tend to think of all these things in church as things that we do, human initiatives, but that is a perception darkened by sin. It is a theological perversion to start our thinking about worship in terms of human actions, least of all human initiatives. The inventory of worship is made up of gifts and blessings from God, graces that we simply appropriate, use or arrange. In the sacraments the aspect of gift or grace is especially pronounced. In sacramental worship we are primarily receiving from God. Water, bread, wine, holy oil and hands of blessing are the means or channels of sacramental grace. We rightly thank God for what 'earth has given and human hands have made'. But in the celebration of the sacraments, whether baptism, confirmation or Eucharist, we are also – and this is definitely secondary – addressing God by way of response, articulating our intention, which is one essentially of reception, thanksgiving and dedication. But it is all enfolded in the prevenient presence and action of the Word, the living <emphasis role="italic">Logos</emphasis>.</para><para ele-id="15D8143">Day has a shrewd point to make about contemporary liturgies. She notes the tendency to lengthen the liturgy while shortening the individual components. Some modern liturgies are frankly 'bitty'. But, as Day points out, snippets of readings and brief prayers are more suited to private devotion, while public worship benefits from repetition and elaboration (p. 16). Liturgies are high in inter-textuality (ch. 5): they are a tissue of canonical and extra-canonical holy words and images, a palimpsest, one might say, of written and unwritten resources. A liturgical text is like a coral reef that has been built up over the centuries, in fact millennia if we start with the worship of the ancient Hebrews, particularly in the Psalms. Continuity is edifying; fragmentation leaves us spiritually adrift. ‘When I worship’, Coleridge confided to his <emphasis role="italic">Notebooks</emphasis>, ‘let me unify!’<footnote label="67" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-7A4144F"><para>Samuel Taylor Coleridge, <emphasis role="italic">The Notebooks of Samuel Taylor Coleridge</emphasis>,<emphasis role="italic"> Volume 3, 1808–1819</emphasis>,<emphasis role="italic"> </emphasis>ed. Kathleen Coburn (London: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1973), no. 4058.</para></footnote></para><para ele-id="90D98CC">Day highlights the identity-forming power of narrative within liturgy, drawing on Alastair MacIntyre and narrative theory. Liturgy not only shapes individual Christians in their life of discipleship, but welds them into the people of God through a process of corporate formation. The words and actions of worship 'shape attitudes to each other, to God and to the world; they enable a transformation or reformation of identity as one's own narrative is inserted (as it were by the Holy Spirit operative in the liturgy and in us) into the narrative of salvation; they make present the kingdom of God' (p. 18; cf. pp. 68–70). The Word in the liturgy brings the community into being: the 'we' of worship is performative; it could not have been said before the people came together (pp. 106–9). Day points to the mediatory role of liturgy, its permeability to divine action and human response, its reconciling function in drawing, luring, humankind to God and articulating God's gracious, attractive invitation in Christ. For this aspect of liturgy she offers the term 'threshold' and opens up suggestively the liminal function of liturgy, how it transports us from one place or state to another. The language of worship is a form of social action (p. 157); it creates a new social structure, a community. 'In worship the Church realizes herself' (p. 109). Day notes the dropping of warm invitatory language in modern revisions in favour of terse instructions: where is the equivalent today of the 'Dearly beloved ...' of the Book of Common Prayer (p. 116)? Richard Hawker, the heroic Rector of the brutal parish of Morwenstow on the north Cornish coast in the mid nineteenth century, had only one person in the congregation when he said Morning and Evening Prayer – his wife. So he habitually began, ‘Dearly beloved Charlotte ...’. Pastoral and conjugal affection were combined.</para><para ele-id="5EEE82F">An imperious question, that affects not only Christian formation but evangelisation and apologetics, arises at this point (p. 82): does the liturgical portrayal of God's story of salvation resonate with our own diverse ways of telling our own story in our own generation? Can we identify with the biblical story of God? Does it speak to our condition? Collective speech needs to carry assent (p. 110). This is the agonising dilemma of liturgical revision: how can it resonate with today’s tacit paradigms while holding on to the tradition? How can scripted prayer, adopted as the vehicle of our speech to God, have authenticity (p. 155)? This question raises the issue of the logic of self-involvement, commitment and authenticity.<footnote label="68" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-BEBA101"><para>See the meticulous analysis in Donald D. Evans, <emphasis role="italic">The Logic of Self-Involvement</emphasis> (London: SCM Press, 1963). See also and fundamentally J. L. Austin, <emphasis role="italic">Philosophical Papers</emphasis>, ed. J. O. Urmson and G. J. Warnock (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1961; id., <emphasis role="italic">How to do things with Words</emphasis>, ed. J. O. Urmson (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1962). Evans expounds and adapts Austin's conceptual scheme. In his later book, <emphasis role="italic">Struggle and Fulfilment: The Inner Dynamics of Religion and Morality</emphasis> (New York and London: Collins, 1979/80), Evans uses the term 'attitude-virtues' to bring out the ethical and action-orientated aspects of intention and commitment. However, Evans does not discuss worship and liturgy in either book, except in passing. For the self-involving character of moral statements see R. M. Hare, <emphasis role="italic">The Language of Morals</emphasis> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1952) and P. H. Nowell-Smith, <emphasis role="italic">Ethics</emphasis> (Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1954). Like religious language, pre-eminently in worship, moral language can never be a mere statement of fact. As Hare puts it, ‘A judgement is not moral if it does not provide, without further imperative premisses [sic], a reason for doing something’ (p. 31). Like religious affirmations, moral judgements always contain a reason for acting upon them one way or another (cf., p. 197).</para></footnote> In worship there is a unique kind of self-abandonment, of self-oblation, a passing over from oneself to the object of worship, which in fact ceases to be an external object and enters into oneself, bringing a sense of union and fulfilment. Liturgical speech is not descriptive, not a statement of the facts, but performative. It enunciates a stance, a posture and an intention that involves and commits the whole of the person and their life. To take part from the ground of the heart in worship is transformative, it cannot leave us unchanged. But for worship to have its perfect work it needs to seize us and hold us in the first place and therefore needs to resonate with our needs, hopes and desires, in other words to have authenticity as far as we, the participants, are concerned. It must be worship not only 'in spirit’ but ‘in truth' (Jn 4. 24), not only in the heart of the worshipper, but also in the act, the event, of worship, that is to say in the liturgy itself. When a liturgy readily lends itself to be the vehicle of our desires, hopes and needs, and unites us to the Paschal Mystery of Jesus Christ, it can be said to be a liturgy that subsists 'in spirit and in truth'.</para></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="B091138"><emphasis role="bold">Pastoral application</emphasis></title><para ele-id="9C3D370">Interpreting the Bible is difficult enough and is very far from being an ‘exact science’, but it is actually only the second hardest task. The difficulty of interpreting the Scriptures is exceeded only by the challenge of serving the Threefold Word of God in what is often a one-to-one pastoral ministry, and particularly of showing the relevance of the Scriptures in that setting. The questions and concerns that come up in pastoral counselling are often fraught with the moral dilemmas with which the individual is wrestling at the time, whether these be linked to relationships, including marriage and sexuality, concerns for one’s children, safeguarding alerts, work issues, depression, guilt and remorse, or religious doubts and loss of faith. The pastoral minister needs to bring the Threefold Word of God (Jesus Christ, the Scriptures and the church’s message, the gospel) to bear on such explorations, but how can this be done without being intrusive, directive and didactic, but rather letting the individual grasp some provisional leads (if not answers) for themselves and thus find a way forward in their faith? So it is no great surprise to find that the pastoral role of the Scriptures is inexplicably overlooked in some standard histories of pastoral care.<footnote label="69" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-5248EB5"><para>E.g., J. T. McNeill, <emphasis role="italic">A History of the Cure of Souls</emphasis> (London: SCM Press, 1952); G. R. Evans (ed.), <emphasis role="italic">A History of Pastoral Care</emphasis> (London and New York: Cassell, 2000).</para></footnote> The recent symposium <emphasis role="italic">The Bible in Pastoral Practice</emphasis> (related to the Cardiff University and Bible Society project that I mentioned earlier) attempts to redress this deficiency. Stephen Pattison is quoted as deploring the fact that 'pastoral theologians seem to have almost completely avoided considering the Bible’. Pattison continues: ‘There is an almost absolute and embarrassing silence about the Bible in pastoral care.’<footnote label="70" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-2F7D170"><para>C. Bartholomew in Paul Ballard and S. R. Holmes, <emphasis role="italic">The Bible in Pastoral Practice</emphasis> (London: Darton, Longman &#x0026; Todd, 2005), p. 135.</para></footnote> However, most of the chapters in that volume are concerned with meta-questions of biblical interpretation, rather than with applied or pastoral theology.<footnote label="71" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-5FBCF84"><para>An exception is ch. 11: H. Anderson, ‘The Bible and Pastoral Care’.</para></footnote> This fact reinforces my point about how difficult it is to apply the Bible to concrete pastoral situations.</para><para ele-id="29BB0FA">To have deep spiritual and moral integrity, the work of the biblical interpreter needs to be embedded in the pastoral context and underpinned by sharing in the church’s regular celebration of the liturgy. Martin Luther understood this: 'Nobody can understand the Scriptures who has not looked after a congregation for a hundred years.’ This thought led Luther to add ruefully: ‘We're beggars, that's the truth.'<footnote label="72" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-70A7D9F"><para><emphasis role="italic">WA Tisch.</emphasis>, 5677; <emphasis role="italic">LW</emphasis>, vol. 54, p. 476.</para></footnote> The first Exhortation in the service of Holy Communion in the Book of Common Prayer, 1662, recognises that the pastoral counsel and guidance of the Christian must be drawn from the Scriptures. Anyone 'who cannot quiet his own conscience' in preparing to receive Holy Communion, but 'requires further comfort or counsel', should approach a 'discreet and learned Minister of God's Word, and open his grief, that by the ministry of God's holy Word he may receive the benefit of absolution, together with ghostly counsel and advice, to the quieting of his conscience, and avoiding of all scruple and doubtfulness.'<footnote label="73" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-E8ECE3D"><para>These words in the first Exhortation of 1662 are adapted from earlier forms in second Exhortation of both the 1549 and 1552 Prayer Books: <emphasis role="italic">The First and Second Prayer Books of Edward VI</emphasis> (London: Dent [Everyman], 1910).</para></footnote></para><para ele-id="969D662">In offering non-directive pastoral counselling to an individual, the minister will often paraphrase Scripture, drawing on the promises of Jesus, the teaching of Paul (with care), or the example of biblical characters – not of course as cut-and-dried solutions to the presenting problems, but as divinely-inspired raw materials for the individual’s reflection and wrestling. The pastoral encounter draws the individual into the original divine-human communicative situation that is reflected in the biblical text. The prayers and blessings that are used on such occasions are either drawn directly from Scripture or echo the sense of Scripture – for example, we often turn to the Psalms for comfort and guidance. I like to think that lonely or otherwise troubled individuals in hotel bedrooms turn to those texts (taken out of context though they inevitably are) which are placed at the front of the Gideon Bibles and find help. But above all it is the deep rounded formation of heart and mind by the Scriptures and the liturgy, the inhabiting of the text, that fits a minister for the pastoral role. And it is the bringing to bear of the whole biblical revelation and perspective to situations of pastoral need that has healing and amending power.</para><para ele-id="87AB4A2">In the ministry of the church’s 'occasional’ or ‘pastoral’ offices, which have strong elements of <emphasis role="italic">rites de passage</emphasis>, the liminal points of transition and growth in human life are filled with biblical content through the appointed liturgy. Baptism is interpreted in the light of the new birth of John 3.3–8 and the descent of the Holy Spirit on Jesus at his baptism in the River Jordan. Confirmation replicates the laying on of hands by the Apostles in the Acts ('after the example of thy holy Apostles', as the Book of Common Prayer, 1662, puts it). Marriage is declared to signify the nuptial bond between Christ and his church, as portrayed in Ephesians 5 (also slightly more tenuous resonances with the marriage at Cana of Galilee (Jn 2.1–11). Funerals draw hope from the compassion of Christ for those who experience sorrow and are acquainted with grief and also from his resurrection and heavenly session, whither he has gone to prepare a place for us. Through these liturgical-sacramental acts, we become conformed to Christ's journey and destiny through the power of God's Word in the Scriptures. We find ourselves caught up into the great narrative of God's redemptive acts so that our life and our faith becomes embedded in it.<footnote label="74" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-02EEC96"><para>Cf. P. Avis, <emphasis role="italic">A Church Drawing Near: Spirituality and Mission in a Post-Christian Culture</emphasis> (London and New York: T&#x0026;T Clark, 2003), especially ch. 6.</para></footnote></para><para ele-id="931A981">But most important of all in any pastoral situation is the presence and power of the primary, original and originating Word of God, the<emphasis role="italic"> Logos</emphasis> incarnate,<emphasis role="italic"> </emphasis>Jesus Christ. Christ's presence in the church's liturgy – that is to say, through word and sacrament, underpinned by pastoral care – is a personal, saving and judging presence. It is not a truism when Bonhoeffer says: 'Christ is present in the church as a person.' It is important that Christ is present in his fullness and in the power of his person and work. 'Christ is present as the Crucified and Risen one,' says Bonhoeffer. His reality is inseparable from the church: he can be conceived of only in the community. Citing Martin Luther, 'So it is one thing if God is there, and another if he is there for you', Bonhoeffer identifies this presence for our benefit with the liturgy, comprising word and sacrament and celebrated by the community. He says both that Christ exists in the church through word and sacrament and that he exists in the church as community. 'This one, whole person, the God-man Jesus Christ, is present in the church in his <emphasis role="italic">pro me</emphasis> structure as Word, as sacrament and as community.'<footnote label="75" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-E10A0D2"><para>D. Bonhoeffer, <emphasis role="italic">Christology</emphasis>, intro. Edwin H. Robertson, trans. John Bowden (London: Collins [Fontana], 1966), pp. 43–9, 58–60. Luther, <emphasis role="italic">WA</emphasis>, 23, 152, cited Bonhoeffer, id., p. 48.</para></footnote></para><para ele-id="DB0AD0A"><superscript>We tend to think of it as a Reformation insight that the church is constituted by word and sacrament. </superscript><emphasis role="italic"><superscript>Confessio Augustana</superscript></emphasis><superscript> VII and the Thirty-nine Articles XIX support that assumption (though we should add that the ministry of word and sacrament requires the ministry of pastoral oversight so that the word is 'purely' taught and the sacraments 'rightly' administered). The Reformers recovered and prioritised this truth, but they did not originate it. It is good to be reminded of what Thomas Kempis (b. 1380) writes towards the end of </superscript><emphasis role="italic"><superscript>The Imitation of Christ</superscript></emphasis><superscript>. There are two things especially necessary, 'without which this life of sorrow would be unbearable,' he says. 'While in the prison-house of this body', we need food and light. 'You have therefore given me in my weakness your sacred Body to be the refreshment of my soul and body, and have set your Word as a lamp to my feet. Without these two, I cannot rightly live; for the Word of God is the light of my soul, and your Sacrament is the bread of my life.' These are two tables set on either side in the treasury of Christ's church: 'the table of the holy altar, having on it the holy bread, the precious Body of Christ; the other ... the divine law, that enshrines the holy doctrine, teaches the true faith, and unerringly guides our steps...'</superscript><footnote label="76" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-033DCE5"><para>Thomas à [sic] Kempis, <emphasis role="italic">The Imitation of Christ</emphasis>, trans. L. Shirley-Price (Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1952), p. 205 (IV, 11).</para></footnote></para><para ele-id="BB9E563">The Vatican II<superscript> echoes Kempis’ image of the two tables. </superscript>The Constitution on the Sacred Liturgy <emphasis role="italic">Sacrosanctum Concilium</emphasis> states that Christ is present in his church in several ways: he is present in the Eucharist and other sacraments, through priests and through the word (note the order). It continues: 'Christ is always present in his church, especially in her liturgical celebrations ... He is present in his word, since it is he himself who speaks when the holy scriptures are read in the church. He is present when the church prays and sings.' The underlying truth is that the celebration of the liturgy is 'an exercise of the priestly office of Jesus Christ'.<footnote label="77" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-B8F6435"><para>Walter M. Abbott, SJ, ed., <emphasis role="italic">Documents of Vatican II</emphasis> (London and Dublin: Geoffrey Chapman, 1966), pp. 140f.</para></footnote> Although in Roman Catholic theology the priest at the altar is (rightly) seen as <emphasis role="italic">in persona Christi</emphasis>, it is also true that the priest is (rightly) seen as the representative of the congregation, thus<emphasis role="italic"> in persona ecclesiae</emphasis>,<emphasis role="italic"> </emphasis>for it is clear that Vatican II teaches that the community not only fully participates in the liturgy, but also corporately celebrates the sacraments.<footnote label="78" role="end-ch-note" xml:id="BLO-C013-87A02A4"><para>SC 7 (Abbott, <emphasis role="italic">Documents of Vatican II</emphasis>, p. 141): ‘In the liturgy full public worship is performed by the Mystical Body of Jesus Christ, that is, by the Head and his members.’ SC 14 (Abbott, <emphasis role="italic">Documents of Vatican II</emphasis>, p. 144): ‘Mother church earnestly desires that all the faithful be led to that full, conscious and active participation in liturgical celebrations which demanded by the very nature of the liturgy. Such participation by the Christian people as “a chosen race, a royal priesthood, a holy nation, a purchased people” (1Peter 2.9; cf. 2.4–5), is their right and duty by reason of their baptism.’ On Christ’s presence in the community through the ministry of the sacraments see also Edward Schillebeeckx, <emphasis role="italic">Christ the Sacrament of the Encounter with God</emphasis> (London: Sheed and Ward, 1963) and Judith M. Kubicki, <emphasis role="italic">The Presence of Christ in the Gathered Assembly</emphasis> (New York and London: Continuum, 2006).</para></footnote> Hence the convention to speak of the priest as the 'president' <emphasis role="italic">at</emphasis> the Eucharist, rather than the 'celebrant' <emphasis role="italic">of</emphasis> the Eucharist. It is the birthright of Christians that, gathered in community, they celebrate the liturgy together. It is their work (<emphasis role="italic">leiturgia</emphasis>) and in doing it they are telling their own story.</para><para ele-id="DC6A5CB">The priest, both in liturgical celebration and in pastoral ministry is the embodied representative in that context of the church, the worshipping, serving Christian community, and in no other capacity, so <emphasis role="italic">in persona ecclesiae</emphasis>. In pastoral encounter, the minister is present in no way as a free-lance individual exercising their personal gifts and exerting the power of their personality – God forbid – but as an agent and instrument of the church where Christ is present and at work through word, sacrament and pastoral care, so also <emphasis role="italic">in persona Christi</emphasis>. The minister is called simply to represent and – yes – to mediate as a channel the Threefold Word: Jesus Christ, the Christian Scriptures and the church’s message; and to do so by standing aside in a self-effacing way, so that the Word can have its full effect, bringing healing of body, mind and spirit.</para></section></chapter></book>