<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE book SYSTEM "docbook.dtd"><book><chapter><label ele-id="36F86254"><emphasis role="bold">Chapter 9. Deviance and Social Control</emphasis></label><title ele-id="36F86256"><emphasis role="italic">Lizabeth A.</emphasis><emphasis role="italic"> </emphasis><emphasis role="italic">Crawford and</emphasis><emphasis role="italic"> </emphasis><emphasis role="italic">Katherine B.</emphasis><emphasis role="italic"> </emphasis><emphasis role="italic">Novak</emphasis></title><para ele-id="20FBF953"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">This chapter begins with a discussion of the constructed nature of deviance, its relativity (what is defined as deviant varies across cultures, across groups within a given society, and over time), and why people typically act in a manner that is consistent with prevailing societal norms.  The influence of money and power in the creation of societal norms and laws is then highlighted and patterns of</emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow"> </emphasis></emphasis><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">delinquency and criminal offending by social class, race and ethnicity, and gender are identified.  The second part of the chapter focuses on prominent theories of deviance from within the different faces of sociological social psychology, including structural strain theory, within social structure and personality, and differential association theory and labeling theory, within the symbolic interactionist tradition.  Micro-level perspectives from within the symbolic interactionist face of social psychology on labeling processes and the social and psychological consequences of being defined as deviant, how individuals manage the stigma associated with a deviant identity, and the nature and function of degradation rituals are emphasized.  The chapter ends with a discussion of how work within the group process and structures orientation can be used to increase our understanding of why deviant behavior within small groups is relatively uncommon.</emphasis></para><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F86257"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box Start&#x003E;</emphasis></title></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F8625C"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box End&#x003E;</emphasis></title><para ele-id="44B072E7">How would you describe the person sitting on a towel, in her swimsuit, reading in a computer lab where classes are regularly held? How would you view this college student if you encountered her in the same position outside, as in the photo on the right? This is the same person, dressed the same way, engaging in the same behavior. Yet, how we evaluate this individual depends on the social setting she is in. Outside, this student appears normal. In the computer lab, the student in the picture is likely to be regarded by others as deviant (i.e., outside of the norm) because she is wearing inappropriate classroom attire and acting in a way that is unusual in this setting.</para><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F8625E"><emphasis role="bold">WHAT IS DEVIANCE?</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F8625F"><emphasis role="bold">Deviance</emphasis> refers to behaviors that violate social norms and result in negative sanctions or reactions from others. Deviance can range from relatively trivial (e.g., sitting backward in your desk during class) to serious (e.g., murder) behaviors. In addition, while we most often focus on negative or bad behaviors, behavior that is defined as positive or good by society may be considered deviant by others if it is outside the range of societal expectations. For example, although cleanliness is considered to be a good thing, someone who is excessively clean (e.g., someone who takes multiple showers a day or cleans his house constantly) is likely to be seen as strange, different, or deviant by others.</para><para ele-id="36F86260">Do you know anyone who is eccentric? People often use this term to describe individuals who violate social conventions, called folkways. <emphasis role="bold">Folkways</emphasis> govern the way in which we keep our houses, what and when to eat, how we dress, and how we spend our leisure time, among other things. <emphasis role="bold">Mores</emphasis>, on the other hand, pertain to more serious issues. For instance, they prohibit murder or the enactment of behaviors that harm other people in other ways.</para><para ele-id="36F86261"><emphasis role="bold">Laws</emphasis>, a third type of social norm, are formally codified and enforced by the state through the institution of criminal justice (the criminal justice system). Laws often, but do not always, correspond to societal mores. For example, laws against murder coincide with most people’s moral code, whereas laws against speeding on the highway and on other public roads are not perceived as moral imperatives.</para><para ele-id="36F86262">Deviance includes all norm violations, including transgressions that violate both informal norms (those that are taken for granted but rarely put in writing; such as, wearing appropriate clothing to class) and formal norms (those that are written down; such as, organizational rules or policies and laws). <emphasis role="bold">Crime</emphasis> is a subcategory or type of deviance that occurs when someone breaks the law.</para><para ele-id="36F86263">The term “deviance” also applies to people’s personal characteristics. Individuals with particular attributes (e.g., people who are overweight, have a mental health condition, are addicted to substances, or much taller or shorter than average) are often regarded by others as abnormal (Kaplan 2006). <link er-cited="true" linkend="T9.1" role="table">Table 9.1</link><table orient="port" role="float" xml:id="T9.1"><label>TABLE 9.1</label><title ele-id="72C9D74C"> Some Topics of Recent Articles on Deviance by Sociological Social psychologists</title><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry><tp ele-id="44557FDC">Police who snitch</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="1F170180">Dirt eating</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="58CE0264">Cyberbullying</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="723E9DE0">Corporate crime in the pharmaceutical industry</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="74CE2FB3">Prisoner’s wives</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="2508D96B">Commercial burglary</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="3FC724E5">Heroin abusers</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="55DF4014">Suicide among dentists</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="4A77BCA0">Child molesters</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="6E8C19AB">Ex-psychiatric inpatients</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="12A141FF">Mental illness</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="4F6D8264">Bug chasers (men who try to get infected with HIV)</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="4BE2FC88">Homosexuality</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="5DFECA64">Incest</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="3686DFBF">Physical disabilities</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="6F428058">Involuntary psychiatric hospitalization</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="4925A879">Marijuana use</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="44BD13C1">Belief in UFOs</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="6BD43EC1">Employee theft</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="487869C6">Sexual asphyxia</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="6CE2D3CE">Strippers</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="54E471F5">Johns (men who go to prostitutes)</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="75F931E5">Cybersex</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="73FC1D58">Gambling</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="27BD10A7">Dogfighting</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="1B34A27F">Academic cheating</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="4611C364">Middle-class coke dealers</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="3281A839">Female patrons of male strip clubs</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="566BF5DA">Sexual harassment</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="06C38810">Morticians and funeral directors</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="4E7199FD">Poaching</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="772D573F">Serial murders</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="3CB4B5D0">Fraternity gang rape</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="7BAFB34B">Satanic cults</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="6A06E4B3">Homelessness</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="25808FC7">Self-injurers</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="5B3BF16B">Shoplifters</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="25A9884A">Medicare and Medicaid fraud</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="30584CE9">Child exploitation websites</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="468B5CBD">Snitches</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="7E422BB2">Wildlife trafficking</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="4B9353F5">Infanticide</tp></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table> includes a list of deviant behaviors, crimes, and deviant attributes that have been recently studied by sociological social psychologists. You can see here that deviance as a subfield of study is quite broad in its focus.</para><para ele-id="68B0C5EF">Historically, sociologists have referred to research on deviance as the study of “nuts and sluts” (Gibbs 1981). This (tongue-in-cheek) label reflects the breadth of work in this subfield (behaviors that are unconventional, as well as those that are illegal) and the fact that it was, and is still to some extent, a bit controversial. The study of deviance delves into behaviors that some people might prefer not to know about, and it reminds us that pressing life questions (what is good or moral behavior and what behaviors are wrong or bad) rarely have definitive answers that apply to all individuals in all social settings. Regarding this latter point, the literature on deviance serves as a reminder that conceptions of good and bad, right and wrong, or normative and deviant are subjective.</para></section></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F86265"><emphasis role="bold">Deviance as a Social Construction</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F86266">You can’t have good, desirable behavior without its bad, undesirable counterpart. Thus, although moral boundaries (what’s good vs. bad) change, there will always be behavior regarded as deviant in every society.  Drawing attention to deviant behavior helps make</para><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F86267"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box Start&#x003E;</emphasis></title></section></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F862AB"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box End&#x003E;</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F862AC">clear to people within a society what constitutes moral conduct. Moreover, identifying and responding to deviance promotes social unity among individuals whose behaviors are normative and lawful (Durkheim 1895).</para><para ele-id="36F862AD">Whether a behavior is considered deviant is a function of social factors. People define a particular behavior as bad, wrong, or immoral when it violates societal expectations for appropriate behavior within a given social context. Because there is variation in norms from culture to culture, across groups within a society, and within the same culture over time, we need to know the context in which a behavior occurred before we know if it will be seen by others as normal or deviant. Because norms also vary across situations and across statuses, the immediate social context in which behavior occurs and the characteristics of the actor will also determine whether an act is considered deviant or not.</para><para ele-id="36F862AE">The following examples illustrate the manner in which definitions of deviance vary cross-culturally, across groups (or subcultures) within a given society, over time, across situations, and across statuses.</para><blockquote><para ele-id="30730646">•	<emphasis role="bold">Cultural variation:</emphasis> Wearing your shoes inside your house in the United States is common and is typically not considered deviant. However, entering someone’s home without first removing your shoes in Japan violates prevailing social norms and would be viewed as offensive.</para><para ele-id="36F862B0">•	<emphasis role="bold">Subcultural or group variation:</emphasis> In some peer groups drinking heavily and its consequences (e.g., disclosing more information in conversation than is typical among nonintoxicated individuals) are valued, viewed as fun or funny, and expected of group members. In other peer groups drinking to excess and the lack of self-regulation associated with alcohol intoxication are regarded as highly deviant and to be avoided.</para><para ele-id="36F862B1">•	<emphasis role="bold">Changes over time:</emphasis> Having tattoos was once considered deviant. Today, they are common. Although views on this behavior have changed, tattoos are still seen as less deviant within certain subcultures (e.g., heavy metal musicians and their fans) and among particular social categories (e.g., adolescents and young adults). There are also norms concerning the number of tattoos people should have and how visible they should be, which affect whether this form of body modification is defined as deviant (Adams 2009). The following photos illustrate some of these rules. What about the first photo, the one of the man with tattoos on his upper body and neck? Is this person deviant?</para><para ele-id="36F862B2">•	<emphasis role="bold">Situational variation:</emphasis> It’s normative to wear a swimsuit when you’re sitting around a pool with friends or sunbathing outside your house. On the other hand, this attire is so inappropriate to the college classroom that it is likely to generate stares, comments, and snickers from those who are present. In fact, if someone wore a swimsuit to class, like the individual in the picture at the beginning of the chapter, it would probably be quite disruptive to the lecture or activities the professor had planned. If class were in session, the professor would probably ask the student dressed in swimwear to leave the room.</para><para ele-id="36F862B3">•	<emphasis role="bold">Variations across statuses:</emphasis> In this society, it is common for women to carry personal belongings in a purse. What if a male carried a purse? How would you evaluate this person and their behavior? In this culture, this individual would most likely be seen as deviant. He has violated the expectations of what it means to be a male in this society.</para></blockquote><para ele-id="36F862B4">Because deviance depends upon the cultural and situational context in which it occurs, and the social characteristics of the actor, no behavior is in and of itself deviant.</para><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F862B5"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box Start&#x003E;</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F862B9"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">[Insert Photo 9.21, 9.22 and 9.23 here (9.21 and 9.22 side by side and 9.23 below)]</emphasis></para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F862BB"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box End&#x003E;</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F862BC">An act is deviant only when people define it as such. It is for this reason that social psychologists regard deviance as a social construct.</para><listitem><para ele-id="3440E5BF"><emphasis role="bold">Q:	What about murder? Isn’t killing someone inherently bad or deviant?</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="040F0AB5">A:	Killing someone is not always defined as murder. We need information about the</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="03D182C0">context within which the killing occurred to know if it was murder and therefore deviant.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="2126B227">Was it a soldier who killed someone during wartime? Did someone kill another person in</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="3527F8D2">self-defense? Did the state carry out the death penalty to punish someone for a crime? Did a</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="291A8CF7">corporation sell unsafe products resulting in the death of individuals? Did an individual</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="4019474E">intentionally shoot someone in order to take her possessions? Whether a particular act</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="7EA5BF15">killing is considered murder within this society varies across the social contexts just</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="6A0A76FF">described (e.g., carrying out the death penalty vs. shooting someone during a robbery) and is</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="037A8CB7">therefore a social construction.</para></listitem></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F862BF"><emphasis role="bold">WHY STUDY DEVIANCE?</emphasis></title><para ele-id="29A200C4">Because definitions of deviance are relative, they are often arbitrary.  As a result, access to important societal resources—power, money, and prestige—influences who makes the rules and to whom they apply. This makes deviance a topic of substantial interest to sociological social psychologists, who study how macro-level societal patterns, including inequality between groups, shape people’s perceptions and behaviors. Because psychologists are less likely to address this issue, almost all of the social psychological research on deviance has been conducted by sociological social psychologists.</para><para ele-id="0DD57B61">Drawing on this literature, we discuss how perceptions of what is, and is not, deviant vary across groups within society in this chapter.  We also describe the processes through which some people’s, but not others’, behaviors are classified as deviant, which tends to reflect prevailing patterns of social inequality, and what happens to someone once others regard them as deviant, which helps to reproduce the existing stratification hierarchy.  However, before examining how deviance is intertwined with social inequality, we discuss some of the more general functions of deviance within society and how people’s reactions to others’, and sometimes their own, deviant actions serves as a mechanism of social control.</para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="4B52ACE7"><emphasis role="bold">MECHANISMS OF SOCIAL CONTROL</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F862C4">There are three mechanisms of social control that encourage conformity and thus reduce deviance among members of society. They are commonly referred to as formal control, informal (or interpersonal) control, and internal (or self) control.</para><para ele-id="36F862C5">When someone breaks the law, they have committed a crime and may be sanctioned by the state for this violation. In the case of crimes, the state has the authority to punish individuals and typically does so through the use of fines, community service, or incarceration. This is a type of <emphasis role="bold">formal control</emphasis>. Formal control refers to sanctions imposed by authorized individuals to encourage conformity. Another example of formal control is the use of suspensions by a university to encourage students to follow the university’s rules for conduct, which are usually spelled out in the university’s student handbook or some comparable document.</para><para ele-id="36F862C6">A second type of social control, <emphasis role="bold">informal control</emphasis>, operates through interpersonal feedback and is rooted in our capacity for embarrassment. We discussed how embarrassment facilitates the self-regulation of public behavior in the previous chapter. We behave in an appropriate (normative) manner when we are around others in order to avoid experiencing embarrassment, the emotion that emerges when an individual fails in a public performance.</para><para ele-id="36F862C7">Whereas informal control requires the presence of others, a third type of social control, internal control, is not directly tied to others’ reactions. <emphasis role="bold">Internal control</emphasis> operates through guilt. People experience guilt when they engage in behavior perceived as immoral, even if no one else is aware that they have violated a societal rule (a norm or the law).</para><para ele-id="36F862C8">In many instances, all three mechanisms of social control (formal, informal, and internal) are in place at the same time and, as a result, the likelihood of rule violation is very low. For example, not only is murder against the law (formal control), most people believe that others would reject them if they were a murderer (informal control), and the vast majority of Americans view murder as immoral and wrong (internal control). As a result, formal, informal, and internal control mechanisms are present in most situations, resulting in relatively low rates of murder relative to other rule violations.</para><listitem><para ele-id="353483A9"><emphasis role="bold">Q:	What if some of the elements of social control are missing? Which of the three</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="3831E63D"><emphasis role="bold">mechanisms of social control is the most effective in regulating behavior by itself, and</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="36F862C9"><emphasis role="bold">which form of social control is the least effective in doing so?</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="016D9728"><emphasis role="bold">A:</emphasis>	In general, internal control is the most effective regulator of behavior because it</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="2B730B44">involves feelings of guilt. Because guilt is not tied to the reactions of others, an individual</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="4C9C5E87">can’t escape it by simply hiding their behaviors. Shame may also serve as a mechanism of</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="2E8CDB5D">internal control, but only when it isn’t tied to the responses of specific others (this would</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="330E26A9">make it a type of informal control).</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="30676AB3">Formal control, on the other hand, is the least effective form of social control because</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="7E9E8754">it applies only to those situations in which we think our behaviors are, or will be, visible to</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="13FF31D4">agents of social control. Agents of formal social control represent social institutions and include</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="5A7AF43E">police officers, school administrators, teachers, bosses, religious leaders, and mental health and</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="4A5B810A">health officials.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="62FBFFB9">Informal control is somewhere in between internal and formal control when it comes to</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="19CD3306">regulating behavior. The presence of almost anyone is enough for interpersonal concerns to</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="36F862CC">shape our behaviors. However, informal control doesn’t occur when we are alone.</para></listitem></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F862CD"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box Start&#x003E;</emphasis></title></section></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F862CE"><emphasis role="bold">What Do You Think?</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F862CF">How might the three types of social control (formal, informal, and internal) influence college students’ likelihoods of cheating on exams and papers?</para><listitem><para ele-id="36F862D0">■	Get together with two or three of your classmates and come up with at least four reasons why students don’t cheat. Have someone in the group write them down.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="36F862D1">■ 	Next, determine which form of social control underlies each of the reasons for not cheating. There is likely to be some variability {e.g., some reasons for not cheating reflect formal control mechanisms, others reflect informal control, and so forth).</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="36F862D2">■ 	When are students most likely to cheat on tests and exams? Explain.</para></listitem></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="570F4883"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box End&#x003E;</emphasis></title><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F862D4"><emphasis role="bold">SOCIETAL PATTERNS</emphasis></title><para ele-id="67AF844C">Although most people conform to societal norms in most settings, this is not always the case. Research on deviance and crime suggests the following patterns.</para></section></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F862D6"><emphasis role="bold">Deviance Among Youth</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F862D7">Much of the literature on deviance and crime has focused on youth. These survey-based analyses often use measures of delinquency similar to the one you completed in Chapter 2 (Box 2.1), or they focus on criminal behaviors or the frequency of arrest. The following patterns have been documented among adolescents.</para><para ele-id="22F727C7">Social class effects on delinquency vary with the type of offense under investigation and are relatively weak. Overall, having economic problems is a stronger risk factor for delinquency than class background. Regarding this, it is important to note that whether someone thinks they are experiencing economic problems is subjective and may reflect their selection of reference groups and aspirations as well as objective factors (economic resources). Thus, the perception that one is having economic problems is not necessarily related to social class (Agnew et al. 2008).</para><para ele-id="5EEE1873">Like social class, race and ethnicity are not strongly associated with delinquency across studies. There is some evidence that Black youth have higher rates of violence (but not property crimes or substance use) than their White counterparts (Felson and Kreager 2015), but other studies show lower levels of delinquency among Black than among White adolescents (Chambers and Erausquin 2018).  Similarly, Hispanics are similar to Whites in their risks for various types of offending, while Asian American youth have low overall levels of deviance.</para><para ele-id="733FB18C">On average, White adolescents tend to exhibit the highest levels of substance use. Presumably, this is because White youth are the group most heavily involved in a party subculture (Felson and Kreager 2015). There are no notable racial/ethnic differences in serious delinquency, though, including offenses severe enough to result in arrest (Agnew 2016; Piquero and Brame 2008).</para><para ele-id="6F0656CE">In contrast, as you probably know, males are more likely to engage in deviant behaviors than females. This gender effect is evident among youth (Chambers and Erausquin 2018; Piquero and Brame 2008) and, as described in the following section, among adults.</para></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F862DB"><emphasis role="bold">Deviance Among Adults</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F862DC">Most studies of deviance among adults have focused on crime, the violation of norms that have been formally codified into law. Presumably, this is due to two factors: the availability of data (government data on crime are readily accessible to social psychologists and other social scientists) and concerns about the well-being of the population (crime often has more negative consequences than other deviant behaviors).</para><para ele-id="632D2BA2">There are sizable gender differences in criminal behavior (male &#x003E; female), especially for violent offenses (U.S. Department of Justice 2019). Men are also more likely than women to be involved in corporate financial crimes, despite increases in women’s representation in professional and managerial positions (Steffensmeier, Schwartz and Roche 2013). The gender gap in some crimes (robbery, burglary, and motor vehicle theft) has, however, been steadily decreasing since the 1960s (O’Brien 1999). Moreover, there is some evidence, albeit inconsistent across studies, that the gender gap in violence is declining (Kruttschnitt 2013).</para><para ele-id="56EFDC03">The convergence in crime rates across gender is presumably due to women’s increased financial independence and changing gender roles, which accord women more latitude today than in the past. As gender equality has increased within this society, women’s and men’s attitudes and behaviors have become more similar, although men are still substantially more likely than women to engage in criminal activities (U.S. Department of Justice 2019).</para><para ele-id="36F862DD">Unlike gender, social class does not have consistent effects on crime rates, in opposition to prevailing cultural stereotypes, and it is questionable as to whether class and a propensity for crime are even related (<emphasis role="underline">Wikström</emphasis> and <emphasis role="underline">Treiber</emphasis><superscript> </superscript>2016).  There is, however, an association between social class and the type of crime committed. In general, the lower class are more involved in what are considered traditional street crimes, while the upper class are more likely to commit offenses such as embezzlement or fraud (Rosoff, Pontell, and Tillman 2004; Tittle, Villemez, and Smith 1978).</para><para ele-id="36F862DE">Also, contrary to prevailing cultural beliefs, there are few racial/ethnic differences in crime among adults who are in the same social class. This suggests that the higher rates of crime observed among racial and ethnic minorities (in particular, Hispanics and Blacks) in comparison to Whites are due to economic factors (Haynie, Weiss, and Piquero 2008; Kaufman 2005).</para><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F862E1"><emphasis role="bold">RESEARCH ON THE CAUSES OF DEVIANCE WITHIN SOCIAL STRUCTURE AND PERSONALITY</emphasis></title><para ele-id="71621172">Approaches to the study of deviance within social structure and personality locate the causes of deviant behavior and crime in the organization of society rather than within individuals. Thus, they focus on identifying the social conditions that produce high rates of deviance and crime and help us to understand some of the patterns described in the previous section. This literature is well developed and encompasses a number of theories that specify the conditions under which people are likely to become deviant with a high degree of precision. Their unifying theme is an emphasis on the intervening interpersonal and psychological mechanisms that link social structure to deviant behavior.</para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F862E3"><emphasis role="bold">Structural Strain Theory</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F862E4">Strain theories focus on the psychological states that result from structural conditions. The most well-known <emphasis role="bold">strain theory</emphasis> was developed by Robert K. Merton (1938, 1968). The crux of this theory is that anomie causes deviance and crime.</para><para ele-id="36F862E5"><emphasis role="bold">Anomie</emphasis> is a term familiar to most sociologists. According to Durkheim (1897), anomie occurs when societal norms lose their regulatory power and don’t exert a strong enough influence on people’s aspirations and behaviors. People experiencing anomie often aren’t sure how they should act. Hence, anomie causes frustration and is associated with an increase in suicide, a type of deviant behavior. Durkheim (1897) argued that rapid social change is one cause of anomie.</para><para ele-id="36F862E6">Merton, like Durkheim, attributed deviance to anomie. However, Merton (1938) argued that the conditions that produce anomie are built into the structure of American society. He focused on the gap between what people are socialized to aspire to and what they might realistically achieve given prevailing patterns of social inequality (Merton 1938).</para><para ele-id="36F862E7">Within this culture, people are socialized to desire many goals, but Merton (1938) argued that financial or material success is emphasized as being of the utmost importance. Americans are encouraged to strive for economic success, and most individuals in this society have internalized this message: they want to be rich.</para><para ele-id="36F862E8">Society also defines the appropriate or legitimate means for becoming rich, which include education, hard work, and landing a good job. Conformity, or abiding by the norms of society, means that an individual is seeking material success through these avenues.</para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F862E9"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box Start&#x003E;</emphasis></title></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F862EC"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box End&#x003E;</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F862ED">Although Merton felt that most societal members desire economic success, he recognized that not all members of society have access to the legitimate means for achieving it.  This creates strain, which may lead individuals to turn to alternative (nonlegitimate) means for making money. From this perspective, nonlegitimate means for making money include crimes like dealing drugs or robbery. According to Merton, individuals who engage in these behaviors are <emphasis role="bold">innovators</emphasis> because, in the face of blocked opportunities, they turn to illegitimate (criminal) means of attaining a key culturally defined goal (making a lot of money).</para><para ele-id="36F862EE">Merton (1938) argued that strain is more common among the lower class because this is the group with limited access to the legitimate means to achieve success. Because they lack access to the legitimate means to success, individuals toward the bottom of the stratification hierarchy should be more likely than their more socioeconomically advantaged counterparts to engage in monetary-based crimes. Strain (which results from the gap between aspirations and opportunities) is hypothesized to be the intervening variable in this causal chain. Being lower class increases strain, which in turn puts one at risk for participation in criminal activities.</para><para ele-id="36F862EF">The relationships between class, strain, and crime are depicted in <link er-cited="true" linkend="F9.1" role="figure">Figure 9.1</link><figure xml:id="F9.1"><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/fig9.1.jpg"/></imageobject></mediaobject><label>FIGURE 9.1</label><caption><para ele-id="2A3712E8"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow"> </emphasis><emphasis role="highlight:yellow"><emphasis role="italic">Structural Strain Theory</emphasis></emphasis></para></caption></figure>. Survey analyses using measures consonant with Merton’s conceptualization of strain (e.g., Farnworth and Leiber 1989; Vowell and May 2007) have yielded results that are largely consistent with his theory.</para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F862F0"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box Start&#x003E;</emphasis></title></section></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F862F1"><emphasis role="bold">What Do You Think?</emphasis></title><blockquote><para ele-id="36F862F2">■ 	Why are you in college? Do you know anyone with similar goals to your own who was not able to continue their education for financial or other reasons? How have they responded to this situation? Does Merton’s strain theory provide an explanation for their reactions?</para><para ele-id="36F862F3">■ 	Consider the policy implications of Merton’s model. If crime is caused by structural strain, what might be done to reduce this type of behavior?</para></blockquote><section role="H2"><title ele-id="61365EDE"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box End&#x003E;</emphasis></title></section></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F862F5"><emphasis role="italic">Social Comparison Processes and Relative Deprivation</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F862F6">Although Merton’s theory was developed to explain financially motivated crimes among the lower classes, it may also apply to more affluent individuals. As you know, research in social structure and personality has shown that reference groups shape both our aspirations and our self-evaluations. When people fall short of the financial benchmark set by their selection of a reference group, they experience relative deprivation.</para><para ele-id="36F862F7">Insofar as these individuals feel that they cannot enhance their economic standing through legitimate means, they may be at risk for deviant behavior. Thus, aspects of Merton’s theory, in particular the concept of anomie, can be used to explain financially motivated crimes committed by individuals who most of us would consider to be fairly well off. These individuals include company chief executive officers (CEOs), chief financial officers (CFOs), and other corporate executives,  If they are making less than members of their reference groups (e.g., friends, top company officials, or others working in the industry), individuals in these kinds of high-paying positions may engage in criminal behaviors, or behaviors that violate the spirit of the law and that others within society are likely to view as deviant, in order to increase their earnings. See Box 9.1 for a discussion of how Merton’s strain theory can be used to explain deviant behavior within the health care industry.</para><section role="H2"><title ele-id="31381361"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box Start&#x003E;</emphasis></title></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="6CB06B35"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box End&#x003E;</emphasis></title></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F862F8"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box Start&#x003E;</emphasis></title></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="5C05CA42"><emphasis role="bold">Box 9.1 Merton, Anomie, and Heath Care Fraud</emphasis></title></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="7FD79FEF">July 20, 2022</title><para ele-id="6B31314A"><emphasis role="italic">The Department of Justice today announced criminal charges against 36 defendants in 13 federal districts across the United States for more than $1.2 billion in alleged fraudulent telemedicine, cardiovascular and cancer genetic testing, and durable medical equipment (DME) schemes.</emphasis></para><para ele-id="593CD5EC"><emphasis role="italic">The nationwide coordinated law enforcement action includes criminal charges against a telemedicine company executive, owners and executives of clinical laboratories, durable medical equipment companies, marketing organizations, and medical professionals. In connection with the enforcement action, the department seized over $8 million in cash, luxury vehicles, and other fraud proceeds.</emphasis></para><para ele-id="0DE7AA43"><emphasis role="italic">Additionally, the Centers for Medicare &#x0026; Medicaid Services (CMS), Center for Program Integrity (CPI) announced today that it took administrative actions against 52 providers involved in similar schemes.</emphasis></para><para ele-id="19E67D7E">The above text, taken verbatim from a U.S. Department of Justice, Office of Public Affairs press release (<emphasis role="underline">https://www.justice.gov/opa/pr/justice-department-charges-dozens-12-billion-health-care-fraud</emphasis>), reflects the government’s aggressive stance on health care fraud, a type of white-collar crime that, according to the National Health Care Anti-Fraud Association (NHCAA 2023), results in tens of billions of dollars in losses annually.</para><para ele-id="68F18ECA">The Department of Justice also lists “noteworthy” recent fraud cases pertaining to health care that resulted in convictions under <emphasis role="italic">Justice News</emphasis>, accessible from their Health Care Fraud Unit webpage.  Some cases are related to the misuse of COVID-19 relief funds but many involve fraudulent Medicare claims, laboratory testing, or prescriptions, and the fraud is usually perpetrated by medical professionals, frequently doctors or pharmacists.</para><para ele-id="12E8830E">A social psychologist might ask why health care fraud is so pervasive and what motivates this type of deviant behavior among individuals who are, presumably, doing well financially, at least in comparison to much of the U.S. population.  The answer may lie in Merton’s structural strain theory.  Doctors and pharmacists, who have high salaries relative to many individuals in the U.S. might feel deprived relative to their peers (others in working in the medical field), or to people within this society who are rich (e.g., individuals in the top 5% of the income/wealth distribution). This could serve as a catalyst for their criminal activities, which are most certainly financially motivated.</para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="4BEEA197"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">Box End</emphasis></title></section></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F86300"><emphasis role="bold">General Strain Theory</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F86301">Focusing on nonfinancial, as well as economically motivated, forms of deviance, Agnew (1992, 2000) extended Merton’s concept of strain to include a wider range of precipitating social conditions. According to his <emphasis role="bold">general strain theory</emphasis>, strain results from the failure to achieve economic or noneconomic goals, racial discrimination, the removal of positive stimuli (e.g., the death of a parent, the termination of a romantic relationship), or the introduction of negative stimuli into someone’s life (e.g., being bullied at school, having arguments with parents). The presence of strain from these sources increases individuals’ levels of stress, especially when the events causing strain occur around the same time. Stress, in turn, results in negative emotions including frustration, unhappiness, and anger, which translate into various forms of deviant behavior.</para><para ele-id="5B3CF9E1">General strain theory has been subject to many empirical tests. These (survey-based) analyses suggest that general strain explains participation in a wide range of deviant and criminal activities, including the violation of military rules (Bucher 2011), corporate crime (Passas 1990), alcohol and drug use (Agnew and White 1992), bullying (Patchin and Hinduja 2011), gambling (Eitle and Taylor 2011), and trolling behaviors (e.g., insulting or swearing at someone for no clear reason) online (Wilson and Seigfried-Spellar 2023).</para></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F86303"><emphasis role="bold">Social Control Theory</emphasis></title><para ele-id="24544968">Whereas strain theories emphasize the structural roots of deviant behavior, control theories locate the cause of deviance within the individual. Hirschi’s (1969) social control theory is the most well-known theory within this tradition. Because it focuses on the individual, at the micro level, Hirschi’s control theory is not itself a structural model. However, it has been used by sociological social psychologists working in the social structure and personality orientation to address structural issues. We provide an overview of Hirschi’s theory, which was developed to explain juvenile delinquency, and then discuss its more macro-level extensions by social structure and personality (SSP) researchers.</para><para ele-id="70771D53">According to Hirschi (1969), we are all motivated to break the rules because it often offers a quick and easy way to get what we want or need.  Given this general tendency to deviate from social norms, <emphasis role="bold">social control theory</emphasis> focuses on explaining why individuals conform, rather than why they deviate. Note that the strain theories discussed in the previous section focus on why people deviate from societal norms. Social control theorists argue that it is the <emphasis role="bold">social bonds</emphasis> that individuals have to conventional (mainstream) society (e.g., to their parents; their school; or through participation in conventional activities, like team sports, or the internalization of laws and rules) that constrains (controls) them and encourages conforming behavior. Therefore, individuals who are weakly bonded to society are more likely to violate the law than those with strong bonds (Hirschi 1969).</para><para ele-id="519EC796">Socialization and participation in societal institutions are presumed to be important in the formation of strong bonds to society.  Hirschi’s theory does not, however, directly address why the bonds of some individuals are stronger than others or whether social bonds vary with individuals’ positions within the structure of society, something of interest to social psychologists working within the social structure and personality tradition.</para><para ele-id="0DE9A4A6">As noted earlier, some researchers have expanded Hirschi’s (1969) control theory in an attempt to address issues of relevance to the social structure and personality face of social psychology. For example, the study by Bui (2009), reviewed in Chapter 1, linked parental attachment (low child–mother conflict), one dimension of social bonding, to low levels of delinquency among immigrant youths.  Other analyses linking bonds to society to social structure have focused mainly on gender. Early studies showed that males did not have higher levels of deviance than females because they have weaker bonds to conventional society (Jensen and Eve 1976; White and LaGrange 1987). However, weak social bonds were associated with participation in delinquency among both males and females in a number of studies (e.g., Chapple, McQuillan, and Berdahl 2005; Sampson and Laub 1993), and more recent research indicates that concepts central to social control theory provide a good explanation as to why boys tend to be more delinquent than girls (Nofziger 2019).</para><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F86311"><emphasis role="bold">RESEARCH ON HOW DEVIANCE IS LEARNED</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F86312">Although the theories described in the previous section have provided some insight into why people engage in deviance (limited economic opportunities and other strains or weak bonds to society), in order to truly understand when and why people deviate from social norms, we need to know something about the processes through which deviant behaviors are acquired. As you might expect, sociological social psychologists take the stance that people learn deviant behavior the same way that they learn to behave in a normative manner: through their socialization experiences.</para><para ele-id="35D31EEE">Many deviant behaviors are learned during childhood or adolescence, whereas others are acquired later in life, typically at work or in other organizational settings. In either case, the initiation of deviant behavior almost always occurs in groups or as the result of an individual’s group affiliations (Kaplan 2006).</para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F86314"><emphasis role="bold">The Symbolic Interactionist Model Revisited</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F86315">We discussed Becker’s (1963) study of the experiences of marijuana users at the beginning of Chapter 3, on symbolic interactionism. Becker (1963) argues that these individuals had to learn how to interpret and respond to the physiological effects of this drug. Getting high was not an inherently pleasant experience. Rather, the participants in Becker’s study learned from more seasoned users to interpret their physiological sensations in a positive manner as they became socialized into a subculture of jazz musicians in which marijuana use was common.</para><para ele-id="36F86316">Among the larger society at the time in which Becker was writing, most people regarded marijuana use as highly deviant. Thus, Becker refers to his participants as “Outsiders.” Symbolic interactionists emphasize the relative nature of deviance, and the qualitative literature on this topic, including Becker’s (1963) analysis, provides illustrations of how individuals learn what others within society define as deviant behavior.</para><dialogue><line ele-id="60138D33"><speaker/><emphasis role="bold">Q:	Is marijuana use still considered deviant in this society? Do you think its</emphasis></line></dialogue><listitem><para ele-id="36F86317"><emphasis role="bold">legalization in some states has affected people’s views on this issue?</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="0BC22A6B"><emphasis role="bold">A:</emphasis>	An analysis of data from the General Social Survey (Smith et al. 2017), generalizable</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="58DEF24B">to the U.S. adult population, suggests that it may have. In 1975, only 22% of GSS</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="4BBB06FE">respondents supported the legalization of marijuana. This percentage increased slightly each</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="1D537996">year throughout the 1970s, then dipped in the 1980s and 1990s (with a low of 17% in 1990).</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="4F74E53B">Since 1993 support for the legalization of marijuana has steadily risen, with larger increases</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="57B88900">following the legalization of marijuana for medical use by five states (California, Alaska,</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="18548B6E">Oregon, Washington, and Maine in 1996–1999). By 2000, it was estimated that 34% of the</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="00F94597">population believed that marijuana should be legal. In 2010 (15 states and the District of</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="198B18F6">Columbia allowed for the use of medicinal marijuana by the year’s end), 48% of GSS</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="111AE758">respondents favored the legalization of this substance. In 2016, by which time over half the</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="6097579C">states in the U.S. legally allowed the use of marijuana (but not all for recreational purposes),</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="0118B8B9">61% of the GSS sample supported its legalization (Smith et al. 2017).  Six years later, in</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="32DAD563">2022, 68% of U.S. adults were in favor of making marijuana legal (Van Green 2022).</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="48262E47">Clearly, support for the legalization of marijuana has increased substantially in this country.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="777BAC88">There is, however, still a lack of consensus as to whether marijuana use is a deviant behavior</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="04896B47">(assuming that support for the legalization of marijuana coincides with the perception that its</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="36F86318">use is not problematic or abnormal, which seems likely).</para></listitem></section></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F86319"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box Start&#x003E;</emphasis></title></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F8631A"><emphasis role="bold">Take a Break</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F8631B">For additional insight into how views of marijuana use have changed in the United States, check out the film <emphasis role="italic">Reefer Madness</emphasis> (1936), available for streaming online at <emphasis role="underline">http://archive.org/details/reefer_madness1938</emphasis>.</para><para ele-id="36F8631C">This cult classic was a serious attempt to reduce drug use when it was produced. The film’s message was “Don’t smoke marijuana because it will make you crazy.” Regardless of their views on the legalization of marijuana for medicinal or other purposes, most contemporary viewers find this movie entertaining.</para></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="43C21EDC"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box End&#x003E;</emphasis></title></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F8631E"><emphasis role="bold">Differential Association Theory</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F8631F"><emphasis role="bold">Differential association theory</emphasis> is a well-known theory of delinquency that is generally consistent with the premises of symbolic interactionism. Developed in the 1930s by Edwin Sutherland (1939), it is similar to the symbolic interactionist approach illustrated in Becker’s (1963) study of marijuana users in that it emphasizes the importance of socialization and the social processes through which deviance is learned.</para><para ele-id="36F86322">Sutherland (1939) argued that individuals learn to be deviant through their associations with others. Within these contexts, people are socialized to perceive the world and act in certain ways. Whereas some individuals acquire beliefs and norms that differ from those of the broader society, others learn to conform to conventional societal definitions and rules. Thus, according to this theory, anyone can become a deviant or a criminal. It is the social environment, and not innate characteristics or predispositions within individuals, which results in deviant actions. People who grow up in high-crime neighborhoods and are regularly exposed to criminal activities, for example, learn to define these behaviors as normative and are taught the tools of the trade (e.g., how to deal or buy drugs) as part of the socialization process.</para><para ele-id="5C6590D4">Despite its emphasis on socialization processes, the research Sutherland’s theory has generated is largely quantitative in orientation. Many of these studies measure specific perceptions and behaviors, as well as the nature of individuals’ (usually adolescents’) group affiliations, called <emphasis role="bold">differential associations</emphasis>. Differential associations are measured using survey questions, which usually focus on how frequently adolescents’ friends engage in delinquent behavior.</para><para ele-id="36F86323">Given its applicability to virtually any social setting, differential association theory explains a wide range of deviant behaviors, including the crimes both of the rich and of the poor. Sutherland himself used his theory to explain why some individuals engage in <emphasis role="bold">white-collar crime</emphasis>, defined as crimes committed by people of relatively high status in the course of their occupation (Sutherland 1940), or become professional thieves (Sutherland 1937).</para><para ele-id="36F86324">Although people can learn from a wide range of associations within primary groups, Sutherland emphasized the importance of the family and peers as agents of socialization. Consistent with this tenet, research suggests that association with deviant peers is one of the strongest correlates of delinquency (Warr 2002).</para><para ele-id="36F86325">Differential association theory predicts that it is the association with delinquent peers that leads an individual to engage in delinquent behavior. However, it is possible that the relationship occurs the other way around. That is, there could be some other factor that causes an individual to engage in delinquent behavior, and then once a person becomes delinquent, they begin to associate with others who participate in similar (delinquent) activities.</para><para ele-id="36F86326">To address this issue of reverse causality, researchers have examined the direction of the relationship between peer relations and delinquency using longitudinal data. Most analyses show that the causal arrow goes both ways, from peers to delinquency, as predicted by Sutherland, and from delinquency to interaction with deviant peers (Thornberry et al. 1994).</para><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F86327"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box Start&#x003E;</emphasis></title></section></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F8632A"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box End&#x003E;</emphasis></title><para ele-id="34D155F5">This reciprocal relationship is depicted in <link er-cited="true" linkend="F9.2" role="figure">Figure 9.2</link><figure xml:id="F9.2"><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/fig9.2.jpg"/></imageobject></mediaobject><label>FIGURE 9.2</label><caption><para ele-id="466D750C"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow"> </emphasis><emphasis role="highlight:yellow"><emphasis role="italic">Reciprocal Relationship Between Peers and Delinquency</emphasis></emphasis></para></caption></figure>. The double plus sign on the arrow from peers to delinquency represents the results of an analysis of a large nationally representative dataset. The study results suggest that the effect of associations with delinquent peers on delinquency is stronger than the effect of delinquency on adolescents’ peer relationships (Matsueda and Anderson 1998).</para><para ele-id="7284724F">Research on deviant behavior in the workplace, which falls in the category of white-collar corporate crime, also provides support for differential association theory.  For example, the results of a qualitative study of twenty-two individuals working in the retail banking industry, who were interviewed over the phone, indicated that employees in these settings are often taught to engage in illegal, and what are considered by most people outside of the industry to be deviant, business practices by their bosses (Leasure and Zhang 2018) as part of a secondary socialization process (see pp. <emphasis role="highlight:yellow">XX-XX</emphasis> for a discussion of secondary, or adult, socialization).</para><para ele-id="3009D635">Presumably, the employees at Wells Fargo, who opened checking and savings accounts in customers’ names without their knowledge in order to meet their sales targets, didn’t think this type of behavior was okay when they started their jobs.  Rather, they learned that this was an acceptable business practice (as long as they didn’t get caught by bank regulators), and one that was necessary to meet stringent sales goals, while they were employed at the company (or through prior work experiences at similar companies within the retail bank industry).  As you may recall, the Wells Fargo fraudulent account scandal was in the news a lot in 2016, when the story broke, and, more recently, in 2023, when one of the company’s high-level executives, Carrie L. Tolstedt, pled guilty to concealing information about the illegal business practices that occurred there from 2011 to 2016.</para><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F8632C"><emphasis role="bold">Differential Reinforcement Theory</emphasis></title><para ele-id="79D79F81">Ronald Akers’ (Akers 1998; Burgess and Akers 1966) <emphasis role="bold">differential reinforcement theory</emphasis> extends Sutherland’s theory of differential association by specifying the mechanisms through which deviance is learned. Drawing on social learning theory (page <emphasis role="highlight:yellow">XXX</emphasis>), Akers argues that deviance is often acquired through imitation (role modeling) and reinforcement. Acts that are reinforced through reward or the avoidance of discomfort are likely to be repeated, whereas acts that result in punishments are likely to be avoided. As a result, individuals are most likely to engage in criminal behavior when differential associations result in definitions favorable to violating the law and this misconduct is reinforced by others with whom they have close relationships (Burgess and Akers 1966).</para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F8632E"><emphasis role="italic">Application: Social Learning and Dating Violence Among Teens</emphasis></title><para ele-id="65E0DA8B">It is estimated that 7 to 14.8% of teens are physically abused by a romantic partner (Gressard, Swahn and Tharp 2015). Most of this research has focused on cisgender adolescents in different-sex relationships. Differential reinforcement theory has often been used to assess the causes of dating violence among these individuals and studies support its utility in enhancing our understanding of when, and why, this behavior is likely to occur among this age group.  A meta-analysis of research (i.e., a study of studies) on this topic revealed the following effects.</para><orderedlist ele-id="260CEB4"><listitem><para ele-id="34C58F03"><token>1.</token>Having peers that engage in dating violence significantly increases the risk that teens will be physically violent toward their own romantic partner.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="3D4F05FF"><token>2.</token>Believing that dating violence will yield positive outcomes is also a strong determinant of which teens physically abuse their romantic partner.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="4AE01AFD"><token>3.</token>The factors that predict which boys and which girls are violent toward their romantic partner are generally similar, with one exception.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="30C52B36"><token>4.</token>Having traditional gender role attitudes increases the risk for perpetrating dating violence more among teen males than females (Pusch 2022), which isn’t surprising since this behavior is consonant with the expectation that males will be aggressive.</para></listitem></orderedlist><para ele-id="66C39ECE">Note that gender itself has a minimal effect on the perpetration of dating violence (Eisner 2021).  This is consistent with what’s been observed among adults.  Among adults (here too research has focused mainly on cisgender, different-sex couples), gender doesn’t affect situational couples’ violence, which takes place as conflicts escalate and is not typically about one partner controlling the other’s behavior.  There is a different kind of interpersonal violence, called intimate terrorism (Johnson 2008), which manifests as part of a pattern of dominance and control (this is the type of domestic violence that results in emergency room visits and stays in shelters), in which there is a notable gender difference in rates of perpetration (male &#x003E; female) (Hardesty and Ogolsky 2020; Johnson 2008).</para><para ele-id="1B1B2B3B">Regarding this, it is important to note that dating violence among adolescents tends to persist into adulthood and may be associated with negative health and relationship outcomes.  Thus, early intervention in this arena could have long-term benefits.</para><para ele-id="797130A4">Toward this end, pinpointing the causes of teen dating violence is likely to be of use.  As outlined above, consistent with Akers’ differential reinforcement theory, studies show that dating violence among teens is learned through differential associations (having peers who engage in this behavior, #1 above), role modelling (enacting behaviors similar to those of one’s peers, #1 above), and reinforcement (perceiving the behavior as rewarding, #2 above). However, results of research in this area suggests that there are some variations in terms of how this process plays out across different groups (e.g., adolescents who have good, versus poor, relations with their parents; teens with or without a history of exposure to violence within their family or dating violence; or whether teen dating violence is considered as acceptable or unacceptable within the geographical region in which one resides) and over time. Thus, it is important that practitioners seeking to reduce teen dating violence, as well as researchers, consider multiple personal and contextual factors when seeking to determine adolescents’ risks for engaging in this behavior (Pusch 2022).</para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F8633A"><emphasis role="bold">OVERVIEW AND EVALUATION OF STRUCTURAL AND LEARNING THEORIES</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F8633B">In general, a review of the empirical literature suggests that concepts that distinguish differential reinforcement theory from differential association theory (i.e., reinforcement and imitation) predict levels of deviance reasonably well. However, differential associations (having friends who engage in dating violence) are themselves strongly related to the commission of crimes and other acts of deviance, including stalking, across studies</para><para ele-id="36F8633C">In addition, research indicates that relationships with deviant peers, and susceptibility to their influence, are highest among adolescents with weak social bonds (e.g., low levels of attachment to their parents), which is what actually increases their risk for deviance. Social bonds themselves have few effects on delinquency independent of their relationship to individuals’ peer relations. Thus, socialization processes are necessary to explain the link between bonds to conventional society and deviant behavior (Erickson, Crosnoe, and Dornbusch 2000; Matsueda and Heimer 1987). This has led some sociological social psychologists to conclude that differential association theory is superior to social control theory when it comes to explaining crime and deviance (Matsueda and Heimer 1987).</para><para ele-id="36F8633D">Differential association is also a better predictor of deviant behavior than the strain theories reviewed toward the beginning of the chapter. Still, these structural models do explain some of the variation in individuals’ participation in deviant activities (Neff and Waite 2007; Vowell and Chen 2004).</para><para ele-id="02744CB1">The strength of structural perspectives, in general, is that they direct our attention to the root of the situational definitions that give rise to behaviors deemed as problematic (e.g., health care fraud). It is through the application of multiple theoretical perspectives, and levels of analysis, that sociological social psychologists gain the most complete understanding of the factors that give rise to various social behaviors, including deviance.</para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F8633F"><emphasis role="bold">THE CONSEQUENCES OF BEING CONSIDERED DEVIANT</emphasis></title><para ele-id="44BDB8A9">The previous sections focused on identifying the factors that put individuals at risk for deviance and the processes through which behaviors deemed non-normative by conventional society are acquired. Sociological social psychologists are also interested in what happens to people who are regarded by others as deviant.</para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F86341"><emphasis role="bold">The Symbolic Interactionist Approach</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F86342"><emphasis role="bold">Labeling theory</emphasis>, the dominant symbolic interactionist approach to the study of deviance, and arguably the dominant perspective on deviance within sociological social psychology, addresses this issue. Unlike research on the legal process or the functioning of the criminal justice system, labeling theorists focus on the social and psychological consequences of labeling at the micro level.</para><para ele-id="3D092C60">Given its symbolic interactionist roots, labeling theory (also called societal reaction theory) is firmly entrenched in Cooley’s looking-glass self and the notion that people’s self-concepts are shaped by how they are perceived and treated by others. Labeling theory arose largely out of the work of Becker (1963), discussed earlier in this chapter, as well as that of Lemert (1972), Kituse (1962), and Scheff (1966). The following section includes a synthesis of the concepts and ideas introduced by these individuals.</para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F86344"><emphasis role="italic">Main Premises of Labeling Theory</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F86345">Labeling theorists point out that everyone engages in deviant behavior. We all violate social norms at one time or another throughout the course of our lives.</para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F86346"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box Start&#x003E;</emphasis></title></section></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F86347"><emphasis role="bold">What Do You Think?</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F86348">Refer back to your score on the delinquency measure presented in Chapter 2 (Box 2.1). Although this is a relatively limited measure of individuals’ engagement in deviant behavior, you can still get a feel for just how common rule violations are. Did you score above a zero? If you did, do you consider yourself to be deviant? Do others see you as deviant? Why or why not? Would you expect your score to be higher if the measure had included other types of deviant acts? The fact that the average score on this measure and others like it is greater than zero (the mean for this index was 4.31) supports labeling theorists’ assumption that we all violate social norms at one time or another.</para><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F86349"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box End&#x003E;</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F8634A"><emphasis role="bold">Primary deviance</emphasis> is behavior in violation of social norms that is not defined by others within society as deviant. Whereas we all engage in deviant behavior (acts of primary deviance), only some of us are singled out and labeled as deviant by agents of social control (e.g., police officers, school administrators, or teachers). Sometimes these individuals don’t notice a norm violation, or if they do notice it, they don’t label the individual as deviant. They may excuse the norm violation or downplay its significance (e.g., he was having a bad day, it was unintentional, she’s under a lot of pressure, it’s just what kids do). Thus, most of us suffer no significant consequences as a result of our participation in deviant activities. We are basically regarded as a good person by others. We may make mistakes from time to time, but they are seen as transitory behaviors and not indicative of who we are.</para><para ele-id="36F8634B">This is not the case for the individual who is labeled as deviant. In this situation, behavior is seen as reflective of the individual. Others come to view the person as a deviant and see their behaviors and actions through the lens of this label. They are quick to notice behaviors that are consistent with the label that has been applied and see any rule violation as an indication that the label is correct.</para><para ele-id="36F8634C">They are also likely to engage in retrospective labeling. <emphasis role="bold">Retrospective labeling</emphasis> occurs when people reflect back on the past behaviors of the individual in question and interpret them in a manner that fits the new (deviant) label. For example, someone is labeled an “alcoholic.” Once this label is applied, her friends start talking about this party, and that party, during which her behavior was totally out of control due to her drinking problem. Insofar as no one thought twice about her drinking prior to the application of the label “alcoholic” retrospective labeling has occurred.</para><para ele-id="36F8634D">Being defined as deviant can have a profound effect on the self-concept of the individual who has been so labeled. Others begin to treat him differently than in the past, in a way that is consistent with the new label. They may not trust him or find him credible. If something goes wrong, they may readily place the blame on him. As a result of this kind of treatment, people who have been labeled as deviant are likely to start seeing themselves as a deviant.</para><para ele-id="36F8634E">This is facilitated by their isolation from nondeviant individuals. In extreme cases, people labeled as deviant are put in prisons or mental hospitals. In less extreme situations, they are simply avoided by people not identified as deviant because the latter individuals do not want to be associated with someone viewed in this negative fashion (i.e., they seek to avoid guilt by association).</para><para ele-id="36F8634F">Once isolation from normal, nondeviant society occurs, the only people a person labeled as deviant has left to interact with are those individuals who have been similarly labeled. Within this context, interaction between deviants, whose only shared characteristic may be their deviance, often results in the formation of what labeling theorists call a <emphasis role="bold">deviant subculture</emphasis>. Once a deviant subculture is formed based on group members’ common deviance, its norms tend to facilitate their participation in subsequent acts of deviance. Within the group, these behaviors are considered normative.</para><para ele-id="36F86350"><emphasis role="bold">Secondary deviance</emphasis> is deviant behavior that occurs after a person has been labeled. Whereas the cause of primary deviance is varied, the cause of secondary deviance is the labeling process itself. This is highly consistent with the Thomas theorem, a key premise of symbolic interactionism: when situations (or people) are defined in a particular way, regardless of the accuracy of this assessment, they become this. Although it is the label itself that produces the secondary deviance, these new behaviors are used to justify the initial labeling. As a result, labeling someone as deviant frequently gives rise to a self-fulfilling prophecy.</para><para ele-id="36F86351">Due, in part, to its controversial message—namely, that labeling someone is bad because it causes more deviance—labeling theory has had its critics over the years. However, many studies support its central propositions (Grattet 2011; Kavish, Mullins and Soto 2016; Link and Cullen 1990; Restivo and Lanier 2015).</para><para ele-id="36F86352">To summarize, a person is singled out and labeled as deviant. As a consequence of the fact that they have been labeled in this manner, this individual begins to see themself as deviant and interacts primarily with other people who have been similarly labeled.</para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F86353"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box Start&#x003E;</emphasis></title></section></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F86357"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box End&#x003E;</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F86358">This in turn leads the individual to commit further acts of deviance, which are taken as an indication that the initial label was accurate. This process is depicted in <link er-cited="true" linkend="F9.3" role="figure">Figure 9.3</link>.</para><para ele-id="3CB7D58F">You might be wondering why this happens. We can find our answer in the literature on the self-concept, reviewed in Chapter 7. People have a need for self-verification. Given this, they seek confirmation for the way that they see themselves, even when their identities or self-conceptions are negative. What makes this process especially problematic when it comes to deviance and labeling is that who gets labeled as deviant reflects broader patterns of inequality within society.</para><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F8635A"><emphasis role="italic">Status and Labeling</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F8635B">One of the authors once asked some of her students to rate various behaviors in terms of their degree of deviance. Overall, these individuals reported that murder, robbery, and rape are highly deviant acts, whereas speeding on the highway and taking two newspapers from a machine for the price of one are normative. (The students themselves generated the list of potentially deviant behaviors. Perhaps someone had recently engaged in paper stealing, which made it salient at the time at which the exercise was completed.) Whereas behaviors such as murder, robbery, and rape were consensually defined as deviant (i.e., there was agreement across students that these are deviant actions), some behaviors were defined as deviant by some students but not by others. These low-consensus behaviors included drinking alcohol, having multiple sex partners, and engaging in homosexual sex.</para><para ele-id="36F8635C">Surveys of the population’s attitudes toward various issues reveal a similar pattern. <link er-cited="true" linkend="T9.2" role="table">Table 9.2</link> includes data pertaining to two sexual behaviors, homosexuality and premarital sex, from the 2022 General Social Survey. GSS data are based on representative samples, so these figures are generalizable to the adult population in the United States.</para><para ele-id="36F8635D">As shown in <link er-cited="true" linkend="T9.2" role="table">Table 9.2</link><table orient="port" role="float" xml:id="T9.2"><label>TABLE 9.2</label><title ele-id="25C566BA"> Perceptions of Homosexuality and Premarital Sex Among U.S. Adults, 2022</title><tgroup cols="3"><thead><row er-header="true"><entry><tp ele-id="2102BCFF"/></entry><entry><tp ele-id="01194ACC"><emphasis role="bold">HOMOSEXUALITY WRONG</emphasis></tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="42572483"><emphasis role="bold">PREMARITAL SEX WRONG</emphasis></tp></entry></row></thead><tbody><row><entry><tp ele-id="121F7599">Total sample</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="5BEF256E">32%</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="007BC54E">18%</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="4F3BB705">N</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="40E90D0D">2261</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="47A67FDE">2344</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="41B74B3F">Education</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="2FCE8801"/></entry><entry><tp ele-id="21445938"/></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="11420793">Less than college</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="2D293C10">34%</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="21F20B5B">19%</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="6AF9566E">College graduate</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="7A75AD0C">27%</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="0F7CA591">17%</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="5B60BACE">Race</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="28EB614E"/></entry><entry><tp ele-id="6900B976"/></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="01BA7638">Minority</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="6955F25F">35%</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="214010EA">24%</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="6CB927AB">White</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="1633C69B">31%</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="5B56E8F8">16%</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="65AA4F72">Gender</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="51B6B236"/></entry><entry><tp ele-id="68DFADBD"/></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="2392EA10">Male</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="562A1E5C">34%</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="28DB9241">15%</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="67886C5B">Female</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="77B1DA3D">30%</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="7D0E47AC">22%</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="6E55D244">Age</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="6D70756F"/></entry><entry><tp ele-id="0E561166"/></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="15DCE334">40 and under</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="5604FE0F">19%</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="189359D2">13%</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="0705CDF6">Over 40</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="04BB093F">40%</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="165E762E">23%</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="302AAB33">Attend Religious Services</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="6FF68516"/></entry><entry><tp ele-id="5F5C9AB8"/></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="20D43CBE">Less than once a month</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="092B06E4">19%</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="52B3FF57">7%</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="60E43D08">Once a month or more</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="2F06360C">40%</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="1C54318B">22%</tp></entry></row></tbody></tgroup><tblfn ele-id="68E7C124"><emphasis role="italic">Source:</emphasis> Davern et al. (2023).</tblfn></table>, there is variation in how people view these behaviors. Not everyone agrees that these acts are deviant (or normative). For homosexual sex, for example, the split is about 32/68. Thirty-two percent of the 2022 GSS sample indicated that homosexuality is wrong, whereas the rest (the majority) of the survey participants (68%) reported that this behavior is sometimes or always acceptable.</para><para ele-id="36F8635E">Not surprisingly, the extent to which people perceive homosexual or premarital sex as deviant varies by status characteristics such as education, race, gender and age, and by religious participation. One exception to this general pattern has to do with the belief that premarital sex is wrong, which doesn’t vary by education (the group difference shown in the table is too small to say there is a relationship between education and beliefs about premarital sex among the U.S. population), and is, overall, relatively low, suggesting that this behavior is now considered acceptable by most U.S. adults.  Racial/ethnic differences in attitudes toward homosexuality are also relatively small.  Note, however, the sizable effect of religious participation on beliefs about premarital sex, as well as the large differences in views about homosexuality by age and by religious participation.</para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F86360"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box Start&#x003E;</emphasis></title></section></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F863AB"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box End&#x003E;</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F863AC">Despite the fact that definitions of deviance vary across individuals and groups within society, it is those individuals at the top of the stratification hierarchy who have the greatest ability to impose their definitions of deviance on others, and those individuals who lack socioeconomic resources who are the least able to resist these labels. Given this, labeling serves to control the behaviors of those at the bottom of the class structure.  Low-status members of society often run the risk of being formally labeled, and experiencing the consequences of this process, if they don’t conform to middle- and upper-class norms (Adler and Adler 2011).</para><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F863AD"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box Start&#x003E;</emphasis></title></section></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F863AE"><emphasis role="bold">What Do You Think?</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F863AF">People are also labeled as deviant when their behaviors do not conform to the expectations for someone of their gender or age. Discuss this with one or two of your classmates.</para><listitem><para ele-id="5A162F39">■ 	Come up with at least three behaviors that are considered deviant for males but not</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="21314DB0">females and at least three behaviors that are considered deviant for females but not for</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="36F863B0">males.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="6689737A">■ 	Give an example of two or three behaviors likely to be regarded as deviant because they</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="36F863B1">are age-inappropriate.</para></listitem></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F863B2"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box End&#x003E;</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F863B3">Even among people who commit the same transgressions, lower-class individuals are more likely than upper-class individuals, and racial and ethnic minorities are more likely than Whites, to be defined as deviant (Chambliss 1973; Link and Cullen 1990; Tapia 2011). Although the behaviors that result in a deviant label may vary across social contexts and with the whims of the labeler, labeling theorists emphasize the fact that it is people with certain social characteristics (in general, the socially disadvantaged) who are most likely to be labeled as deviant.</para><para ele-id="36F863B4">This is a serious issue, given the effects of labeling on individuals’ self-concepts and subsequent behaviors, which has been demonstrated in numerous studies (Bernburg 2019). While the negative spiral depicted in <link er-cited="true" linkend="F9.3" role="figure">Figure 9.3</link><figure xml:id="F9.3"><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/fig9.3.jpg"/></imageobject></mediaobject><label>FIGURE 9.3</label><caption><para ele-id="046AA989"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow"> </emphasis><emphasis role="highlight:yellow"><emphasis role="italic">Labeling as a Self-Fulfilling Prophecy</emphasis></emphasis></para></caption></figure> can be disrupted, it is not always easy to do so. Often there must be some major change in a labelee’s social environment for that individual to break out of this cycle.</para><para ele-id="09D5B16B">High school students making the transition to college are often happy they are going away to school because they recognize that it will give them a clean slate (Karp et al. 1998). Research on the consequence of labeling (Chambliss 1973) suggests that this kind of change in environment can be of great benefit to individuals who have been labeled as deviant. This is because it increases their likelihood of receiving interpersonal feedback that confirms nondeviant identities.</para><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F863B6"><emphasis role="italic">Deviant Selves</emphasis></title><para ele-id="7F00A35A">A deviant label, whatever its source, is often a stigmatizing one. A <emphasis role="bold">stigma</emphasis> is a trait or characteristic that causes one to lose prestige and social status in the eyes of others. As such, it results in an individual’s identity being discredited or spoiled (Goffman 1963). In order to avoid this, some individuals actively resist the labeling process. Resistance is most likely to occur when the individual labeled as deviant has power that is equal to or greater in magnitude to that of the labelers or is able to maintain relationships with others based on prior nondeviant identities.</para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F863B8">MANAGING STIGMA FROM A DRAMATURGICAL PERSPECTIVE</title><para ele-id="36F863B9">Goffman (1963) discusses a number of strategies that are used to minimize the effects of having a stigmatized identity. They all involve mechanisms for controlling the information that is given to others in order to reduce the likelihood that labeling will occur or its negative impact.</para><para ele-id="36F863BA">Some individuals opt to conceal their deviance in order to avoid potential negative consequences associated with labeling. <emphasis role="bold">Passing</emphasis> involves deliberately concealing the stigmatized characteristic. This technique is often employed by individuals who have a stigmatized attribute that they can readily hide (Goffman 1963). Historically, the term “passing” has been used to describe the behaviors of light-skinned African Americans who posed as Whites in order to avoid being the victims of racism. Today, some Muslim Americans use this identity management strategy.</para><para ele-id="36F863BB">Muslim Americans are in a precarious position in the post 9/11 era, in that many non-Muslims suspect them of hating Americans and of being potential terrorists. Although Muslim Americans are regarded as different, and sometimes as “scary,” by non-Muslims, they are often viewed negatively by other Muslims for being too American when they present themselves in ways that hide their Muslim status (e.g., by not wearing religious attire, such as the Hijab, and thereby “passing” as non-Muslim). Hence, what reduces stigma in one arena (interactions with non-Muslims) increases stigma in another (interactions with other Muslims).</para><para ele-id="36F863BC">Muslim Americans who try to reduce the stigma associated with their religion by minimizing its relevance to their interactions with non-Muslims (e.g., by trying not to appear too religious) also tend to be rejected by other Muslims (Casey 2017). This stigma management strategy is called <emphasis role="bold">covering</emphasis>. More generally, covering involves self-presentational strategies that minimize or keep the stigmatized characteristic from being the focal point of interactions, even though others are aware of its existence.</para><para ele-id="36F863BD">If an individual is not able to conceal or cover her stigma, or if attempts at doing so fail, she may openly disclose her deviant identity to others with the hope that they will accept her anyway. <emphasis role="bold">Disclosure</emphasis> might also be undertaken to alleviate the burden of living with a secret, with a goal toward casting the stigmatized identity in a positive light, or for preventative reasons. People may respond more favorably to a revelation about a person’s stigmatized identity when that information comes directly from that individual, instead of from someone else in the form of gossip (Goffman 1963).</para><para ele-id="36F863BE">Sometimes it is easier for individuals to disclose a stigmatized identity online than in person. For example, gay men who came out on Facebook reported that they felt less threatened by others’ negative reactions than they would have had they shared this information offline. On Facebook this kind of revelation reaches many individuals within a short time frame. While some of them might respond negatively to this disclosure, others are likely to be supportive (Owens 2017).</para><para ele-id="36F863BF">When it comes to the issue of stigma, individuals with an LGBTQ identity are in a unique situation. Unlike people with stigmatized identities who consistently experience hostility from others, responses to individuals with LGBTQ identities range from overt hostility to full acceptance. In addition, despite having to strategically manage their LGBTQ identity in the context of interactions characterized by negative attitudes and discriminatory actions, LGBT	Q young adults tend to reject cisgender heterosexuals’ frame of reference. This makes them more immune to stigma than other groups in this society (Orne 2013).</para><para ele-id="36F863C0">A final technique for managing identities deemed as undesirable, <emphasis role="bold">deviance disavowal</emphasis>, involves the open acknowledgment of stigma and attempts to present oneself in a positive light (Goffman 1963). The stigma associated with certain characteristics or behaviors can be managed this way within a group context or through some type of collective effort (Adler and Adler 2011; Herman 1995). There are many voluntary associations for individuals with stigmatized identities, or their allys, including the National Stuttering Project, Overeaters Anonymous, and Gamblers Anonymous. These groups are often organized to provide support for members, to give information and advice, to create opportunities for people to meet others who face similar issues.  Other organizations, like CHADD (Children and Adults with Attention Deficit and Hyperactivity Disorder) and PFLAG (which initially stood for Parents, Families and Friends of Lesbians and Gays but is now just PFLAG, for greater inclusivity and responsivity to the LGBTQ+ community) are geared toward advocacy and promoting social change, as well as serving as sources of social support.</para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F863C2">DEGRADATION CEREMONIES AND THE USE OF ACCOUNTS</title><para ele-id="36F863C3">When a member of society breaks the law and the violation is consensually regarded as serious (e.g., they commit murder, molest a child, or steal large sums of money), his actions often result in public shaming. If society were to allow this behavior to go unchecked, it would call into question our understanding of the world—who we are and what we believe in. Through denunciation rituals, people are able to express their collective moral outrage at the perpetrator’s behavior and validate their understandings of what is good and bad by ostracizing this individual from the group or society (Garfinkel 1956).</para><para ele-id="36F863C4"><emphasis role="bold">Degradation ceremonies</emphasis> are rituals designed to transform the identity of an individual and to expel him from membership in the group. Through a standard set of rituals, the identity of the individual is transformed into something dishonorable, disreputable, and deviant. The denouncer often suggests that the individual’s old identities are accidental and that it is the new one that is real. “What he is now is what, ‘after all,’ he was all along” (Garfinkel 1956:422).</para><para ele-id="36F863C5">Garfinkel (1956) discusses the conditions required for a successful degradation ceremony. For a degradation ceremony to be effective, people denouncing a perpetrator must complete the following steps.</para><orderedlist ele-id="D26CC3F"><listitem><para ele-id="79466BA4"><token>1.</token>They must make their claims public so that there is widespread recognition that the perpetrator is different or out of the ordinary.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="3841D9AD"><token>2.</token>They must get others to see the perpetrator and behavior as one and the same and thus reflective of a particular type.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="25A7D395"><token>3.</token>They must show this type to be devalued by contrasting it with its opposite, which is good and desirable.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="00425477"><token>4.</token>They must speak not as private individuals but as public figures who represent the community and their shared values.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="0B808868"><token>5.</token>They must show that they have a right to speak for the group.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="71F9409A"><token>6.</token>They must create distance by distinguishing themselves and others who are law-abiding as good and thus as different from the perpetrator, who is bad or immoral.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="36F863CC"><token>7.</token>Finally, they must ensure that the denounced person is ritually separated from the legitimate social order and made an outsider (Garfinkel 1956).</para></listitem></orderedlist><para ele-id="36F863CD">The criminal justice system itself (investigation, prosecution, and conviction of offenders) has elements of a degradation ceremony because it has the power to transform an individual’s identity from a law-abiding member of the community to a convicted felon (Benson 1985; Einstadter and Henry 2006). The “perp walk” is part of this process.</para><para ele-id="36F863CE">Degradation ceremonies also include the public outcry and denunciation that occur when a politician falls from grace because of a scandal or when an individual has been accused of a serious crime. Some good examples of individuals subject to highly public degradation ceremonies include Mark Sanford, a former governor of South Carolina, a vocal advocate of “family values,” who had an extramarital affair; actor and comedian Bill Cosby, for sexual abuse; Ghislaine Maxwell, for conspiring in the sexual abuse of minors; and Elizabeth Holmes, CEO of Theranos, a blood testing startup, for defrauding investors.</para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F863CF"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box Start&#x003E;</emphasis></title></section></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F863D1"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">[Insert Photo 9.4 here]</emphasis></title><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F863D3"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box End&#x003E;</emphasis></title></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F863D4"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box Start&#x003E;</emphasis></title></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F863D5"><emphasis role="bold">What Do You Think?</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F863D6">Can you think of any other highly visual degradation ceremonies recently represented on television, in newspapers, or on the Internet? If so, to what extent were the steps identified by Garfinkel evident in the condemners’ verbal statements and behaviors? How did you feel when you were exposed to this information? Did you feel anger or outrage at the perpetrator’s behavior? How did you feel about the perpetrator?</para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F863D7"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box End&#x003E;</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F863D8">The kind of public labeling associated with a degradation ceremony makes it difficult for its target to maintain a positive sense of self or convey to others that they are more than a criminal. However, criminals and others who have been publically labeled as deviant can minimize the effects of a degradation ceremony if they can undermine one or more of its required elements (Garfinkel 1956). For example, the continual and visible support of family members and friends may reduce the impact of a degradation ceremony on how a perpetrator is viewed by showing that she has identities other than that of “criminal.”</para><para ele-id="70B2CF7F">In addition, individuals convicted of crimes may account for their actions in an attempt to thwart their transformation from law-abiding citizen to criminal (Benson 1985). In this context, <emphasis role="bold">accounts</emphasis> are excuses or justifications for behavior that are designed to relieve individuals of responsibility for their actions (Scott and Lyman 1968). In the case of criminals, accounts are often used to deny that there was criminal intent, which demonstrates to others that they are not really deviant. Alternatively, a criminal may suggest that their crime represents only one behavior and is not indicative of who they are as a person, thereby negating the claims of the denouncers (Benson 1985).</para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F863DA">TECHNIQUES OF NEUTRALIZATION</title><para ele-id="36F863DB">Accounts may also be used to reduce the guilt and shame associated with the violation of society’s rules. According to Sykes and Matza (1957), most people who engage in deviant behavior have internalized the general norms of society and believe in the moral validity of the law. For this reason, they often develop rationalizations (accounts) about why it was okay to break the rules or violate the law in a particular situation. This neutralizes the negative affect associated with their deviant actions.</para><para ele-id="36F863DC"><emphasis role="bold">Techniques of neutralization</emphasis>, as identified by Sykes and Matza (1957), commonly take one or more of the following five forms:</para><orderedlist ele-id="F6680B9"><listitem><para ele-id="26F8F06B"><token>1.</token><emphasis role="bold">Denial of responsibility:</emphasis> The individual denies any responsibility for the behavior or its consequences by arguing that it was not his fault (e.g., due to peer pressure), that it was unintentional (e.g., an accident), or that it was beyond his control (e.g., due to biological drives or bad parenting). As illustrated in the previous section, this technique of neutralization is commonly used by criminals trying to counteract a degradation ritual.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="74B84AD1"><token>2.</token><emphasis role="bold">Denial of injury:</emphasis> The perpetrator argues that no one was hurt by her behavior. They may use particular language to cultivate this meaning. For example, instead of stealing a car, it was just “borrowed.” Or, in the case of white-collar crime, no individual was harmed when the perpetrator embezzled money from her company.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="1806518C"><token>3.</token><emphasis role="bold">Denial of victim:</emphasis> The violator transforms the victim into the one who is responsible for what happened to them (e.g., they got what they deserve) or into the wrongdoer (they shouldn’t have been out so late). Alternatively, the perpetrator may claim that there was no victim. In the case of employee theft, for instance, one might claim that the corporation is hardly affected by such a small loss.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="74364A5C"><token>4.</token><emphasis role="bold">Condemnation of condemners:</emphasis> The perpetrator shifts the focus away from his own acts to the motives and behaviors of the one who disapproves of the rule violation (e.g., teachers, the police, or his or her parents). He might argue that that person is a hypocrite, corrupt, or unfair (Sykes and Matza 1957). Police are out to get gang members, or federal regulators targeting particular industries are making crimes out of standard business practices in order to enhance their own careers. The argument about career enhancement is often made in regard to prosecutors when individuals convicted of white-collar crimes talk about their trials (Benson 1985). Similarly, claims of government incompetence have been used by corporations under federal investigation to shift attention away from their negligence or overtly criminal behavior. For example, Fiat Chrysler attributed the many deaths from explosions caused by fuel tank fires in their Jeep Grand Cherokee and Jeep Liberty models to the government and the poor quality of national data on auto safety, rather than to design flaws and their delay in recalling affected vehicles (Whyte 2016).</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="36F863E1"><token>5.</token><emphasis role="bold">Appeal to higher loyalties:</emphasis> The deviant individual sacrifices the demands or rules of the larger society for those of smaller groups to which she belongs. A gang member or a rogue police officer might justify behavior that is harmful to others by emphasizing how it benefits his friends or work colleagues. Similarly, someone might rationalize breaking the law by stealing food if the food is for their family (Sykes and Matza 1957).</para></listitem></orderedlist><para ele-id="5FB4C845">Each of these techniques of neutralization serves to redefine the situation so that the behavior in question is viewed as acceptable. Thus, techniques of neutralization enable individuals to engage in deviant acts without serious damage to their self-image or feelings of guilt or shame. They can maintain a positive self-concept despite their participation in activities that others within society view negatively. See Box 9.2 for an application of techniques of neutralization to student cheating.</para><para ele-id="36F863E5"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box Start&#x003E;</emphasis> <emphasis role="highlight:green">problems with box—were unable to fix (see 2</emphasis><emphasis role="highlight:green"><superscript>nd</superscript></emphasis><emphasis role="highlight:green"> edition for format)</emphasis></para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F863E6"><emphasis role="bold">Box 9.2 College Student Cheating</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F863E7">Cheating in college is a pervasive problem among American students. For some time, surveys have indicated that the majority of college students cheat on tests, homework, and assignments (Klein et al. 2007; Rettinger and Kramer 2009) and the COVID-19 pandemic increased this behavior (Ives and Cazan 2023; Jenkins et al. 2022). Two classic studies within the social psychological literature provide detailed illustrations of how students rationalize this behavior using the techniques of neutralization specified by Sykes and Matza (1957). By reducing the shame and guilt associated with cheating, these kinds of accounts may be used to negate the effects of some of the informal and internal controls you identified in the exercise earlier in the chapter.</para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F863E8"><emphasis role="bold">Denial of Responsibility</emphasis></title><blockquote><para ele-id="36F863EA">“Here at . . . you must cheat to stay alive. There’s so much work and the quality of materials from which to learn, books, professors, is so bad there is no other choice.” (McCabe 1992)</para></blockquote><listitem><para ele-id="36F863EC">“Everyone has test files in Fraternities, etc. If you don’t, you’re at a great disadvantage.” (McCabe 1992)</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="16603BA7">“I was taking the test and someone in another part of the room was telling someone else an answer. I heard it and just couldn’t not write it down.” (Labeff et al. 1990)</para></listitem></section></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F863F1"><emphasis role="bold">Denial of Injury</emphasis></title><listitem><para ele-id="36F863F3">“These grades aren’t worth much therefore my copying doesn’t mean very much. I am ashamed, but I’d probably do it the same way again.” (McCabe 1992)</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="2272229E">“If I extend the time on a take home it is because I feel everyone does and the teacher kind of expects it. No one gets hurt.” (McCabe 1992)</para></listitem></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F863F6"><emphasis role="bold">Condemnation of Condemners</emphasis></title><listitem><para ele-id="36F863FA">“It is known by students that certain professors are more lenient to certain types, e.g., blonds or hockey players.” (McCabe 1992)</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="4727BC01">“Major exams are very important to your grade and it seems that the majority of instructors make up the exams to try and trick you instead of testing your knowledge.” (Labeff et al. 1990)</para></listitem></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F863FD"><emphasis role="bold">Appeal to Higher Loyalties</emphasis></title><listitem><para ele-id="36F863FF">“I only cheated because my friend had been sick and she needed help . . . it (cheating) wouldn’t have happened any other time.” (Labeff et al. 1990)</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="36F86401">“I personally have never cheated. I’ve had friends who asked for help so I let them see my test. Maybe some would consider that to be cheating.” (Labeff et al. 1990)</para></listitem><para ele-id="6C9ED8CE">Although the two studies of student cheating that yielded the results just described were conducted over 30 years ago, there is no reason to think that these findings would not apply to current college students. A later analysis (Brent and Atkisson 2011) shows that students still use the same techniques of neutralization to rationalize cheating, although detailed statements by students accounting for their actions were not provided in this study.</para><para ele-id="36F86402">Moreover, research on cheating during the COVID-19 pandemic (Walsh et al. 2021) revealed rationalizations (neutralizations) on the part of science students that are remarkably similar in terms of their underlying themes to those previously identified within the literature (e.g., students in the COVID study reported cheating because they were “overwhelmed” and “losing motivation” due to the pandemic, and because it was so easy to do when they were taking exams online--ways of denying responsibility--or because classes were “structured poorly,” which is in the “condemning the condemners” category).</para><para ele-id="36F86403">How do you feel about this issue?  Is cheating OK? Professors, school administrators, and some students think it’s not. It gives an unfair advantage to individuals who break the rules and is likely to reinforce the notion that unethical behaviors are acceptable for instrumental purposes. What might college and university professors and administrators do to minimize student cheating in the post-COVID world?</para><section role="H2"><title ele-id="6C999244"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box End&#x003E;</emphasis></title></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="2A649939"><emphasis role="bold">Deviation From Norms Within Groups</emphasis></title><para ele-id="7056F5F2">Up to this point, we have said little about the manner in which deviance is studied within the group processes and structure face of social psychology. Given its focus, social psychologists aligned with this orientation have not studied deviance with the same degree of depth as those working within the other two faces of sociological social psychology (social structure and personality and symbolic interactionism). They have, however, discussed the extent to which some of the processes identified earlier in the chapter apply to interaction in small groups organized for the purpose of accomplishing some goal.</para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F86405"><emphasis role="italic">Status Violation Theory</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F86406">Within the GPS tradition, <emphasis role="bold">status violation theory</emphasis> (Wagner 1988), an expansion of status characteristics theory, focuses on how members of task-oriented groups respond to behaviors deemed inappropriate given an actor’s status characteristics (e.g., gender, race/ethnicity, or level of task-related expertise). Insofar as group members consistently behave in a non-normative manner (e.g., a low-status member challenges high-status group members on multiple occasions), status violation theory predicts that they will be accorded a new status, that of “deviant.” In combination with their other status characteristics, this deviant status is expected to influence other group members’ expectations, and evaluations, of the actor. Because the status of deviant is regarded as negative, this process should inhibit the extent to which individuals defined in this manner are given opportunities to contribute to the groups’ outcomes and lead to more negative evaluations of their task performance.</para><para ele-id="36F86407">Most people are aware of the potential for labeling within task groups, which increases their likelihood of behaving appropriately. Thus, within the context of small-group encounters, the labeling process may serve a social control function similar to that observed in other social settings (Wagner 1988). Albeit largely untested, the results of a recent experiment (Youngreen and Moore 2008) offer some support for status violation theory.</para><para ele-id="27637A14">The effects of deviant identities that are not themselves constructed during the group interaction (e.g., deviant identities that individuals bring with them to the group encounter, such as “criminal” or “drug addict”) on task-group behavior have not been systematically examined by sociological social psychologists working within the group processes and structures tradition. However, it is likely that they would function much like other diffuse status characteristics, including gender and race/ethnicity.</para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F86409"><emphasis role="italic">Other Perspectives</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F8640A">Like social psychologists who have studied deviance as a status characteristic, whose work we described in the previous section, social identity theorists have focused on how deviance emerges within groups and on how other group members treat deviants. In general, these studies suggest that group members who engage in non-normative behaviors are marginalized, unless their deviance makes others look upon the group more favorably (Hogg and Reid 2006).</para><para ele-id="66DC29C4">Within the social exchange framework, it is assumed that behaving in a deviant manner with regard to the process of exchange itself (e.g., withholding rewards from an exchange partner in a manner perceived as inappropriate) will reduce the rewards received in future exchanges with a given actor. Failing to meet others’ expectations may also reduce an individual’s desirability as an exchange partner, especially in the case of reciprocal exchange relations, such as marriage or friendship. Given their desire to maximize rewards, and minimize losses, it is assumed that people will behave in accordance with prevailing group norms insofar as it is in their interest to do so.</para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F8640C"><emphasis role="bold">CHAPTER SUMMARY</emphasis></title><para ele-id="678D7016">Sociological social psychologists have sought to identify the structural conditions that give rise to deviance, how deviant behaviors are learned, and the social experiences of individuals considered deviant. The theories governing their analyses, and the faces of sociological social psychology they represent, are summarized in <link er-cited="false" linkend="T9.3" role="table">Table 9.3</link>. As illustrated throughout the chapter, these theories direct our attention to prevailing societal patterns and to the micro-level interactions they generate.  They also emphasize how social inequality at the macro level creates conditions conductive to crime or is reflected in who is defined as deviant when they violate social norms, which serves as a source of social control and has profound consequences for the content of their self-concepts and subsequent behaviors.   Because definitions of deviance are socially constructed and both reflect and reproduce macro-level inequalities between social groups, understanding the causes and consequences of this type of behavior provides us with important information about how society operates.</para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F8640E"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box Start&#x003E;</emphasis></title></section></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="658ADEE5"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box End&#x003E;</emphasis></title><section role="H2"><title ele-id="0B1AC8EE"><emphasis role="bold">Key Points to Know</emphasis></title><itemizedlist ele-id="47126F6" mark="disc"><listitem><para ele-id="3CA98038"><emphasis role="bold">Deviance is socially constructed, which means that no behavior is in and of itself deviant</emphasis>. Behaviors are defined as deviant only in relation to prevailing social norms. Whether an act is considered deviant also depends upon the situation within which it occurs and the status characteristics of the actor.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="60D3DE67"><emphasis role="bold">Deviance is a topic of interest to sociological social psychologists because it is a regular occurrence and it reflects the concerns of their home discipline—the manner in which inequality at the macro level influences individuals’ everyday social experiences</emphasis>. The study of deviance is still somewhat controversial, albeit less so than in the past, because it directs our attention to behaviors that make some people uncomfortable.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="73589476"><emphasis role="bold">Class and race do not have strong and consistent effects on delinquency</emphasis>. Most racial/ethnic differences in crime among adults are due to socioeconomic factors. Thus, they are really class differences. Although males have higher rates of deviance than females in both adolescence and adulthood, the gender gap in crime among adults appears to be decreasing.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="16DEB2E4"><emphasis role="bold">Structural theories emphasize the relationship between social class and crime</emphasis>. Research on the causes of deviance suggest that people engage in financially motivated crimes when they are socialized to aspire to culturally defined goals but are denied the legitimate means for obtaining these ends. Other kinds of strain (e.g., discrimination or the loss of something or someone who is valued) also result in deviant behavior.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="3E3957D7"><emphasis role="bold">Social control theory attributes delinquency to weak social bonds</emphasis>. Extensions of this theory within the social structure and personality face of social psychology have investigated the link between social structure and social bonding. A number of these studies have focused on gender, but social bonds do not explain males’ higher levels of delinquency than their female counterparts.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="1FD75E92"><emphasis role="bold">At the micro level, symbolic interactionists focus on the social processes through which deviance is learned. Two theories of deviance (differential association theory and differential reinforcement theory) share this concern, but the research they have generated is largely quantitative in orientation</emphasis>. Research showing a strong effect of adolescents’ peer affiliations on their levels of delinquency supports the main premises of these theories.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="08881524"><emphasis role="bold">Labeling theory is the dominant symbolic interactionist approach to the study of deviance. Rather than focusing on the causes of deviance, labeling theorists direct their attention to the effects of status characteristics, in particular social class and race/ethnicity, on who gets labeled and on the consequences of the labeling process</emphasis>.  As such, they emphasize how social inequality within society affects, and is reproduced, through labelling processes.  Being labeled as deviant has negative effects on individuals’ self-concepts and subsequent behaviors, and the self-fulfilling prophecy it generates may be difficult to disrupt without some major change in the target’s social environment.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="2EF615B7"><emphasis role="bold">Degradation ceremonies involve the public shaming of criminals who have engaged in behaviors consensually regarded as immoral</emphasis>. These rituals provide a forum for law-abiding individuals to collectively express their outrage and serve to remind us of what it means to be good and moral.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="702CB751"><emphasis role="bold">Individuals use a variety of strategies to manage deviant selves</emphasis>. They may minimize the stigma associated with a deviant identity by hiding or selectively revealing information about their identity or by affiliating with others with similar characteristics for social or political reasons. People may also neutralize their deviant behaviors through the use of accounts that enable them to deny responsibility for their actions, deny that their actions are harmful to others, or view their behaviors as appropriate given their group loyalties or the actions of others.</para></listitem><listitem><para ele-id="36F86448"><emphasis role="bold">Status violation theory suggests that individuals who violate task-group norms will be accorded the status of “deviant,” which is likely to generate negative performance expectations and evaluations</emphasis>. Although there is some empirical support for this perspective, there is little research on how deviant identities developed prior to joining the group influence members’ perceptions and behaviors. Given its focus, there are fewer systematic analyses of deviance within the group processes and structure tradition than there are within the other two faces of sociological social psychology.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F86449"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box Start&#x003E;</emphasis></title><table orient="port" role="inline"><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry><tp ele-id="59FA1185"><emphasis role="bold">Terms and Concepts for Review</emphasis></tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="697EFA53"/></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="4F541BBC">Accounts</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="68B8E35F">General strain theory</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="10AE5395">Anomie</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="0AC943D0">Informal control</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="09AEA2A2">Appeal to higher loyalties</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="0BA1E604">Innovators</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="293BE506">Condemnation of condemners</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="79CDF117">Internal control</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="5D78E4C4">Covering</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="01ED08DA">Labelling theory</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="2E62BFA3">Crime</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="1D5EA077">Laws</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="4BF175DC">Degradation ceremonies</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="094363EC">Mores</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="365DBC24">Denial of injury</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="45078BF7">Passing</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="3C0D0CB8">Denial of responsibility</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="5BADCD41">Primary deviance</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="4EA6E014">Denial of victim</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="72EF344E">Retrospective labelling</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="22D2C6E9">Deviance</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="0B258D79">Secondary deviance</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="480B51A6">Deviance disavowel</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="75482604">Social bond</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="61F8D221">Deviant subculture</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="21A22CC2">Social control theory</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="3D31DBB0">Differential associations</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="3CC5D3B7">Status violation theory</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="3DB01E09">Differential association theory</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="287D2194">Stigma</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="420F2354">Differential reinforcement theory</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="59CB2C39">Strain theory</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="7BBBBC0C">Disclosure</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="6C2A150A">Techniques of neutralization</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="6F532BCE">Folkways</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="64C479EA">White-collar crime</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="3D26F591">Formal control</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="1AA79C69"/></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></section></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F86474"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box End&#x003E;</emphasis></title><section role="H2"><title ele-id="36F86475"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box Start&#x003E;</emphasis></title></section></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F86476"><emphasis role="bold">Questions for Review and Reflection</emphasis></title><para ele-id="36F86477">1.	What do sociological social psychologists mean when they say that deviance is socially constructed? What factors influence whether an act, or an individual, is defined as deviant?</para><para ele-id="36F86478">2.	Apply at least three of the theories of deviance discussed in this chapter to the topic of college student drinking. Which theory offers the best explanation of this behavior? Discuss the utility of combining theoretical perspectives when studying deviance.</para><para ele-id="36F86479">3.	Consider a high school student who regularly skips class to hang out with friends in the local park. What factors are likely to influence whether this student is labeled as deviant by teachers and school administrators? What is likely to happen to this individual if labeling occurs?</para><para ele-id="36F8647A">4.	Reality shows are quite popular these days. Some of these programs focus on revealing what people’s lives are like after they are released from prison (e.g., shows such as <emphasis role="italic">Love after Lockup or</emphasis> <emphasis role="italic">Life After Lockup</emphasis>) or they receive treatment for an addiction (e.g., <emphasis role="italic">Mama June:  From Not to Hot</emphasis>), whereas others provide an inside look into the lives of individuals with characteristics or experiences that make them of interest to viewers (e.g., <emphasis role="italic">My 600-lb Life</emphasis> or <emphasis role="italic">90 Day Fiancé</emphasis>, which does not adhere to social norms pertaining to the trajectory of romantic relationships in this society). Why are these television programs so popular? Please make reference to the literature on deviant selves when responding to this question. (If you aren’t familiar with any of the programs listed, look them up online. You’ll get the gist of their focus.)</para><para ele-id="05733F76">5.  Choose one of the theories of deviance described in the chapter and discuss how it addresses issues related to social inequality. Use this theory to explain one or more of your experiences or the experience/s of someone you know personally or have read or heard about. Assess the extent to which this application of the theory you selected drew your attention to processes or issues you hadn’t previously considered.</para></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="36F8647B"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">&#x003C;Box End&#x003E;</emphasis></title><section role="H2"><title ele-id="34570C93"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow"><emphasis role="italic">Source</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">: Becker (1963), Kituse (1962), Lemert (1972), and Scheff (1966).</emphasis></title><para ele-id="0C4C96CB"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">[Photo 9.11 and 9.12 side to side here]</emphasis></para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="714195A7"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow"><emphasis role="italic">Source</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">: Lizabeth Crawford.</emphasis></title><para ele-id="1C2B4CC0"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">PHOTO 9.2 Although social norms pertaining to tattoos have changed, some people within this society would regard these individuals as deviant. Who do you think would be considered most deviant? Why?</emphasis></para></section><section role="H2"><title ele-id="699BEAB9"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow"><emphasis role="italic">Source</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">: (1) Craftvision, (2) cecciangiochi/Getty Images , (3) Mike Kemp/Getty Images.</emphasis></title></section></section><section role="H1"><title ele-id="20540AC9"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">[Insert Photo 9.3 Here]</emphasis></title><section role="H2"><title ele-id="532E8B1F"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">Source:  Ljupco Smokovski / Shutterstock</emphasis></title></section></section><title ele-id="6E21B291"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">PHOTO 9.4 The “perp walk” is often part of a public degradation ritual.</emphasis></title><section role="H2"><title ele-id="433E94D1"><emphasis role="highlight:yellow"><emphasis role="italic">Source</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">: </emphasis><emphasis role="highlight:yellow"><emphasis role="italic">New York Daily</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis role="highlight:yellow"> </emphasis><emphasis role="highlight:yellow"><emphasis role="italic">News</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis role="highlight:yellow">/Getty Images.</emphasis></title><table orient="port" role="float" xml:id="T9"><label>Table 9.</label><title ele-id="1DFF0675"> 3 Theories of Deviance Summary</title><tgroup cols="4"><thead><row er-header="true"><entry><tp ele-id="5BA77884"><emphasis role="bold">THEORY</emphasis></tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="42C73AC4"><emphasis role="bold">FACE OF SOCIAL PSYCHOLOGY</emphasis></tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="702650BC"><emphasis role="bold">PRIMARY RESEARCH QUESTION</emphasis></tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="08F42CD8"><emphasis role="bold">EMPIRICAL SUPPORT</emphasis></tp></entry></row></thead><tbody><row><entry><tp ele-id="4A461A3A">Structural strain (Merton)</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="7E68EFB8">Social structure and personality</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="1AC15F15">What causes economically motivated crimes?</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="07695810">Moderate</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="6CD876FA">General strain (Agnew)</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="47593541">Social structure and personality</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="445CCFC3">What causes crime and other forms of deviance?</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="379B3AD1">Strong</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="0E1FBE59">Social control (Hirschi)</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="72D61A98">Social structure and personality (extensions of theory)</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="1AC73740">Why aren’t more people deviant more of the time?</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="679F59A8">Moderate</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="054CA4D5">Symbolic Interactionist (e.g., Becker)</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="685C3E2B">Symbolic interactionist</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="35C9D9B4">How is deviance learned?</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="1BB19F51">Strong</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="25CEF936">Differential association (Sutherland)</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="103B54A0">Symbolic interactionist</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="4F2A46F4">How is deviance learned?</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="23F0EDC3">Strong</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="1EA3CD66">Differential reinforcement (Akers)</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="0D0B87AB">Psychological (social learning)/symbolic interactionist</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="0E6054C9">How is deviance learned through patterns of reinforcement and punishment?</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="20A15633">Strong</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="5C049206">Labeling (many theorists)</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="3662E345">Symbolic structures</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="0AB5A7E9">What happens to people labeled as deviant?</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="75F740F3">Strong</tp></entry></row><row><entry><tp ele-id="3B1EC335">Status violation (Wagner)</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="26339AFA">Group processes and structures</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="24CD30AE">What happens to people labeled as deviant in task groups?</tp></entry><entry><tp ele-id="6ED13E1A">Some</tp></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></section></chapter></book>